<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Cuesmes</location>, <date>between about Tuesday, 22 and Thursday, 24 June 1880.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">It’s with some reluctance that I write to you</stress>, not having done so for so long, and that
            for many a reason. Up to a certain point you’ve become a stranger to me, and I too am
            one to you, perhaps more than you think; perhaps it would be better for us not to go on
            this way. It’s possible that I wouldn’t even have written to you now if it weren’t that
            I’m under the obligation, the necessity, of writing to you. If, I say, you yourself
            hadn’t imposed that necessity. I learned at Etten that you had sent fifty francs for me;
            well, I accepted them. Certainly reluctantly, certainly with a <stress reason="family">rather melancholy
            feeling</stress>, but I’m in some sort of impasse or mess; what else can one do? And so it’s to
            thank you for it that I’m writing to you.</p>
      <p>As you may perhaps know, I’m back in the Borinage; my father spoke to me of staying in
            the vicinity of Etten instead; I said no, and I believe I acted thus for the best.
            Without wishing to, I’ve more or less become some sort of impossible and suspect
            character in the family, in any event, somebody who isn’t trusted, so how, then, could I
            be useful to anybody in any way? That’s why, first of all, so I’m inclined to believe,
            it is beneficial and the best and most reasonable position to take, for me to go away
            and to remain at a proper distance, as if I didn’t exist. What moulting is to birds, the
            time when they change their feathers, that’s adversity or misfortune, hard times, for us
            human beings. One may remain in this period of moulting, one may also come out of it
            renewed, but it’s not to be done in public, however; <bad_health>it’s scarcely entertaining, it’s
            not cheerful, so it’s a matter of making oneself scarce</bad_health>. Well, so be it. Now, although
            it may be a thing of rather demoralizing difficulty to regain the trust of an entire
            family perhaps not entirely devoid of prejudices and other similarly honourable and
            fashionable qualities, nevertheless, I’m not utterly without hope that little by little,
            slowly and surely, a good understanding may be re-established with this person and that.
            In the first place, then, I’d like to see this good understanding, to say no more,
            re-established between my father and me, and I would also be very keen that it be
            re-established between the two of us. Good understanding is infinitely better than
            misunderstanding. I must now bore you with certain abstract things; however, I’d like
            you to listen to them patiently.</p>
      <p>I, for one, am a man of passions, capable of and liable to do rather foolish things for
            which I sometimes feel rather sorry. I do often find myself speaking or acting somewhat
            too quickly when it would be better to wait more patiently. I think that other people
            may also sometimes do similar foolish things. Now that being so, what’s to be done, must
            one consider oneself a dangerous man, incapable of anything at all? I don’t think so.
            But it’s a matter of trying by every means to turn even these passions to good account.
            For example, to name one passion among others, I have a more or less irresistible
            passion for books, and I have a need continually to educate myself, to study, if you
            like, precisely as I need to eat my bread. You’ll be able to understand that yourself.
            When I was in different surroundings, in surroundings of paintings and works of art, you
            well know that I then took a violent passion for those surroundings that went as far as
            enthusiasm. And I don’t repent it, and now, far from the country again, I often feel
            homesick for the country of paintings. </p>
      <p>You may perhaps clearly remember that I knew very well (and it may well be that I still
            know) what Rembrandt was or what Millet was, or Jules Dupré or Delacroix or Millais or
            M. Maris. Good — now I no longer have those surroundings — however, that something
            that’s called soul, they claim that it never dies and that it lives for ever and seeks
            for ever and for ever and for evermore. So instead of succumbing to homesickness, I said
            to myself, one’s country or native land is everywhere. So instead of giving way to
            despair, I took the way of active melancholy as long as I had strength for activity, or
            in other words, I preferred the melancholy that hopes and aspires and searches to the
            one that despairs, mournful and stagnant. So I studied the books I had to hand rather
            seriously, such as the Bible and Michelet’s La révolution Française, and then last
            winter, Shakespeare and a little V. Hugo and Dickens and Beecher Stowe, and then
            recently Aeschylus, and then several other less classic authors, several good minor
            masters. You well know that one who is ranked among the minor (?) masters is called
            Fabritius or Bida. Now the man who is absorbed in all that is sometimes shocking, to
            others, and without wishing to, offends to a greater or lesser degree against certain
            forms and customs and social conventions. It’s a pity, though, when people take that in
            bad part. For example, you well know that I’ve frequently neglected my appearance, I
            admit it, and I admit that it’s shocking. But look, <stress reason="money">money troubles and poverty have
            something to do with it</stress>, and then <stress reason="environment">a profound discouragement also has something to do
            with it</stress>, and then it’s sometimes a good means of ensuring for oneself the solitude
            needed to be able to go somewhat more deeply into this or that field of study with which
            one is preoccupied. One very necessary field of study is medicine; there’s hardly a man
            who doesn’t try to know a little bit about it, who doesn’t try to understand at least
            what it’s about, and here I still don’t know anything at all about it. But all of that
            absorbs you, but all of that preoccupies you, but all of that makes you dream, ponder,
            think. And now for as much as 5 years, perhaps, I don’t know exactly, I’ve been more or
            less without a position, wandering hither and thither. Now you say, from such and such a
            time you’ve been going downhill, you’ve faded away, you’ve done nothing. Is that
            entirely true? It’s true that sometimes I’ve earned my crust of bread, sometimes some
            friend has given me it as a favour; I’ve lived as best I could, better or worse, as
            things went; it’s true that <stress reason="friendship">I’ve lost several people’s trust</stress>, it’s true that my
            <stress reason="money">financial affairs are in a sorry state</stress>, it’s true that the future’s not a little dark,
            it’s true that I could have done better, it’s true that just in terms of earning my
            living I’ve lost time, it’s true that my studies themselves are in a rather sorry and
            disheartening state, and that I lack more, infinitely more than I have. But is that
            called going downhill, and is that called doing nothing? Perhaps you’ll say, but why
            didn’t you continue as people would have wished you to continue, along the university
            road? </p>
      <p>To that I’d say only this, it costs too much and then, <stress reason="environment">that future was no better than the
            present one</stress>, on the road that I’m on. <bad_health>But on the road that I’m on I must continue; if I
            do nothing, if I don’t study, if I don’t keep on trying, then I’m lost, then woe betide
            me.</bad_health> That’s how I see this, to keep on, keep on, that’s what’s needed. But what’s your
            ultimate goal, you’ll say. That goal will become clearer, will take shape slowly and
            surely, as the croquis becomes a sketch and the sketch a painting, as one works more
            seriously, as one digs deeper into the originally vague idea, the first fugitive,
            passing thought, unless it becomes firm. You must know that it’s the same with
            evangelists as with artists. There’s an old, often detestable, tyrannical academic
            school, the abomination of desolation, in fact — men having, so to speak, a suit of
            armour, a steel breastplate of prejudices and conventions. Those men, when they’re in
            charge of things, have positions at their disposal, and by a system of circumlocution
            seek to support their protégés, and to exclude the natural man from among them. Their
            God is like the God of Shakespeare’s drunkard, Falstaff, ‘the inside of a church’; in
            truth, certain evangelical (???) gentlemen find themselves, by a strange conjunction
            (perhaps they themselves, if they were capable of human feeling, would be somewhat
            surprised) find themselves holding the very same point of view as the drunkard in
            spiritual matters. But there’s little fear that their blindness will ever turn into
            clear-sightedness on the subject. This state of affairs has its bad side for someone who
            doesn’t agree with all that, and who protests against it with all his heart and with all
            his soul and with all the indignation of which he is capable. Myself, I respect
            academicians who are not like those academicians, but the respectable ones are more
            thinly scattered than one would believe at first glance. <stress reason="career">Now one of the reasons why I’m
            now without a position, why I’ve been without a position for years</stress>, it’s quite simply
            because I have different ideas from these gentlemen who give positions to individuals
            who think like them. It’s not a simple matter of appearance, as people have
            hypocritically held it against me, it’s something more serious than that, I assure
            you.</p>
      <p>Why am I telling you all this? — not to grumble, not to apologize for things in which I
            may be more or less wrong, but quite simply to tell you this: on your last visit, last
            summer, when we walked together near the disused mine they call La Sorcière, you
            reminded me that there was a time when we also walked together near the old canal and
            mill of Rijswijk, and then, you said, we were in agreement on many things, but, you
            added — you’ve really changed since then, you’re not the same any more. Well, that’s not
            quite how it is; what has changed is that my life was less difficult then and my future
            less dark, but as far as my inner self, as far as my way of seeing and thinking are
            concerned, they haven’t changed. But if in fact there were a change, it’s that now I
            think and I believe and I love more seriously what then, too, I already thought, I
            believed and I loved. So it would be a misunderstanding if you were to persist in
            believing that, for example, I would be less warm now towards Rembrandt or Millet or
            Delacroix, or whomever or whatever, because it’s the opposite. But you see, there are
            several things that are to be believed and to be loved; there’s something of Rembrandt
            in Shakespeare and something of Correggio or Sarto in Michelet, and something of
            Delacroix in V. Hugo, and in Beecher Stowe there’s something of Ary Scheffer. And in
            Bunyan there’s something of M. Maris or of Millet, a reality more real than reality, so
            to speak, but you have to know how to read him; then there are extraordinary things in
            him, and he knows how to say inexpressible things; and then there’s something of
            Rembrandt in the Gospels or of the Gospels in Rembrandt, as you wish, it comes to more
            or less the same, provided that one understands it rightly, without trying to twist it
            in the wrong direction, and if one bears in mind the equivalents of the comparisons,
            which make no claim to diminish the merits of the original figures. If now you can
            forgive a man for going more deeply into paintings, admit also that the love of books is
            as holy as that of Rembrandt, and I even think that the two complement each other. I
            really love the portrait of a man by Fabritius, which one day, also while taking a walk
            together, we looked at for a long time in the Haarlem museum. Good, but I love Dickens’s
            ‘Richard Cartone’ in his Paris et Londres en 1793 just as much, and I could show you
            other strangely vivid figures in yet other books, with more or less striking
            resemblance. And I think that Kent, a man in Shakespeare’s King Lear, is just as noble
            and distinguished a character as any figure of Th. de Keyser, although Kent and King
            Lear are supposed to have lived a long time earlier. To put it no higher, my God, how
            beautiful that is. Shakespeare — who is as mysterious as he? — his language and his way
            of doing things are surely the equal of any brush trembling with fever and emotion. But
            one has to learn to read, as one has to learn to see and learn to live. So you mustn’t
            think that I’m rejecting this or that; in my unbelief I’m a believer, in a way, and
            though having changed I am the same, and my torment is none other than this, what could
            I be good for, couldn’t I serve and be useful in some way, how could I come to know more
            thoroughly, and go more deeply into this subject or that? Do you see, <stress reason="environment">it continually
            torments me</stress>, and then you feel a prisoner in penury, excluded from participating in this
            work or that, and such and such necessary things are beyond your reach. Because of that,
            you’re not without melancholy, and you feel emptiness where there could be friendship
            and high and serious affections, and you feel a terrible discouragement gnawing at your
            psychic energy itself, and fate seems able to put a barrier against the instincts for
            affection, or a tide of revulsion that overcomes you. And then you say, How long, O
            Lord! Well, then, what can I say; does what goes on inside show on the outside? Someone
            has a great fire in his soul and nobody ever comes to warm themselves at it, and
            passers-by see nothing but a little smoke at the top of the chimney and then go on their
            way. So now what are we to do, keep this fire alive inside, have salt in ourselves, wait
            patiently, but with how much impatience, await the hour, I say, when whoever wants to,
            will come and sit down there, will stay there, for all I know? May whoever believes in
            God await the hour, which will come sooner or later. Now for the moment all my affairs
            are going badly, so it would seem, and that has been so for a not so inconsiderable
            period of time, and it may stay that way for a future of longer or shorter duration, but
            it may be that after everything has seemed to go wrong, it may then all go better. I’m
            not counting on it, perhaps it won’t happen, but supposing there were to come some
            change for the better, I would count that as so much gained; I’d be pleased about it,
            I’d say, well then, there you are, there was something, after all. </p>
      <p>But you’ll say, though, you’re an execrable creature since you have impossible ideas on
            religion and childish scruples of conscience. If I have any that are impossible or
            childish, may I be freed from them; I’d like nothing better. But here’s where I am on
            this subject, more or less. You’ll find in Souvestre’s Le philosophe sous les toits how
            a man of the people, a simple workman, very wretched, if you will, imagined his mother
            country, ‘Perhaps you have never thought about what your mother country is, he
            continued, putting a hand on my shoulder; it’s everything that surrounds you, everything
            that raised and nourished you, everything you have loved. This countryside that you see,
            these houses, these trees, these young girls, laughing as they pass by over there,
            that’s your mother country! The laws that protect you, the bread that is the reward of
            your labour, the words that you exchange, the joy and sadness that come to you from the
            men and the things among which you live, that’s your mother country! The little room
            where you once used to see your mother, the memories she left you, the earth in which
            she rests, that’s your mother country! You see it, you breathe it everywhere! Just
            think, your rights and your duties, your attachments and your needs, your memories and
            your gratitude, put all that together under a single name, and that name will be your
            mother country.’ Now likewise, everything in men and in their works that is truly good,
            and beautiful with an inner moral, spiritual and sublime beauty, I think that that comes
            from God, and that everything that is bad and wicked in the works of men and in men,
            that’s not from God, and God doesn’t find it good, either. But without intending it, I’m
            always inclined to believe that the best way of knowing God is to love a great deal.
            Love that friend, that person, that thing, whatever you like, you’ll be on the right
            path to knowing more thoroughly, afterwards; that’s what I say to myself. But you must
            love with a high, serious intimate sympathy, with a will, with intelligence, and you
            must always seek to know more thoroughly, better, and more. That leads to God, that
            leads to unshakeable faith. Someone, to give an example, will love Rembrandt, but
            seriously, that man will know there is a God, he’ll believe firmly in Him. Someone will
            make a deep study of the history of the French Revolution — he will not be an
            unbeliever, he will see that in great things, too, there is a sovereign power that
            manifests itself. Someone will have attended, for a time only, the free course at the
            great university of poverty, and will have paid attention to the things he sees with his
            eyes and hears with his ears, and will have thought about it; he too, will come to
            believe, and will perhaps learn more about it than he could say. Try to understand the
            last word of what the great artists, the serious masters, say in their masterpieces;
            there will be God in it. Someone has written or said it in a book, someone in a
            painting. And quite simply read the Bible, and the Gospels, because that will give you
            something to think about, and a great deal to think about and everything to think about,
            well then, think about this great deal, think about this everything, it raises your
            thinking above the ordinary level, despite yourself. Since we know how to read, let’s
            read, then! Now, afterwards, we may well at times be a little absent-minded, a little
            dreamy; there are those who become a little too absent-minded, a little too dreamy; that
            happens to me, perhaps, but it’s my own fault. And after all, who knows, wasn’t there
            some cause; it was for this or that reason that I was absorbed, preoccupied, anxious,
            but you get over that. The dreamer sometimes falls into a pit, but they say that
            afterwards he comes up out of it again. </p>
      <p>And the absent-minded man, at times he too has his presence of mind, as if in
            compensation. He’s sometimes a character who has his raison d’être for one reason or
            another which one doesn’t always see right away, or which one forgets through being
            absent-minded, mostly unintentionally. One who has been rolling along for ages as if
            tossed on a stormy sea arrives at his destination at last; one who has seemed good for
            nothing and incapable of filling any position, any role, finds one in the end, and,
            active and capable of action, shows himself entirely different from what he had seemed
            at first sight. I’m writing you somewhat at random whatever comes into my pen; I would
            be very happy if you could somehow see in me something other than some sort of idler.
            Because there are idlers and idlers, who form a contrast. There’s the one who’s an idler
            through laziness and weakness of character, through the baseness of his nature; you may,
            if you think fit, take me for such a one. Then there’s the other idler, the idler truly
            despite himself, who is gnawed inwardly by a great desire for action, who does nothing
            because he finds it impossible to do anything since he’s imprisoned in something, so to
            speak, because he doesn’t have what he would need to be productive, because the
            inevitability of circumstances is reducing him to this point. Such a person doesn’t
            always know himself what he could do, but he feels by instinct, I’m good for something,
            even so! I feel I have a raison d’être! I know that I could be a quite different man!
            For what then could I be of use, for what could I serve! There’s something within me, so
            what is it! That’s an entirely different idler; you may, if you think fit, take me for
            such a one. In the springtime a bird in a cage knows very well that there’s something
            he’d be good for; he feels very clearly that there’s something to be done but he can’t
            do it; what it is he can’t clearly remember, and he has vague ideas and says to himself,
            ‘the others are building their nests and making their little ones and raising the
            brood’, and he bangs his head against the bars of his cage. And then the cage stays
            there and the bird is mad with suffering. ‘Look, there’s an idler’, says another passing
            bird — that fellow’s a sort of man of leisure. And yet the prisoner lives and doesn’t
            die; nothing of what’s going on within shows outside, he’s in good health, he’s rather
            cheerful in the sunshine. But then comes the season of migration. A bout of melancholy —
            but, say the children who look after him, he’s got everything that he needs in his cage,
            after all — but he looks at the sky outside, heavy with storm clouds, and within himself
            feels a rebellion against fate. I’m in a cage, I’m in a cage, and so I lack for nothing,
            you fools! Me, I have everything I need! Ah, for pity’s sake, freedom, to be a bird like
            other birds! </p>
      <p>An idle man like that resembles an idle bird like that. And it’s often impossible for men
            to do anything, prisoners in I don’t know what kind of horrible, horrible, very horrible
            cage. There is also, I know, release, belated release. A reputation ruined rightly or
            wrongly, poverty, inevitability of circumstances, misfortune; that creates prisoners.
            You may not always be able to say what it is that confines, that immures, that seems to
            bury, and yet you feel I know not what bars, I know not what gates — walls. Is all that
            imaginary, a fantasy? I don’t think so; and then you ask yourself, Dear God, is this for
            long, is this for ever, is this for eternity? You know, what makes the prison disappear
            is every deep, serious attachment. To be friends, to be brothers, to love; that opens
            the prison through sovereign power, through a most powerful spell. But he who doesn’t
            have that remains in death. But where sympathy springs up again, life springs up again.
            And the prison is sometimes called Prejudice, misunderstanding, fatal ignorance of this
            or that, mistrust, false shame. But to speak of something else, if I’ve come down in the
            world, you, on the other hand, have gone up. And while I may have lost friendships, you
            have won them. That’s what I’m happy about, I say it in truth, and that will always make
            me glad. If you were not very serious and not very profound, I might fear that it won’t
            last, but since I think you are very serious and very profound, I’m inclined to believe
            that it will last. </p>
      <p>But if it became possible for you to see in me something other than an idler of the bad
            kind, I would be very pleased about that. And if I could ever do something for you, be
            useful to you in some way, know that I am at your service. Since I’ve accepted what you
            gave me, you could equally ask me for something if I could be of service to you in some
            way or another; it would make me happy and I would consider it a sign of trust. We’re
            quite distant from one another, and in certain respects we may have different ways of
            seeing, but nevertheless, sometime or some day one of us might be able to be of use to
            the other. For today, I shake your hand, thanking you again for the kindness you’ve
            shown me. Now if you’d like to write to me one of these days, my address is care of C.
            Decrucq, rue du Pavillon 8, Cuesmes, near Mons, and know that by writing you’ll do me
            good. </p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
