<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>Sometimes, I fear, you throw a book away because it’s too realistic. Have compassion and
        patience with this letter, and read it through, despite its severity.
        <location>Etten</location>, <date>on or about Friday, 23 December 1881.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation> My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>As I already wrote to you from The Hague, I have some things to discuss with you now that
            I’m back here. It’s not without emotion that I look back on my trip to The Hague. When I
            went to see M.<stress reason="career"> my heart was beating rather hard</stress>, because I was thinking to myself, will
            he too try and fob me off or will I find something else here? And well, what I
            experienced with him was that he instructed and encouraged me in all manner of kind and
            practical ways. Though not merely by always approving of everything I did or said, on
            the contrary. But if he tells me, this or that isn’t good, then it’s because he’s saying
            at the same time ‘but try it this way or that way’, and that’s entirely different from
            criticizing for the sake of criticizing. Or if someone says ‘you’re ill with this or
            that’, that doesn’t help much, but if someone says ‘do this or that and you’ll get
            better’, and his advice isn’t deceit, look, that’s the real thing, and – and – it
            naturally helps. Now I’ve come from him with a few <work origin="existing" stage="finished">painted studies</work> and a couple of
            <work origin="existing" stage="finished">watercolours</work>. Of course they aren’t masterpieces and yet I truly believe there’s
            something sound and real in them, more at least than in what I’ve made up to now. And so
            I now consider myself to be at the beginning of the beginning of making something
            serious. And because I now have a few more technical resources at my disposal, namely
            paint and brush, all things are made new again, as it were.</p>
      <p> But – now we have to put it into practice. And the first thing is that I must find a
            room large enough to be able to take a sufficient distance. Mauve just said to me, when
            he saw my studies, ‘you’re too close to your model’. In many cases this makes it next to
            impossible to take the necessary measurements for the proportions, so this is certainly
            one of the first things I have to watch out for. Now I must arrange to rent a large room
            somewhere, be it a room or a shed. And that won’t be so terribly expensive. A labourer’s
            cottage in these parts costs 30 guilders a year to rent, so it seems to me that a room
            twice as large as that in a labourer’s cottage would cost something like 60
            guilders.</p>
      <p> And that isn’t insurmountable. I’ve already seen a shed, though it has too many
            inconveniences, especially in the winter. But I’d be able to work there, at least when
            the weather is milder. And here in Brabant, moreover, there are models to be found, I
            believe, not only in Etten but also in other villages, if difficulties were to arise
            here.</p>
      <p> Still, though I love Brabant very much, I also have a feeling for other figures than the
            Brabant peasant types. Scheveningen, for example, I again found unspeakably beautiful.
            But after all I’m here, and it would very probably be cheaper to stay here. However,
            I’ve definitely promised M. that I’ll do my utmost to find a good studio, and now I must
            also use better paint and better paper.</p>
      <p>Nevertheless, Ingres paper is excellent for studies and scratches. And it’s much cheaper
            to make sketchbooks in all formats from it oneself than to buy ready-made sketchbooks. I
            still have a small supply of Ingres paper, but you’d be doing me a big favour if you
            could send some more of the same kind when you send back those studies. Not pure white,
            though, but the colour of unbleached linen, no cold shades. </p>
      <p>Theo, what a great thing tone and colour are! And anyone who doesn’t acquire a feeling
            for it, how far removed from life he will remain! M. has taught me to see so many things
            I didn’t see before, and when I have the opportunity I’ll try and tell you about what
            he’s told me, because perhaps there are still one or two things that you don’t see
            properly either. Anyway, we’ll talk about artistic matters sometime, I hope.</p>
      <p> And you can’t imagine <unstress reason="money">the feeling of relief I’m beginning to get when I think of the
            things M. said to me about earning money</unstress>. Just think of how I’ve slogged away for years,
            always in a kind of false position. And now, now there’s a glimmer of real light.</p>
      <p> I do wish that you could see the <work origin="existing" stage="finished">two watercolours</work> I’ve brought with me, because you
            would see that they’re watercolours just like any other watercolours. There may be many
            imperfections in them, be that as it may, I’d be the first to say that I’m still very
            dissatisfied with them, and yet, it’s different from what I’ve done up to now, and it
            looks fresher and sounder. All the same, it must become much fresher and sounder, but
            one can’t do what one wants all at once. It comes gradually. I need those couple of
            drawings myself, however, to compare with what I’ll be making here, because I have to do
            them at least as well as what I did at M.’s.</p>
      <p>But even though Mauve tells me that if I continue to slog away here for a couple of
            months and then go back to him again in March, for instance, I’ll then be able to make
            saleable drawings on a regular basis, I’m nevertheless going through a rather difficult
            period. The cost of models, studio, drawing and painting materials are multiplying, and
            there are no earnings as yet.</p>
      <p>Admittedly, Pa said that I needn’t be afraid of the inevitable expense, and Pa is pleased
            with what M. himself said to him, and also with the studies and drawings I brought back.
            But I do find it utterly, utterly wretched that Pa should suffer by it. Of course we
            hope that things will turn out well later, but still, it weighs heavily on my heart.
            Because since I’ve been here Pa really hasn’t profited from me, and more than once he’s
            bought a coat or trousers, for example, which I’d actually rather not have had, even
            though I really needed it, but Pa shouldn’t suffer by it. The more so if the coat and
            trousers in question don’t fit and are only half or not at all what I need. Anyway,
            still more petty vexations of human life. And, as I’ve told you before, I find it
            absolutely terrible not to be free at all. Because even though Pa doesn’t ask me to
            account for literally every penny, still, he always knows exactly how much I spend and
            what I spend it on. And now, although I don’t necessarily have any secrets, I don’t
            really like people being able to look at my cards. Even my secrets aren’t necessarily
            secrets to those for whom I feel sympathy.</p>
      <p> But Pa isn’t the kind of man for whom I can feel what I feel for you, for example, or
            for Mauve. I really do love Pa and Ma, but it’s a very different feeling from what I
            feel for you or Mauve. Pa cannot empathize or sympathize with me, and I cannot settle in
            to Pa and Ma’s routine, it’s too constricting for me — it would suffocate me.</p>
      <p>Whenever I tell Pa anything, it’s all just idle talk to him, and certainly no less so to
            Ma, and I also find Pa and Ma’s sermons and ideas about God, people, morality, virtue,
            almost complete nonsense. I also read the Bible sometimes, just as I sometimes read
            Michelet or Balzac or Eliot, but I see completely different things in the Bible than Pa
            sees, and I can’t agree at all with what Pa makes of it in his petty, academic way.
            Since the Rev. Ten Kate translated Goethe’s Faust, Pa and Ma have read that book,
            because now that a clergyman has translated it, it can’t be all that immoral (??? what
            is that?). Yet they don’t see anything in it but the catastrophic consequences of an
            unchaste love.</p>
      <p>And they certainly understand the Bible just as little. Take Mauve, for instance, when he
            reads something deep he doesn’t immediately say, that man means this or that. Because
            poetry is so deep and intangible that one can’t simply define it all systematically, but
            Mauve has a refined sensibility and, you see, I find that sensibility to be worth so
            much more than definition and criticism. And oh, when I read, and I actually don’t read
            so much and even then, only one-and-a-half writers, a couple of men whom I accidentally
            found, then I do so because they look at things more broadly and milder and with more
            love than I do, and are better acquainted with reality, and because I can learn
            something from them. But all that drivel about good and evil, morality and immorality, I
            actually care so little about it. For truly, it’s impossible for me always to know what
            is good, what is evil, what is moral, what is immoral. Morality or immorality
            coincidentally brings me to K.V. Ah! I’d written to you that it was beginning to seem
            less and less like eating strawberries in the spring. Well, that is of course true. If I
            should lapse into repetition, forgive me, I don’t know if I’ve already written to you
            about what happened to me in Amsterdam. I went there thinking, who knows whether the no,
            nay, never isn’t thawing, it’s such mild weather. And so one evening I was making my way
            along Keizersgracht, looking for the house, and indeed found it. And naturally I rang
            the bell and heard that the family were still at table. But then I heard that I could
            come in all the same. And there they were, including Jan, the very learned professor,
            all of them except Kee. And they all still had a plate in front of them, and there
            wasn’t a plate too many. This small detail caught my eye. They wanted to make me think
            that Kee wasn’t there, and had taken away her plate, but I knew she was there, I thought
            it so much like a comedy or game. </p>
      <p>After a while I asked (after chatting a bit and greeting everyone), But where’s Kee? Then
            J.P.S. repeated my question, saying to his wife, Mother, where’s Kee? And the missus
            said, Kee’s out. And for the time being I didn’t pursue the matter but talked a bit with
            the professor about the exhibition at Arti he’d just seen. Well, the professor
            disappeared and little Jan Vos disappeared, and J.P.S. and the wife of the same and
            yours truly remained alone and got ourselves into position. J.P.S., as priest and
            Father, started to speak and said he’d been on the point of sending a certain letter to
            yours truly and he would read that letter aloud. However, first I asked again,
            interrupting His Hon. or the Rev., Where’s Kee? (Because I knew she was in town.) Then
            J.P.S. said, Kee left the house as soon as she heard you were here. Well, I know some
            things about her, and I must say that I didn’t know then and still don’t know with
            certainty whether her coldness and rudeness is a good or bad sign. This much I do know,
            that I’ve never seen her so seemingly or actually cool and callous and rude towards
            anyone but me. So I didn’t say much in reply and remained dead calm. Let me hear that
            letter, I said, or not, I don’t really care either way. Then came the epistle. The
            writing was reverent and very learned and so there wasn’t really anything in it, though
            it did seem to say that I was being requested to stop corresponding and I was given the
            advice to make vigorous attempts to forget the matter. At last the reading of the letter
            was over. I felt exactly as though I were hearing the minister in the church, after some
            raising and lowering of his voice, saying amen – it left me just as cold as an ordinary
            sermon. And then I began, and I said as calmly and politely as I could, well yes, I’ve
            already heard this line of reasoning quite often, but now go on – and after that? But
            then J.P.S. looked up... he even seemed to be somewhat amazed at my not being completely
            convinced that we’d reached the extreme limit of the human capacity to think and feel.
            There was, according to him, no ‘after that’ possible. We went on like this, and once in
            a while Aunt M. put in a very Jesuitical word, and I got quite warm and finally lost my
            temper. And J.P.S. lost his temper too, as much as a clergyman can lose his temper. And
            even though he didn’t exactly say ‘God damn you’, anyone other than a clergyman in
            J.P.S.’s mood would have expressed himself that way. But you know that I love both Pa
            and J.P.S. in my own way, despite the fact that I truly loathe their system, and I
            changed tack a bit and gave and took a bit, so that at the end of the evening they said
            to me that if I wanted to stay at their house I could. Then I said, thank you. If Kee
            walks out of the house when I come, then I don’t think it’s the right moment to stay
            here, I’m going to my boarding-house. And then they asked, where are you staying? I
            said, I don’t know yet, and then Uncle and Aunt insisted on bringing me themselves to a
            good, inexpensive boarding-house. And heavens, those two old dears came with me through
            the cold, misty, muddy streets, and truly, they showed me a very good boarding-house and
            very inexpensive. I didn’t want them to come at all but they insisted on showing me.</p>
      <p> And, you see, I thought that rather humane of them and it calmed me down somewhat. I
            stayed in Amsterdam two more days and talked with J.P.S. again, but I didn’t see Kee,
            she made herself scarce each time. And I said that they ought to know that although they
            wanted me to consider the matter over and done with, I couldn’t bring myself to do it.
            And they continued to reply firmly: ‘Later on I would understand it better’. Now and
            then I also saw the professor again, and I have to say he wasn’t so bad, but – but – but
            – what else can I say about that gentleman? I said I hoped that he might fall in love
            one day. Voilà. Can professors fall in love? Do clergymen know what love is?</p>
      <p> I recently read Michelet, La femme, la religion et le prêtre. Books like that are full
            of reality, yet what is more real than reality itself, and what has more life than life
            itself? And we who do our best to live, why don’t we live even more!</p>
      <p> I walked around aimlessly those three days in Amsterdam, I felt damned miserable, and
            that half-kindness on the part of Uncle and Aunt and all those arguments, I found them
            so tedious. Until I finally began to find myself tedious and said to myself: would you
            like to become despondent again? And then I said to myself, Don’t let yourself be
            overwhelmed. And so it was on a Sunday morning that I last went to see J.P.S. and said
            to him, Listen, my dear Uncle, if Kee Vos were an angel she would be too lofty for me,
            and I don’t think that I would stay in love with an angel. Were she a devil, I wouldn’t
            want to have anything to do with her. In the present case, I see in her a real woman,
            with womanly passions and whims, and I love her dearly, that’s just the way it is, and
            I’m glad of it. So long as she doesn’t become an angel or a devil, the case in question
            isn’t over. And J.P.S. couldn’t say very much to that, and spoke himself of womanly
            passions, I’m not really sure what he said about them, and then J.P.S. left for the
            church. No wonder one becomes hardened and numb there, I know that from my own
            experience. And so as far as your brother in question is concerned, he didn’t want to
            let himself be overwhelmed. But that didn’t alter the fact that he felt overwhelmed,
            that he felt as though he had been leaning against a cold, hard, whitewashed church wall
            for too long. Oh well, should I tell you more, old chap? It’s rather daring to remain a
            realist, but Theo, Theo, you too are a realist, oh bear with my realism! I told you,
            even my secrets aren’t necessarily secrets. Well, I won’t take those words back, think
            of me as you will, and whether you approve or disapprove of what I did is less
            important.</p>
      <p> I’ll continue – from Amsterdam I went to Haarlem and sat very agreeably with our dear
            sister Willemien, and I took a walk with her, and in the evening I went to The Hague,
            and I landed up at M.’s around seven o’clock. </p>
      <p>And I said: listen M., you were supposed to come to Etten to try and initiate me, more or
            less, into the mysteries of the palette. But I’ve been thinking that that wouldn’t be
            possible in only a couple of days, so now I’ve come to you and if you approve I’ll stay
            four weeks or so, or six weeks or so, or as long or as short as you like, and we’ll just
            have to see what we can do. It’s extremely impertinent of me to demand so much of you,
            but in short, I’m under a great deal of pressure. Well, Mauve said, do you have anything
            with you? Certainly, here are a couple of studies, and he said many good things about
            them, far too many, at the same time voicing some criticism, far too little. Well, and
            the next day we set up a still life and he began by saying, This is how you should hold
            your palette. And since then I’ve made a few painted studies and after that two
            watercolours.</p>
      <p> This is a summary of my work, but there’s more to life than working with the hands and
            the head.</p>
      <p>I remained chilled to the marrow, that’s to say to the marrow of my soul by that
            aforementioned imaginary or not-imaginary church wall. And I didn’t want to let myself
            be overwhelmed by that deadening feeling, I said. Then I thought to myself, I’d like to
            be with a woman, I can’t live without love, without a woman. I wouldn’t care a fig for
            life if there wasn’t something infinite, something deep, something real. But, I said to
            myself in reply: you say ‘She and no other’ and should you go to a woman? But surely
            that’s unreasonable, surely that goes against logic? <stress reason="love">And my answer to that was, Who’s
            the master, logic or I</stress>? Is logic there for me or am I there for logic, and is there no
            reason and no understanding in my unreasonableness or my stupidity? And whether I act
            rightly or wrongly, I can’t do otherwise, that damned wall is too cold for me, I’ll look
            for a woman, I cannot, I will not, I may not live without love. I’m only human, and a
            human with passions at that, I need a woman or I’ll freeze or turn to stone, or anyway
            be overwhelmed. In the circumstances, however, I struggled much within myself, and in
            that struggle some things concerning physical powers and health gained the upper hand,
            things which I believe and know more or less through bitter experience. One doesn’t live
            too long without a woman without going unpunished. And I don’t think that what some call
            God and others the supreme being and others nature is unreasonable and merciless, and,
            in a word, I came to the conclusion, I must see whether I can’t find a woman. And
            heavens, I didn’t look so very far. I found a woman, <stress reason="love">by no means young, by no means
            pretty, with nothing special about her, if you will</stress>. But perhaps you’re rather curious.
            She was fairly big and strongly built, she didn’t exactly have lady’s hands like K.V.
            but those of a woman who works hard. But she was not coarse and not common, and had
            something very feminine about her. She slightly resembled a nice figure by Chardin or
            Frère or possibly Jan Steen. Anyhow, that which the French call ‘a working woman’. She’d
            had a great many cares, one could see that, and life had given her a drubbing, <stress reason="love">oh
            nothing distinguished, nothing exceptional, nothing out of the ordinary</stress>.</p>
      <p> Every woman, at every age, if she loves and if she is kind, can give a man not the
            infinite of the moment but the moment of the infinite.</p>
      <p> Theo, I find such infinite charm in that je ne sais quoi of withering, that drubbed by
            life quality. Ah! <unstress reason="love">I found her to have a charm</unstress>, I couldn’t help seeing in her something
            by Feyen-Perrin, by Perugino. Look, I’m not exactly as innocent as a greenhorn, let
            alone a child in the cradle. It’s not the first time I couldn’t resist that feeling of
            affection, particularly love and affection for those women whom the clergymen damn so
            and superciliously despise and condemn from the pulpit. I don’t damn them, I don’t
            condemn them, I don’t despise them. Look, I’m almost thirty years old, and do you think
            I’ve never felt the need for love?</p>
      <p>K.V. is older than I am, she also has love behind her, but she’s all the dearer to me for
            that very reason. She’s not ignorant, but neither am I. If she wants to subsist on an
            old love and if she wants to know nothing of new ones, that’s her business, but the more
            she perseveres in that and avoids me, the more I can’t just stifle my energy and
            strength of mind for her sake. No, I don’t want that, I love her, but I don’t want to
            freeze and deaden my mind for her sake. And the stimulus, the spark of fire we need,
            that is love and I don’t exactly mean mystic love.</p>
      <p>That woman didn’t cheat me – oh, anyone who thinks all those sisters are swindlers is so
            wrong and understands so little.</p>
      <p> That woman was <unstress reason="love">good to me, very good, very decent, very sweet</unstress>. In what way? That I won’t
            repeat even to my brother Theo, because I strongly suspect my brother Theo of having
            experienced something of this himself now and then. The better for him.</p>
      <p>Did we spend a lot together? No, because I didn’t have much and I said to her, listen,
            you and I don’t have to get drunk to feel something for one another, just pocket what I
            can afford. And I wish I could have afforded more, because she was worth it.</p>
      <p>And we talked about all kinds of things, about her life, about her cares, about her
            destitution, about her health, and I had a livelier conversation with her than with my
            learned professorial cousin Jan Stricker, for instance.</p>
      <p>I’ve actually told you these things because I hope you’ll see that even though I perhaps
            have some feeling, I don’t want to be sentimental in a senseless way. That, no matter
            what, I want to preserve some warmth of life and keep my mind clear and my body healthy
            in order to work. And that I understand my love for K.V. to be such that for her sake I
            don’t want to set about my work despondently or let myself get upset.</p>
      <p> You’ll understand that, you who wrote in your letter something about the matter of
            health. You talk of having been not quite healthy a while back, it’s very good you’re
            trying to get yourself straightened out.</p>
      <p> Clergymen call us sinners, conceived and born in sin. Bah! I think that damned nonsense.
            Is it a sin to love, to need love, not to be able to do without love? I consider a life
            without love a sinful condition and an immoral condition. If there’s anything I regret,
           <stress reason="environment"> it’s that for a time I let mystical and theological profundities seduce me into
            withdrawing too much inside myself</stress>. I’ve gradually stopped doing that. If you wake up in
            the morning and you’re not alone and you see in the twilight a fellow human being, it
            makes the world so much more agreeable. Much more agreeable than the edifying journals
            and whitewashed church walls the clergymen are in love with. It was a sober, simple
            little room she lived in, with a subdued, grey tone because of the plain wallpaper and
            yet as warm as a painting by Chardin, a wooden floor with a mat and an old piece of
            dark-red carpet, an ordinary kitchen stove, a chest of drawers, a large, perfectly
            simple bed, in short, a real working woman’s interior. She had to do the washing the
            next day. Just right, very good, I would have found her just as charming in a purple
            jacket and a black skirt as now in a brown or red-grey frock. And she was no longer
            young, perhaps the same age as K.V., and she had a child, yes, life had given her a
            drubbing and her youth was gone. Gone? – there is no such thing as an old woman. Ah, and
            she was strong and healthy – and yet not rough, not common. Those who value distinction
            so very highly, can they always tell what is distinguished? Heavens! People sometimes
            look for it high and low when it’s close by, as I do too now and then.</p>
      <p>I’m glad that I did what I did, because I think that nothing in the world should keep me
            from my work or cause me to lose my good spirits. When I think of K.V., I still say ‘she
            and no other’, and I think exactly the same as I did last summer about ‘meanwhile
            looking for another lass’. But it’s not only recently that I’ve grown fond of those
            women who are condemned and despised and cursed by clergymen, my love for them is even
            somewhat older than my love for Kee Vos. Whenever I walked down the street – often all
            alone and at loose ends, half sick and destitute, with no money in my pocket – I looked
            at them and envied the people who could go off with her, and I felt as though those poor
            girls were my sisters, as far as our circumstances and experience of life were
            concerned. And, you see, <stress reason="environment">that feeling is old and deeply rooted in me</stress>. Even as a boy I
            sometimes looked up with endless sympathy and respect into a half-withered female face
            on which it was written, as it were: life and reality have given me a drubbing. But my
            feelings for K.V. are completely new and something entirely different. Without knowing
            it, <stress reason="love">she’s in a kind of prison</stress>. She’s also poor and can’t do everything she wants, and
            you see, she has a kind of resignation and I think that the Jesuitisms of clergymen and
            devout ladies often make more of an impression on her than on me, Jesuitisms that no
            longer impress me for the very reason that I’ve learned a few tricks. But she adheres to
            them and couldn’t bear it if the system of resignation and sin and God and whatnot
            appeared to be a conceit. And I don’t think it occurs to her that perhaps God only
            actually begins when we say those words with which Multatuli closes his prayer of an
            unbeliever: ‘O God, there is no God’.</p>
      <p> Look, I find the clergymen’s God as dead as a doornail. But does that make me an
            atheist? The clergymen think me one – be that as it may – but look, I love, and how
            could I feel love if I myself weren’t alive and others weren’t alive? And if we live,
            there’s something wondrous about it. Call it God or human nature or what you will, but
            there’s a certain something that I can’t define in a system, even though it’s very much
            alive and real, and you see, for me it’s God or just as good as God. Look, if I must die
            in due course in one way or another, fine, what would there be to keep me alive?
            Wouldn’t it be the thought of love (moral or immoral love, what do I know about it?).
            And heavens, I love Kee Vos for a thousand reasons, but precisely because I believe in
            life and in something real I no longer become distracted as I used to when I had
            thoughts about God and religion that were more or less similar to those Kee Vos now
            appears to have. I won’t give her up, but that inner crisis she’s perhaps going through
            will take time, and I have the patience for it, and nothing she says or does makes me
            angry. But as long as she goes on being attached to the past and clinging to it, I must
            work and keep my mind clear for painting and drawing and business. So I did what I did,
            from a need for warmth of life and with an eye to health. I’m also telling you these
            things so that you don’t get the idea again that I’m in a melancholy or distracted,
            pensive mood. On the contrary, I’m usually pottering about with and thinking about
            paint, making watercolours, looking for a studio &amp;c. &amp;c. Old chap, if only I
            could find a suitable studio. </p>
      <p>Well, my letter has grown long, but anyway. I sometimes wish that the three months
            between now and going back to M. were already over, but such as they’ll be, they’ll
            bring some good. Write to me, though, now and then. Are you coming again in the
            winter?</p>
      <p> And listen, renting a studio &amp;c., I’ll do it or I won’t, depending on what Mauve
            thinks of it. I’m sending him the floor plan as agreed, and perhaps he’ll come and have
            a look himself if necessary. But Pa has to stay out of it. Pa isn’t the right man to get
            mixed up in artistic matters. And the less I have to do with Pa in business matters, the
            better I’ll get along with Pa. But I have to be free and independent in many things,
            that goes without saying.</p>
      <p>I sometimes shudder at the thought of K.V., seeing her dwelling on the past and clinging
            to old, dead notions. There’s something fatal about it, and oh, she’d be none the worse
            for changing her mind. I think it quite possible that her reaction will come, there’s so
            much in her that’s healthy and lively. And so in March I’ll go to The Hague again and –
            and – again to Amsterdam. But when I left Amsterdam this time, I said to myself, under
            no circumstances should you become melancholy and let yourself be overwhelmed so that
            your work suffers, especially now that it’s beginning to progress. Eating strawberries
            in the spring, yes, that’s part of life, but it’s only a short part of the year and it’s
            still a long way off.</p>
      <p>And you should envy me because of this or that? Oh no, old chap, because what I’m seeking
            can be found by all, by you perhaps sooner than by me. And oh, I’m so backward and
            narrow-minded about so many things, if only I knew exactly why and what I should do to
            improve. But unfortunately we often don’t see the beams in our own eye. Do write to me
            soon, and you’ll just have to separate the wheat from the chaff in my letters, if
            sometimes there’s something good in them, something true, so much the better, but of
            course there’s much in them that’s wrong, more or less, or perhaps exaggerated, without
            my always being aware of it. I’m truly no scholar and am so extremely ignorant, oh, like
            many others and even more than others, but I can’t gauge that myself, and I can gauge
            others even less than I can gauge myself, and am often wide of the mark. But even as we
            stray we sometimes find the track anyway, and <unstress reason="environment">there’s something good in all movement</unstress> (by
            the way, I happened to hear Jules Breton say that and have remembered that utterance of
            his). Tell me, have you ever heard Mauve preach?? I’ve heard him imitate several
            clergymen – once he gave a sermon on Peter’s barque (the sermon was divided into 3
            parts: First, would he have bought it or inherited it? Second, would he have paid for it
            in instalments or parts? Third, did he perhaps (banish the thought) steal it?). Then he
            went on to preach on ‘the goodness of the Lord’ and on ‘the Tigris and the Euphrates’
            and finally he did an imitation of J.P.S., how he had married A. and Lecomte.</p>
      <p>But when I told him that I had once said in a conversation with Pa that I believed that
            one could say something edifying even in church, even from the pulpit, M. said, Yes. And
            then he did an imitation of Father Bernhard: God – God – is almighty – he created the
            sea, he created the earth and the sky and the stars and the sun and the moon, he can do
            everything – everything – everything – and yet – no, He’s not almighty, there’s one
            thing He cannot do. What is the one thing that God Almighty cannot do? God Almighty
            cannot cast away a sinner. Well, adieu, Theo, do write soon, in thought a handshake,
            believe me</p>
   </body>
   <close> Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
