<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Etten</location>, <date>on or about Saturday, 30 April or Sunday, 1 May 1881.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation> My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>My sincere congratulations on your birthday. I think of your visit time and again, I’m
            glad we spoke to each other again in this way, and hope it turns out that you’ll come
            again in the summer. I’ve been here for a few days and <unstress reason="environment">it’s beautiful outdoors</unstress>, but the
            weather doesn’t yet permit of drawing outdoors every day.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile <work origin="new" stage="sketch">I’ve started on the Millets</work>, The sower is finished and the 4 times of the day
            sketched. And now still to come are The labours of the field. As you know, there was an
            exhibition of watercolours in Brussels and it was quite interesting. There were 4 or 5
            Mauves, woodcutters, 1 J. Maris, dunes, just like a painting by Ruisdael or Van de
            Velde. Then J.H. Weissenbruch, superb, 5 large drawings, Roelofs ditto, also 5 large
            pieces. Then Gabrië and Van de Sande Bakhuyzen and Valkenburg and Van Trigt and P.
            Stortenbeker, and Vogel&amp;c. of the Dutchmen.</p>
      <p> Then there was a Mesdag that one had to imagine wasn’t there in order to see any of the
            other drawings, at least that’s how it was with me. The beach at twilight, stormy
            weather, sky with grey clouds with a ruddy glow from the sun, which had set.</p>
      <p> In the foreground a fisherman on a horse, a tall, singular, dark silhouette standing out
            against the white, foaming waves. This figure is speaking with people on board a pink
            floating in the middle ground. On deck people are busy with a lantern, and they’re
            evidently speaking to the man on horseback about the anchor, which he must come and
            fetch. It was a large, important drawing, broadly done and so powerful that, as I said,
            nothing else could hold a candle to it.</p>
      <p> What also struck me were 2 drawings by Ter Meulen, sheep in the dunes and ditto in the
            snow, he’s becoming really good. If I remember rightly, I saw that man struggling and
            swotting in Bakhuyzen’s studio, and now he’s succeeded all the same, those two drawings,
            at any rate, were excellent.</p>
      <p> Then there were drawings by Meunier, Farm-hand in a barn, distinguished in colour and
            treatment, and in conception reminiscent of Millet, for instance, as regards simplicity
            and faithfulness to nature. Also by him a stoker and a factory worker.</p>
      <p> There were also various drawings by Rochussen. And many others, but Meunier was the only
            one of the Belgians who actually moved me. Rappard is going to Holland in 3 weeks, and
            will probably carry on working in the countryside this summer and then possibly go to
            Paris next winter, but as yet he won’t go there with the intention of staying. I believe
            that he really received a cold shower when he was there earlier, but that’s no reason to
            think that he won’t have more luck during his next stay. He’s certainly progressed a
            good deal since then.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="career">I’m very glad indeed</unstress> that it’s been arranged for me to work here quietly for a while, I
            hope to make as many studies as I possibly can, for that’s the seed from which later
            drawings will grow. Do write to me from time to time and keep me informed, if possible,
            of one thing and another that strikes you, and think of me if you happen to hear of a
            position for a draughtsman somewhere or other.</p>
      <p> And now it’s time for the post, I’ll keep you informed of what I’m doing, and you must
            also tell me from time to time what you would advise me, by preference, to draw and to
            look out for. Sometimes I’ll find it useful, sometimes perhaps not, but don’t hesitate
            to tell me one thing and another, I’ll do the same to you, and then we must both try to
            separate the wheat from the chaff.</p>
   </body>
   <close> Adieu, with a handshake in thought. </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
