<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Etten</location>, <date>beginning of October 1881</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>As a letter is going to you again, I’m enclosing a word in it. I sincerely hope that
                  you’re doing well and will be able to find half an hour to write to me again. I
                  want to tell you what I’ve done since I last wrote to you. First of all, two large
                  drawings (chalk and some sepia) of <work origin="existing" stage="middle">Pollard willows</work>, something like the sketch
                  below.</p>
      <p>Also the same, but vertical, <work origin="existing" stage="middle">of Leurseweg</work>. Then I had a model a couple of times,
                  <work origin="existing" stage="middle">digger and basket-maker</work>. And then last week I got a box of paints from Uncle Cent
                  that is rather good, certainly good enough to start with (the paint is from
                  Paillard). And I’m very glad to have it. </p>
      <p>I’ve just tried making <work origin="existing" stage="middle">a kind of watercolour</work>, like the above motif. </p>
      <p>I count myself very lucky to be able to get models, I’m also searching around for a
                  horse and donkey. That thick Ingres paper is especially good for drawing with
                  watercolour, and a great deal cheaper than other paper. Still, there’s no
                  particular hurry, because I have some on hand, but unfortunately plain white
                  brought from The Hague. Anyway, you see that I’m hard at work. Uncle Cent will be
                  going to The Hague tomorrow and will most likely speak with Mauve again about when
                  I should next visit him. And now adieu, have walked far today and am surprisingly
                  tired, but didn’t want the letter to leave without enclosing something. I wish you
                  well, and accept a handshake in thought.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent.</sig>
</letter>
