<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Brussels</location>, <date>February 1881</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>Dear Pa and Ma,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I received your letter and was glad to have it, for I had already been looking forward to
            it, especially because of Pa’s indisposition. It’s fortunate that he’s starting to get
            better. Things continue to go quite well with my work, although it’s still imperfect and
            must improve a lot. I found a very good illustration of a skeleton in that painter’s
            studio. Because such things are fairly difficult to find, I asked him whether he’d give
            it to me for a day or two in order to copy it. At first he objected, probably because he
            thought that I wouldn’t be able to do it or that it would take me too long, but I
            insisted on having it and he allowed me to. That was last Sunday afternoon, and as soon
            as I got home I started on it, and on Monday evening it was finished, and to his
            surprise I brought it back to him on Tuesday morning already and he thought my drawing
            good, and in fact it isn’t that bad. I’ll profit even more from that man if only he has
            the time, he’s well informed on some points, especially perspective, and I can anyhow
            learn a lot from him. Now I must tell you about something else I’ve done. As I told you
            in a letter, I bought a pair of trousers and a jacket second-hand about a month ago. It
            turned out so well that I bought another jacket and another pair of trousers from the
            same man. I was of course more or less provided for by the first one, but having two
            suits is actually better and they don’t wear out so fast, because one can alternate
            between them. I herewith send you a sample of the material. And I also needed to
            supplement my underclothes with 3 pairs of underwear for which I paid 2.75 francs
            apiece, and I also bought a pair of shoes for 4 francs. I really did have to buy a few
            things. These few things have made a noticeable hole in what was sent for this month,
            and I’ll have to tighten my belt rather, especially because I paid the painter 5 francs
            in advance for the lessons. Don’t be concerned about these expenses, though, and don’t
            suspect me of recklessness, for in fact the opposite is sooner my failing, and if I
            could spend more I’d easily progress and make headway more quickly. If you could send me
            some more this month without inconveniencing yourselves, I’d like to ask it of you after
            all.</p>
      <p>But if you can’t, there’s no immediate hurry, because I mentioned to my landlord that I
            might find it hard to manage this month, and it’s all right with him if I pay him when
            it suits me, because by now he’s known me long enough not to demand absolutely that I
            pay in advance, at least not a whole month in advance. As regards that other suit, I
            have another objective apart from wearing it myself for as long as possible, for the
            fact is that when it’s a bit older it will serve me in another way. You see, I’ll
            gradually need a small collection of work-clothes with which to dress the models for my
            drawings. The blue smock of Brabant, for example, the grey linen suit that the miners
            wear and their leather hat, also a straw hat and clogs, a fisherman’s costume of brown
            fustian and a sou’wester. And most definitely the clothing made of that kind of black or
            brown velvet that’s very picturesque and characteristic — furthermore, a red doublet or
            vest. Likewise a couple of women’s costumes, such as that of Kempen and the area of
            Antwerp with the Brabantian cap and that of Blankenberge, for example, or Scheveningen
            or Katwijk. However, it’s by no means my plan to buy all of this at once, but most
            certainly to gather this and that gradually, piece by piece, when the opportunity
            arises. And because one can obtain these clothes second-hand, it’s not wholly
            unattainable. And all of this can get well and truly underway only when I have some kind
            of studio somewhere permanent.</p>
      <p>This is the only true way to succeed, by drawing from a model with the necessary
            costumes. Only if I pursue drawing this thoroughly and seriously, always seeking to
            portray reality, shall I succeed, and then, despite the inevitable expenses, a living
            can be made out of it. Because a good draughtsman can certainly find work nowadays, and
            there’s a great demand for such individuals and there are positions to be had that pay
            very well. So the thing is to try and become as good at it as possible. In Paris there
            are many draughtsmen who earn 10 or 15 francs a day, and in London and elsewhere just as
            much or even more, but one can’t achieve this all at once and I am by no means that far,
            but it could well come to that if I’m a little blessed and come again into contact with
            people like Mr Tersteeg and Theo and, more specifically, with good painters and
            draughtsmen. But only on the condition that a great deal of work and study be done. It
            won’t surprise you if I tell you that I’m extraordinarily eager to know what Theo’s
            proposal could possibly be, or perhaps to hear something from Mr Tersteeg. Because one
            way or another I must know anyway sometime in the month of March where I stand and how
            and where I’ll be able to work during the spring and summer months.</p>
      <p>And should I gradually begin to earn some money, that wouldn’t be disagreeable at all,
            even though the main thing is that I progress and become better at drawing. Then much
            will fall into place later on, whether it takes a long time or not. Models are
            expensive, relatively expensive at any rate, and if I could pay them and use them often
            I’d be able to work much better. But a studio then becomes indispensable. And people
            like Mr Tersteeg and Theo and others know this very well. Anyway, I’ll have to wait
            until they write about one thing and another, and meanwhile do what I can. Made a
            drawing of miners in the snow that’s a little better than the one from last winter, it
            has more character and effect.</p>
      <p>Am also collecting wood engravings again in the manner of those scrapbooks that Theo and
            Willemien used to have. For if I have that a bit more complete I may well profit by it,
            for it could very well be that one day I’ll do work for wood engravings. I want you to
            know that those clothes I bought are well cut and look better on me than anything else I
            can remember. I tell you this because you might think they were tawdry or out of the
            ordinary. This material is worn often, especially in the studios. And now I’ll close,
            after sending my regards to everyone and after congratulating you on Anna’s birthday,
            and believe me</p>
   </body>
   <close>Your loving </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>At the moment that painter with whom I now take lessons is making a very good painting of
            a Blankenberge fisherman, among other things. </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
