<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>,<date> on or about Monday, 10 April <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Today <work origin="existing" stage="finished">I sent you 1 drawing by post</work> which I’m sending to you as a<unstress reason="friendship"> token of gratitude </unstress>for
            so much that you’ve done for me during this otherwise hard winter. Last summer, when you
            had that large woodcut by Millet, ‘the shepherdess’, I thought: how much one can do with
            one single line! Naturally I don’t presume to say as much as Millet with a single
            outline. But I’ve nevertheless tried to put some sentiment into this figure. Now I only
            hope that this figure is to your liking. And now you see at the same time that I’m hard
            at work. Now that I’ve started, I’d like to make around 30 studies of the nude. The
           <work origin="existing" stage="finished"> enclosed is, I think, the best figure I’ve drawn</work>, that’s why I thought I’d send it to
            you.</p>
      <p>This isn’t the study from the model and yet it’s directly from the model. You should know
            that I had two sheets underneath my paper. Well, I’d toiled to get the outlines right
            and when I took the drawing off the plank it was very cleanly impressed on the two
            underlying sheets and then I immediately worked it up after the first study, so that
            this one is even fresher than the first. I’ve kept the other two and wouldn’t like to
            part with them. At the same time you’ll see from this that it isn’t without reason that
            I wrote to you that I wished the money for H.G.T. could wait, I need it so much myself
            now, and working hard with a model seems to me to be the quickest way of getting right
            on top of it. The model I have isn’t at all expensive, but because the expense recurs
            day after day it’s often difficult for me to pay it. Anyway, arrange it as best you can,
            but if it’s convenient for you, send what you spoke of not too late in the month. Adieu,
            with a handshake. </p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>It seems to me that this drawing would do well in a simple grey mount.</p>
      <p>Naturally I don’t always draw like this. But I’m extremely fond of those English drawings
            that are done in this style, so it’s no wonder that I tried to do the same for once, and
            because it was for you, who understands these things, <stress reason="career">I didn’t hesitate to be somewhat
            melancholy</stress>. I wanted to say something like </p>
      <p>But the heart’s emptiness remains That nothing will make full again as it says in
            Michelet’s book.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
