<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>on or about Sunday, 1 October <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Just a word to say that your letter arrived in good order, I thank you
      heartily for the contents. These last few days I’ve done almost nothing but watercolours. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">A
      scratch of a large one is enclosed.</work> You may remember Mooijman’s state lottery office at the
      beginning of Spuistraat. I passed it one rainy morning when a throng of people were standing
      there waiting to get lottery tickets. For the most part they were old women and the sort of
      people of whom it’s impossible to say what they do or how they live, but who evidently potter
      along and fret and get on with life. Of course, viewed superficially, a crowd of folk who
      evidently attach so much importance to ‘Draw today’ is something that almost makes you and me
      laugh, because we’re not in the least bit interested in the lottery. But the group of people —
      and their waiting expression — struck me, and it took on a larger, deeper meaning for me while
      I was working on it than in the first moment. It becomes more meaningful, I believe, if one
      thinks of it as the poor and money.</p>
      <p>That, in fact, applies to nearly all figure groups: one
      occasionally has to think about them for a while before one understands what one is seeing.
      The curiosity and delusion about the lottery seem more or less childish to us, but it becomes
      serious when one thinks about the other side: misery and forlorn attempts by these poor souls
      to be saved, so they think, by buying a lottery ticket, paid for with pennies saved by going
      without food. <work origin="new" stage="middle">Be that as it may, I’m working on a large watercolour of it.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’m also working on
      one of a church pew that I saw in a small church in the Geest district where the almsmen go</work>
      (they’re known here very expressively as ORPHAN men and orphan women). The way things are
      going, being busily drawing again, <unstress reason="environment">I sometimes think there’s nothing so pleasant as drawing.</unstress>
      This is part of the bit with pews; there are other men’s heads in the background. Things like
      this are difficult, though, and won’t come off in one go. Success is sometimes the outcome of
      a whole string of failures.</p>
      <p>Speaking of orphan men, I was interrupted while writing this by
      the arrival of my model. And I worked with him until it got dark — wearing a big old overcoat
      which gave him a curiously broad figure. I believe you might perhaps enjoy this collection of
      orphan men in their Sunday and working clothes. Then I also tackled him sitting with a pipe.
      He has an interesting bald head — big ears (NB. Deaf) and white sideboards. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">I did this scratch
      half in the dark, but perhaps it can give you an idea of the composition.</work> Once it has been put
      together, something like this can be quickly scribbled down. Putting it together was less
      easy, and I don’t claim that it stands now as I wanted to have it. I would enjoy painting it
      with figures the length of roughly one foot, or slightly less, with the composition then a
      little broader. However, I don’t know whether I’ll do it. I’d need a large canvas, and if it
      didn’t work there might be considerable costs involved. I also think — although I would
      greatly enjoy it — that I’ll come to things like that of my own accord, by continuing to do
      types of figures. Then later it will come naturally from the studies from the model, either in
      this or another form, but with the same sentiment.</p>
      <p>I’m becoming more and more aware of how
      useful and very necessary it is to keep studies from the model. Though they have less value
      for others, the person who has made them recognizes the model in them, and things are brought
      vividly to mind again. When there’s an opportunity, remember to send some of the old studies
      back to me. <work origin="new" stage="planned">I hope in time to use them to make more beautiful things.</work> It goes without saying
      that there were wonderful colours in the group of figures of which I’m sending you a black
      scratch — blue smocks and brown jackets, white, black, yellowish worker’s trousers, faded
      shawls, an overcoat turned greenish, white caps and black top hats, muddy paving-stones and
      boots contrasting with pale faces or ones weathered by the elements. And that’s where painting
      or watercolouring comes in. Well, I’m toiling away at it. I count on you to write again, of
      course, but thank you again for sending the money in good time, which is badly needed if I’m
      to carry on vigorously.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Adieu, old chap, accept a hearty handshake in thought, and believe
      me</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>There’s a little more foreground in the watercolour — here the figures are too far forward and one’s eye doesn’t grasp the 
      foreground enough.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
