<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>Sunday, 5 November <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Your letter and its contents were very welcome. A point that will perhaps be
      raised more and more is the one you refer to. People will be forced to recognize that much of
      what’s new, in which people at first thought they saw progress, is indeed less sound than the
      old, and consequently the need will become apparent for strong men to redress the balance.
      Since I believe arguing about this will make no difference to the matter itself, I think it
      quite unnecessary to write more about it.</p>
      <p>But for my part I can hardly say that I share your
      idea that you express as follows: ‘in my view it’s in the nature of things that the desired
      change will come’. Just think of how many great men have died or... won’t be with us much
      longer — Millet, Brion, Troyon, Rousseau, Daubigny, Corot — and a host of others — are no
      more. Think further back, I say, Leys, Gavarni, Degroux (to name just a few), or still
      further, Ingres, Delacroix, Géricault, think how old it already is, modern art. Add to them
      many who are aged. Nonetheless, there was still progress up to Millet and Jules Breton in my
      view, but as for surpassing these two men, don’t talk to me of that. Their genius may be
      equalled in past, present or later ages, but to surpass them isn’t possible. If one reaches
      that high zone, one is amid an equality of geniuses, but one can’t climb higher than the top
      of the mountain. Israëls, for example, may equal Millet, but with genius there’s no question
      of surpassing or being inferior.</p>
      <p>Now, though, the top has been reached in art. In the years to
      come we’ll most certainly see splendid things; something more sublime than what we’ve already
      seen — no. And for my part I fear that in a few years there may be a kind of panic, in this
      form: since Millet we have sunk very low — the word decadence, now whispered or pronounced in
      veiled terms (see Herkomer), will then sound like an alarm bell. Many, like I myself, now keep
      quiet, because they already have the reputation of being awkward customers, and talking about
      it doesn’t help. That — namely, talking — isn’t what one needs to do — one must work, though
      with sorrow in the heart. Those who later cry out the loudest about decadence will themselves
      belong to it the most. I repeat: by this shall ye know them, by their work, and it won’t be
      the most eloquent who say the truest things. See Millet himself, see Herkomer, they’re
      certainly not orators, and speak almost reluctantly.</p>
      <p>Enough of this, in you I find someone who
      understands much about the great men, and I find it delightful to hear things about them now
      and then that I don’t know, like, for example, what you write to me about Daumier. The series
      of portraits of politicians &amp;c., the painting of the 3rd-class carriage, the Revolution —
      I don’t know any of them. Now I haven’t seen them myself through what you say, but in my
      imagination Daumier’s personality has gained in importance as a result. I would rather hear
      talk about such men than about the latest Salon, for example.</p>
      <p>Now as for what you write about
      Vie Moderne, or rather about a type of paper that Buhot promised you. This is something that
      interests me very much. Do I understand correctly that this paper is such that when one does a
      drawing on it (I assume in autographic ink), this drawing — without using a second draughtsman
      or engraver or lithographer as an intermediary — can be transferred as it is onto a stone, or
      that a print can be made of it, so that any number of impressions can be obtained, the latter
      then being facsimiles of the original drawing? If this is the case, be so good as to give me
      all the information you can find about how one should work on this paper, and do your best to
      send me some of it on which I can do some trials. If I could do my trials before you come,
      then we could discuss what to do with them at that time.</p>
      <p>I think it possible that within a
      relatively short time there may be a demand for employees for illustration, more so than at
      present. If for my part I fill my portfolios with studies from the models that I can grab or
      catch, I’ll get something to show so that I’ll be eligible, I hope, to be given employment. To
      keep on illustrating, like for example Morin, Lançon, Renouard, Jules Ferat, Worms in their
      day, one must have plenty of ammunition in the form of various studies in different fields.
      I’m trying to gather these together, as you know, and will see in due course. </p>
      <p> By the way, so
      far I have not yet received the packet of studies which you wrote that you had returned
      through rue Chaptal. Could they already have arrived at the Plaats? If you think they have,
      I’ll have them collected, because they’ll be useful to me in connection with things I’ve been
      doing recently. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">Do you know who I drew this morning? Blok the Jewish bookseller, not David but
      the short one who’s on the Binnenhof.</work> I wish I had more from that family, for they are a true
      type. It’s enormously difficult to get the types one would prefer to have — in the meantime
      I’m content to draw what I can get, without losing sight of the others I would draw if I had
      the choice. I’m very pleased with Blok. He reminds me of things from many years ago. I hope
      he’ll come again some other Sunday morning. Naturally, while working one always feels and
      ought to feel a sort of dissatisfaction with oneself, a desire to be able to do it much
      better, but still it’s delightful and enjoyable to gradually assemble all kinds of figures —
      although the more one makes, the more one realizes one needs.</p>
      <p> One can’t do everything at once,
      but it will be absolutely necessary for me to do a number of horse studies some day, not just
      scratches on the street but with a model for once. I know of an old white horse, a real nag if
      ever there was one (at the gasworks), but the man, who makes the poor animal do all manner of
      heavy jobs and just wants to get what he can out of it, asked a lot for it, namely three
      guilders to come to me for a morning, a daalder at the very least at his place, provided I
      came on Sunday. And when you consider that for what I need, namely 30 strong studies, say, I
      would have to work quite a few mornings, it would cost me too much. But I’ll find a better
      opportunity sometime. I can get a horse much more easily here and there for a very short time,
      these people are sometimes willing to do that, but in a very short time one cannot do what
      really needs to be done, so that’s little help. I try to work quickly, because otherwise it
      just doesn’t pan out, but a study that’s of some use requires at least half an hour, say, so
      one always comes back to actual posing. At Scheveningen, for instance, I’ve occasionally had a
      boy or a man stand still for a moment, as they say, on the beach. The outcome was always a
      great desire on my part for a longer pose, and standing still for a moment isn’t enough for
      me, neither for a person nor for a horse. If I’m correctly informed, the draughtsmen for The
      Graphic whose turn it was always had models at their disposal in a studio at the offices.
      Dickens has some nice things to say about the painters of his age and their wrong way of
      working, namely slavishly and yet only half sticking to the model. He says: Fellows, do
      understand that your model isn’t your ultimate goal but a means for giving body and vigour to
      your ideas and inspiration.</p>
      <p>Look at the French (Ary Scheffer, for example) and see how much
      better than you they do it. It’s just as if the English listened to him — they continued
      working with models, but they learnt to see the model in a grander and bolder way, and learnt
      to take better advantage of it for sounder and nobler compositions than those of Dickens’s
      painting contemporaries. Two things that remain eternally true and complement each other, in
      my view are: don’t snuff out your inspiration and power of imagination, don’t become a slave
      to the model; and, the other, take a model and study it, for otherwise your inspiration won’t
      take on material form.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">When your letter came there were things I had to pay immediately. I
      hope it won’t inconvenience you to send again no later than 10 Nov.</stress> Understand that the
      question of that process Buhot spoke to you about strikes me as being pretty important. I
      would be very pleased if I could learn it, and would like to do my best at it.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Adieu, with a handshake.</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent.</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>Do you know the effects one sees here early in the morning
      these days? It’s splendid — it’s what Brion painted in the painting in the Luxembourg, The end
      of the flood, namely that band of red light on the horizon with rain-clouds above. This brings
      me to the landscape painters. Compare those of Brion’s time with now. Is it better now than
      then? I doubt it. I’ll gladly acknowledge that they’re much more productive in that field than
      in the past, but although I can’t help admiring what they make now, the old landscapes in a
      more old-fashioned manner always give me pleasure when I see them. There were a few years when
      I walked past a Schelfhout, for example, and thought something like: that’s not worth the
      effort. Yet the new, although it takes someone in, doesn’t always continue to make the same
      strong, moving impression over time, and a naive painting like a Schelfhout or a Ségé, a Jules
      Bakhuyzen, is seen again with vivid pleasure after one has long been looking at newer things.
      I really didn’t deliberately set out to be somewhat disenchanted as regards progress; on the
      contrary, it began to develop unwittingly in my thoughts very much against my will, because as
      time passed I felt more and more a kind of emptiness which I can’t fill with the things being
      made today. While searching for an example, I think of old woodcuts by Jacque that I saw at
      least 10 years ago at C.M.’s. It was a series, The months. They were done in Jacque’s old
      manner, in the manner of those etchings that appeared in annual series, or even more
      old-fashioned. The local tone is less in them than in his later work, but the draughtsmanship
      and a certain terseness are reminiscent of Millet. You see, with the many croquis in the
      present magazines it seems to me that a not entirely unconventional elegance threatens to
      replace that typical, truly rustic quality of which the croquis by Jacque that I mean are an
      example. Might not the cause of this also lie in the lives and characters of the artists? I
      don’t know what your experience is, but do you find many people these days prepared to go for
      a long walk in grey weather, for example? You would do it gladly, and enjoy it too, as I
      would, but for many it would be a chore. Equally, I was struck by the fact that when one talks
      to painters, in most cases, by far, the conversation is not interesting. When he wants, Mauve
      has the power to say something in words so that one sees it, and most certainly others here
      have that too when they want. Yet, that curious fact that when one talks to a painter one
      immediately has a sense of the open air — is it your impression that that’s as strong as it
      used to be? This week I read in Forster, Life of C. Dickens, all kinds of details about long
      walks on Hampstead Heath &amp;c. outside London, the final goal being, for example, to have
      bacon and eggs at an old inn way out in the country. Those walks were very jolly and cheerful,
      but all the same it was usually the case that serious plans for books were made, or else the
      changes Dickens was to make to one character or another were discussed. <stress reason="environment">The present has
      something hectic and harried about it for which I do not care, and it’s just as if death has
      touched everything.</stress> I’d like your expectation ‘that the desired change will come’ to prove
      true, but in my view it isn’t ‘in the nature of things’. Be this as it may, opposing in words
      is a complete side issue, I believe, and what everyone who considers the matter important
      should do in his own circle is to try to make or help to make something. Have been working
      again on women miners carrying sacks of coal in the snow — watercolour. But above all I’ve
      drawn 12 or so studies of figures for it, and 3 heads, and I’m not yet finished. I’ve got the
      effect in the watercolour, I believe, but it isn’t yet strong enough in character for my
      taste. The reality is like Millet’s The gleaners — austere — so you will understand that one
      shouldn’t turn it into a snow effect, which would only be an impression and have no raison
      d’être unless the landscape is the whole point. I think that I’ll start all over again —
      although the studies I have for now may please you — precisely because I was more successful
      with them than with many others. It would be really suitable, I believe, for the Vie Moderne.
      If I get the paper, I already have one of the figures, for example, to do as a trial. But it
      must become a little troop of women, a small caravan.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
