<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>,<date> on or about Thursday, 6 April <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>It shouldn’t surprise you that I wrote to you: become a painter. For I myself am now
                  in a period in which I’m deriving some benefit from my earlier worries. Because as
                  things are now, every week I make one thing or another that I couldn’t make
                  before, and that’s what I spoke about, that it’s as though one were young again.
                  And it’s the awareness that nothing – <bad_health>(except sickness)</bad_health> can rob me of the strength
                  that’s now beginning to develop, <unstress reason="environment">it’s that awareness that gives me faith in the
                  future and enables me to bear many unpleasantnesses in the present. It’s a
                  wonderful thing to look at something and find it beautiful, to reflect on it and
                  hold it fast and then to say: I’m going to draw that, and then to work on it until
                  it’s done</unstress>. Obviously that’s why I’m not yet content with my work to the extent
                  that I think I needn’t do it any better. But the way to do it better later is to
                  do it as well as one can today, there can’t be anything but progress tomorrow.
                  Naturally I don’t know what you’ll think of my drawings when you finally see them,
                  but this much I do know, I’m greatly longing for you to come. </p>
      <p>And if I write to you, become a painter, then it really isn’t because I think that in
                  your present position there isn’t a very great deal that’s beautiful. <unstress reason="career">But I find
                  being a painter more beautiful</unstress>, and I wish you worked in your own studio instead
                  of at a reading-desk in the office. There you have it. I know for certain that
                  something would awaken in you in your own studio which you don’t know of now – a
                  huge, hidden force of working and creating. And once it’s awake, it’s awake for
                  good. When I hear Tersteeg talking about agreeableness and saleability I can only
                  think: work one has slaved away at and done one’s best to imbue with character and
                  sentiment can be neither disagreeable nor unsaleable. And perhaps it’s better that
                  one doesn’t immediately please everyone. <unstress reason="environment">What wonderful weather we’re having –
                  there’s spring in everything. I can’t let go of the figure, for that’s No. 1 for
                  me, but sometimes I can’t keep myself from going outdoors.</unstress> But I’m busy with
                  difficult things that I can’t let slide. Recently I’ve been making many studies of
                  parts of the figure: heads, neck, breast, shoulder. See the enclosed scratch. I’d
                  very much like to make more studies of the nude. You know <work origin="existing" stage="finished">I’ve drawn the Exercices
                  au fusain, several times eve</work>n, but they don’t include any female figures. </p>
      <p>Of course, doing it from life is something entirely different. <work origin="existing" stage="finished">A little drawing like
                  the enclosed</work> is simple enough in line, but it’s difficult enough to capture those
                  simple, characteristic lines when one is sitting in front of the model. Those
                  lines are now so simple that one can outline them with the pen, but I repeat, the
                  problem is finding those broad outlines, so that one can say what’s essential with
                  a couple of strokes or scratches. Choosing the lines in such a way that it’s
                  obvious, as it were, that they must run thus, that’s something that isn’t obvious,
                  however. It’s true, Theo, that recently, since I’ve been in The Hague, I’ve spent
                  more than 100 francs a month, but if I didn’t do that, I couldn’t work with a
                  model, and would remain at the same level, making no progress. I see this in other
                  painters: Breitner, for example. They’re afraid to take a model regularly, and
                  they work little and slowly – if only it were good anyway, but it isn’t even that.
                  Breitner had been taking a model again lately, though, and there was of course
                  more spirit in his work, but then he fell ill. The English painters, certainly the
                  draughtsmen for The Graphic &amp;c., have a model nearly every day. Without that
                  it really doesn’t work, in my opinion. If someone with many years of experience
                  draws figures from the imagination after a great deal of study, fine, but to work
                  systematically from the imagination seems overly rash to me. Israëls and Blommers
                  and Neuhuys don’t do that, even though they have so much experience. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">If I’ve spent more than 100 francs a month here, it’s because it’s not possible to
                  spend less. And believe me, I don’t throw it around rashly or too freely. I do
                  wish I didn’t have to give Tersteeg the 25 guilders back yet, because I really
                  need the money to be able to go on working energetically. </stress>Tersteeg is none the
                  poorer by it, and in the beginning he himself said that I needn’t worry about it.
                  Even though every 25 guilders less means that my work suffers and that I can’t do
                  what really needs to be done. If I fill my portfolios with studies I’ll get my
                  money’s worth out of them later. And I’d rather earn a bit more later than now.
                  I’d rather see to it that I’m equal to my profession than rush to sell a drawing
                  by the grace of God. The <work origin="existing" stage="finished">enclosed drawing was scratched after a larger study which
                  has a more sombre expression</work>. There’s a poem by Tom Hood, I believe, in which he
                  tells of a great lady who can’t sleep at night because during the day, when she
                  went out to buy a frock, she saw the poor seamstresses pale, consumptive,
                  emaciated, working in an airless room. And now she has twinges of remorse about
                  her wealth and wakes up at night in panic. In short, it’s a slender, white female
                  figure, restless in the dark night. If I must, I’ll talk no more about it and give
                  Tersteeg the 25 guilders when you send money again, but if it could be arranged,
                  I’d prefer to wait until he takes a drawing for it later, because now I definitely
                  need as much money as I can possibly spare for my studies. Anyway, it seems to me
                  that Tersteeg won’t be so severe as not to understand that at the moment 25
                  guilders are worth more to me than they are to His Hon. Well, I wish you well, and
                  remember, I hope you’re working in your own studio in the near future. It needn’t
                  happen too quickly – but I believe that after a relatively short time of worry,
                  you’d be happier once and for all. Adieu. </p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>P.S. I don’t have many studies of the nude yet, but there are some that bear a very
                  close resemblance to the Bargues, are they therefore less original? Perhaps it’s
                  because I learned to look at nature through the Bargues. </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
