<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>Monday, 25 September <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Your latest letter with the enclosure reached me in good order, and I thank
    you right heartily for it. <stress reason="money">I was and even still am in a bit of a spot — that is, with a view to
    painting. There are all kinds of costs involved.</stress> But that’s also partly because many of the
    things that I begin don’t come off, and then one has to start again and the effort comes to
    nothing, except that this is the way to make progress, and that one must persevere.</p>
      <p>There was no
    answer in your last letter to what I said about sending or not sending painted studies. Perhaps
    it slipped your mind. Now, I decided that it wasn’t a weighty matter after all, and so <work origin="new" stage="finished">today
    I’ve sent you a painted study by post.</work> But, as I said in my last letter, I would of course
    rather you could see them all together sometime, and it goes without saying that you mustn’t
    judge the future by this one, since I haven’t been working with the brush long enough for me not
    to change a great deal. I wanted to send you a different one, <work origin="new" stage="finished">but the others I would rather have
    sent aren’t yet dry enough for me to risk rolling them up.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Like me, you will no doubt have
    reservations about the background in particular. The only explanation I can offer about this is
    that the study was done as a study of the foreground, namely the tree roots; a lot of work had
    already gone into them, and as usual I wasn’t sitting peacefully because of passers-by, and so
    when I had got the study to the point you see I couldn’t bear it any more. <stress reason="environment">You can’t imagine how
    wearying and irritating it is that people always gather round so close.</stress>
         <bad_health>It makes me so nervous
    sometimes that I have to give up.</bad_health> Just yesterday morning, although it was very early and I hoped
    to be spared, a study of the chestnut trees on Bezuidenhout (which are so splendid now) was a
    failure because of it. <stress reason="environment">And sometimes they’re so nasty and insolent.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Oh well. But it’s not just
    the regrets that one has — there’s also the cost of the paint, etc., which can’t be recovered.
    Of course things like that won’t get on top of me, and I’ll fight my way through them just as
    others do, but I do so feel that I could reach my goal much faster if there were fewer of these
    petty vexations. Now, as regards this study — if it’s the case that, on seeing it and knowing
    that I have many others as well as this one, you don’t regret enabling me to make it, then I’ll
    be content and shall carry on in good heart. If you’re disappointed, remember that I started
    only a short time ago; if you’re pleased, so much the better for me, for I would so much like to
    be able in time to send you something that gave you pleasure.</p>
      <p>Now I must tell you that <unstress reason="love">I had a very unexpected and very pleasing visit from Pa,</unstress> 
    who came to my house and to the studio, which I believe is infinitely better than his only hearing about me through reports 
    from others. If people visit me, then at least their impression is original, but I don’t like opinions based on
    what people say. <good_health>It really gave me great pleasure to see Pa and talk to him.</good_health> I’ve again heard a
    lot about Nuenen — that churchyard there with the old crosses won’t leave me alone, I do so hope
    that in time I’ll get round to doing it. I also heard a lot about your visit, and that you had
    given them that engraving after Israëls, which touched them deeply. <work origin="new" stage="finished"/> — I could send the first, but since then I’ve
    caught the colour of the sea better, and so I’m waiting until a later one is thoroughly dry.
    Recently, though, I’ve painted considerably more than in the original plan we discussed. But
    perhaps it’s necessary to continue doing this if it’s at all possible.</p>
      <p>I received a letter from Rappard the other day. I wish he lived a little closer. And rest assured that I’m truly glad to
    hear your comments, just as they come into your mind. I often feel a desire and need to seek
    advice from someone on various questions, but after what happened with Mauve I don’t give in to
    that, and I don’t discuss my work with painters. However brilliant someone may be, what good is
    it to me if he argues differently from the way he works? I would rather M. had spoken to me
    about the use of body-colour instead of saying: ‘Above all, you mustn’t use body-colour’, while
    he himself and all the others, so to speak, nearly always use it, and to the best effect. 
    Well, in many cases one can gradually find out things by looking for oneself as well, and I’m doing
    that as best I can.</p>
      <p>Yes — if it were so that I could do exactly what I wanted, I would take up
    painting on a somewhat larger scale and, above all, work much more with a model. I draw many
    figures in my spare moments. The small figure in this study is actually there simply and solely
    for the size, so that if I do use the study I can find the proportion of any figure, more or
    less. Of course, a proper figure is a very different matter and involves a great deal more. It’s
    also there to provide an accent. Make no mistake, old chap, I send you this because, since you
    said nothing about it, I didn’t know what to do. Of course I intend something very different
    from this, and I’m sending it in the same way that I make a scratch sometimes, to give you an
    idea of what I’m working on.</p>
      <p>Adieu, accept a handshake in thought. I hope that all is as well
    with you as possible, and that your headache isn’t something that lasts or keeps coming back. I
    have it too sometimes, more as a sense of unpleasant dullness than severe pain. Pa and I went
    for a walk on Rijswijkseweg, it’s lovely there too.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Well, regards again, and believe me</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>If this arrives safely, then this is an easy way of sending you things
    occasionally. I don’t know whether one can send drawings or paintings by post as printed matter.
    Another thing, you understand that I could do some things differently, for example some branches
    &amp;c., if I painted them again — but I think that one shouldn’t tinker with studies if they’re
    to be of any use. They should be hung up in the studio just as they come out of the woods. For
    some they may be less pleasing, but there’s more of his impression in them for the painter
    himself.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
