<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>Saturday, 11 March <year>1882</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo. </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>You’ll perhaps find it rather harsh, what I wrote to you about Tersteeg. By no means do I
            take it back, though. Tersteeg is someone who is extremely hard of hearing, though I
            don’t consider him deaf. He must be told things very decidedly, otherwise it doesn’t
            penetrate his armour. <stress reason="career">For years he’s thought me a kind of blockhead and dreamer, he
            still views me as such, and even says about my drawings: that’s a kind of opium daze you
            administer to yourself so as not to feel the pain you suffer at not being able to make
            watercolours. Now then, that’s very cleverly put, but that expression is actually
            ill-considered, superficial and doesn’t hold water</stress> (the main reason I can’t make
            watercolours straightaway is that I must draw more seriously and pay attention to
            proportion and perspective). Similarly, Mr T.’s ‘practical talks’ (say) on art couldn’t
            be more impracticable. It doesn’t help him even if he uses as arguments some things that
            could be called conversation killers, because it’s difficult to find an answer to them.
            Enough – I don’t deserve his reproaches, and if my drawings don’t amuse His Hon. neither
            does it amuse me to show them to His Hon. like that. </p>
      <p>He condemns drawings of mine which contain much that is good, and I hadn’t expected that
            of His Hon. If I make serious studies from a model it’s a lot more practical than his
            practical talks about saleability or unsaleability, about which I – having dealt in
            paintings and drawings myself, for that matter – don’t need to be enlightened by His
            Hon. to the extent that he thinks. I’d prefer, then, to lose his friendship than agree
            with him about this.</p>
      <p>Although at times I’m overwhelmed by worries, all the same, I’m calm, and my calmness is
            based on my serious approach to my work and on reflection. Although I have moments of
            passion,<stress reason="career"> and my disposition tends to make them worse</stress>, nonetheless I’m composed, as His
            Hon., who’s known me long enough, very well knows. Now he even said to me: you have too
            much patience. <stress reason="career">Those words aren’t right, one can’t have too much patience in art, that
            word is beyond the pale. Perhaps in my case Mr H.G.T. has too little patience. Now he
            must see, once and for all, that I’m setting to work seriously and won’t let myself be
            forced into sending work into the world that doesn’t bear the stamp of my own character.</stress>
            My own character is beginning to emerge particularly in my last drawings??? studies???,
            which Tersteeg rejected. </p>
      <p>Perhaps – perhaps I’d succeed even now in making something in the genre of watercolour
            that could perhaps be sold with a great deal of effort. But that would be forcing
            watercolours to grow in the hothouse. Tersteeg and you must wait for the natural season,
            and it hasn’t arrived yet. He spoke English when he was here because of the model. I
            said to him: in due time you shall have your watercolours, now you can’t – they are not
            due yet. Take your time. And I’m sticking to that. Enough. Since T.’s visit I’ve made a
            <work origin="new" stage="finished">drawing of an orphan boy polishing shoes</work>. It might have been done with a hand that
            doesn’t exactly obey my will yet, but even so it contains the type of that orphan boy.
            And no matter how clumsy my hand, that hand will still have to end up doing what my head
            wants. So I’ve made a study of the studio with the stove, the fireplace, easel,
            tabouret, table &amp;c., of course not exactly saleable just now, but very good for
            putting perspective into practice. I’m longing for you to come, you have quite a lot to
            see, which I’ve made since your visit last summer. Theo, I’m counting on your looking at
            my work with sympathy and with confidence, and not with two minds or dissatisfaction.
            Tersteeg thinks, because I work so much, that it’s easy, that’s where he’s also
            mistaken. But I’m actually a drudge or a draught ox. </p>
      <p>If you come, would you be sure and think of the Ingres paper? It’s the thick one in
            particular that I like to work on, and it seems to me it must lend itself even to
            studies in watercolour. Believe me that in artistic matters the words hold true: Honesty
            is the best policy. Better to put a bit more effort into serious study than being
            stylish to win over the public. Occasionally, in times of worry, I’ve longed to be
            stylish, but on second thoughts I say no – just let me be myself – and express severe,
            rough, yet true things with rough workmanship. I won’t run after the art lovers or
            dealers, let those who are interested come to me. In due time we shall reap if we faint
            not.</p>
      <p>Oh well. Listen, Theo, what a man that Millet was! I have the big work by Sensier on loan
            from De Bock. It interests me so much that I wake up at night and light the lamp and go
            on reading. Because during the day I have to work. Do send me something soon if it’s at
            all possible. I wish that for once Tersteeg had to face a week of doing what I do on
            what I have to spend, he’d notice that it’s not dozing or dreaming or an opium daze, but
            that one has to be wide awake to combat the many difficulties that crop up. Nor is it
            easy to find models and to get them to pose. Most painters are driven to desperation by
            it. Especially when one has to scrimp – go short of – food, drink, clothing in order to
            pay them. Well, Tersteeg is Tersteeg and I am I. Nonetheless, rest assured, I’m not
            <stress reason="career">opposed to, i.e. hostile towards him, but I must make him understand that he judges me
            too superficially and – and – I believe that he’ll change his mind – I sincerely hope
            so, because being at odds with His Hon</stress>. pains me very much and makes life difficult for
            me. I hope your letter comes soon – <stress reason="money">my last pennies are for posting this letter</stress>. It’s
            only been a few days since I received the 10 guilders from Tersteeg, but that same day I
            had to pay 6 guilders of it to the model, to the baker, to the girl who sweeps the
            studio. Adieu, I wish you health and good cheer, in spite of everything <good_health>I’m not without
            good cheer either</good_health>.</p>
   </body>
   <close> I shake your hand.</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>I had a very pleasant visit from Jules Bakhuyzen, and I may go and visit him whenever I
            wish.</p>
      <p>Here you have a few words that struck me and moved me in Sensier’s Millet, sayings of
            Millet. Art is a battle – you have to put your whole life into art. One must work like a
            bunch of negroes.</p>
      <p>I’d rather say nothing than express myself weakly. It was only yesterday that I read that
            last saying of Millet, but I’d felt the same before then, which is why I sometimes feel
            the need to scratch in what I feel not with a soft brush but a hard carpenter’s pencil
            and a pen. Watch out! Tersteeg! Watch out! You’re clearly wrong. </p>
      <p>Theo, it’s almost miraculous!!!</p>
      <p>First of all, a message arrives that I must go and fetch your letter. Secondly, C.M.
            comes, orders 12 small pen drawings from me, views of The Hague, having seen a few that
            were finished (Paddemoes. The Geest district – Vleersteeg were finished) for a
            rijksdaalder apiece, the price set by me. With the promise that if I make them to his
            liking he’ll order 12 more, but for which he’ll fix the price higher than I do. Thirdly,
            I run into Mauve, successfully delivered of his large painting, promises to come by
            soon. So, it’s fine – it’s going well – it’ll get even better! And something else moved
            me, and moved me deeply – I’d said that the model didn’t have to come today – I hadn’t
            said why – but the poor woman came anyway and I protested. Yes, but I’m not coming to be
            drawn, I’m just coming to make sure you’ve got something to eat – she had a portion of
            string beans and potatoes with her. There are indeed things in life that are worth the
            effort.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
