<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>Wednesday, 1 November 1882.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>For several days I’ve been completely taken up by
      something that may also be of interest to you and I think it well worth writing to you about
      it especially. In a letter from Rappard I received an extract from a lecture by Herkomer on
      the subject of the wood engravings of recent times. I can’t tell you about the whole thing in
      detail, you may have read the article yourself (which was in an English art magazine, perhaps
      the Art Journal). It was mainly about the drawings in The Graphic. Herkomer relates how he
      himself worked on them with great ambition and enthusiasm, and he particularly recalls the
      splendid prints in the first volumes. Feels that no words can express sufficiently forcefully
      how important he finds the work of those first artists. He reviews the progress made in
      process and technique, the difference between the old and the modern wood engraving, &amp;c.
      &amp;c. Then talks about the present day, and that brings him to the real subject of his
      lecture. He says: the wood engravers are cleverer than ever, but nonetheless I see a decadence
      if I think back to when The Graphic began. And — he goes on — in my view the reason lies in
      two things against which I protest. One has to do with the publishers, the other with the
      artists. Both have their faults, which will ruin things if one doesn’t combat them. The
      publishers, he says, demand things done for effect: ‘correct and honest drawing is no longer
      wanted, complete designs are no longer in request, a “bit” just covering an awkward corner of
      a page, is all that is required’. ‘The managers declare that the public require the
      representation of a public event or so and are satisfied if it is correct and entertaining,
      caring nothing for the artistic qualities of the work. I do not believe what they say. The
      only excuse you may accept is “dearth of good draughtsmen”’. Then he comes to the artists, and
      says that he regrets that these days all too often it’s the wood engraver, not the
      draughtsman, who makes the prints beautiful. Urges the artists not to accept this — to draw
      soberly and forcefully so that the engraver remains what he should be, the translator of the
      draughtsman’s work, and doesn’t get the upper hand. Then comes his conclusion, a forceful plea
      to all to continue supporting the cause warmly, and not to allow any weakening.</p>
      <p>There’s something of a reproach in his plea, and it isn’t without some melancholy that he speaks, and
      as one fighting against the indifference he finds intolerable. ‘To you — the public — the art
      offers infinite pleasure and edification. For you it is really done. Therefore clamour loudly
      for good work and be sure it will be forthcoming’ — are his closing words. The whole thing is
      thoroughly sound, firm, honest. His manner of speaking makes the same impression on me as some
      letters by Millet. It gives me encouragement, and it truly does me good to hear someone talk
      like that for once. I say that it’s a terrible pity that here there’s no enthusiasm, so to
      speak, for the art that’s most suitable for the common people. If the painters were to close
      ranks to ensure that their work (which, after all, is made for the people, in my view — at
      least I believe that is the highest, noblest vocation for any artist) could also come into the
      hands of the people and was put within everyone’s reach, that would be something that would
      produce the same results as were produced in the first years of The Graphic. Neuhuys, Van der
      Velden and a few others made drawings this year for ‘De Zwaluw’, a magazine that appears
      monthly and costs 7 1/2 cents. There are some good ones, but one can see that most were done
      with a weak hand (not the original drawings but the way of popularizing them), and from what I
      hear the magazine is no more likely to keep going than its predecessors. Why doesn’t it work?
      — the booksellers say they earn nothing from it, and instead of circulating it they block it.
      And as for the painters, I believe they haven’t yet made every effort to take the matter to
      heart. The definition that many a painter here in Holland gives in reply to the question ‘What
      is a wood engraving?’ is: ‘it’s those things lying in the Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’. So they
      rank them among the drinks. And the makers of them among the drunks, perhaps. And what do the
      dealers say? Suppose I went to anyone here with around 100 sketches that I’ve gathered
      together. At best I fear I would be told ‘did you imagine those things had commercial value?’</p>
      <p>My love and respect for the great draughtsmen of both the age of Gavarni and of the present
      day increases the better acquainted with their work I become, and above all as I do my best
      myself to make something from what one sees every day on the streets. What I value in
      Herkomer, in Fildes, in Holl and the other founders of The Graphic, why I find and will
      continue to find them even more sympathetic than Gavarni and Daumier, is that, while the
      latter seem to view society more with mockery, the former, like such men as Millet, Breton,
      Degroux and Israëls, choose subjects which — while as true as those of Gav. or Daum. — have
      something noble and in which there’s a more serious sentiment. That, above all, must remain,
      it seems to me. An artist need not be a minister or a collector in church, but he must have a
      warm heart for people, and I find it a noble thing that, for example, no winter passed without
      The Graphic doing something to keep alive sympathy for the poor. For instance, I have a print
      by Woodville showing the distribution of turf tickets in Ireland, another by Staniland
      entitled Help the helpers depicting various scenes in a hospital — where money was short,
      Christmas in the workhouse by Herkomer, Homeless and hungry by Fildes &amp;c. I find them even
      more beautiful than the drawings by Bertall or somebody for the Vie Elégante or other
      élégances. Perhaps you’ll find this a tedious letter — but everything was once more fresh in
      my mind. I had gathered together and mounted my 100 or so studies and when I had finished the
      job a slightly melancholy sense of ‘what’s the good?’ came over me — but then Herkomer’s
      forceful words calling on people not to <unstress reason="career">weaken and saying that it’s more necessary than ever
      to keep the hand to the plough did me so much good, and I thought I’d briefly tell you the
      substance of what he said</unstress>.</p>
   </body>
   <close>With a handshake in thought, believe me</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>I hope to hear from you in the coming days, <unstress reason="family">I received a good letter from home.</unstress>
      </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
