<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>on or about Saturday, 14 January 1882.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>Dear brother, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>As I’ve often done, I sent you an answer in my last letter that was brief and to the
                  point about one thing and another, yet in harsh words that nevertheless truly
                  express what I think about things, but you mustn’t think that<stress reason="family"> I’m always in a
                  gruff, cold-hearted mood which Mauve would perhaps call a yellow soap mood or
                  saltwater mood</stress>. But even if I had written a yellow soap letter or a saltwater
                  letter, <stress reason="family">surely that’s no worse than taking things too sentimentally</stress>. You say,
                  ‘you’ll truly regret it some day’. Old chap, I believe that I’ve had many such
                  regrets &amp;c. before now. I saw it coming and tried to nip it in the bud, well
                  that didn’t work, and anyway, what happened, happened. Will I now regret it? No,
                  actually I don’t have time for regrets. Drawing is becoming more and more of a
                  passion, and it’s just like a sailor’s passion for the sea. Mauve has now shown me
                  a new way to make something, namely watercolours. Well, now I’m immersed in that,
                  and I’m daubing and washing out, in short, seeking and striving. For one must make
                  desperate attempts.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="career">Because there’s something diabolical about the execution of a watercolour.</unstress> Because
                  there’s something good in all energetic movement. So although I was planning to
                  write to you in even more detail about what happened at home, to try and explain
                  how things stand from my point of view, even though I also wanted to tell you this
                  and that about other subjects, I haven’t time for that now, and think it better to
                  write to you again about drawing. </p>
      <p>In addition to <work origin="new" stage="planned">a couple of small watercolours</work>, I’ve just started <work origin="new" stage="planned">a large one</work>, at
                  least as large as <work origin="existing" stage="finished">one of those figure studies I made at Etten</work>. Naturally it
                  doesn’t automatically go well and easily straightaway. Mauve himself says that
                  I’ll ruin at least 10 drawings or so before I know how to handle the brush a
                  little. But it will lead to a brighter future, so I work on with as much
                  cold-bloodedness as I can muster, and don’t let myself be deterred by my mistakes. </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">This is a little sketch of one of the small watercolours</work>, it’s a corner of my studio
                  with a girl grinding coffee. You see I’m looking for tone, a head or a hand that
                  glows, with life in it, and that stands out against a drowsy background, twilit,
                  and standing out boldly against that, that fragment of fireplace and stove, iron
                  and brick, and a wooden floor. If I could get that drawing the way I’d like it,
                  I’d make at least 3/4 of it in yellow soap style and treat only that corner where
                  the child is sitting delicately and tenderly and with sentiment. But you
                  understand that I still can’t express all of that as I feel it, but it seems to me
                  the point is simply to attack the difficulties, and the yellow soap passage still
                  isn’t yellow soapy enough and the contrasting tenderness still not tender enough.
                  But anyway, the sketch is still chucked on and its conception is clear, and to me
                  it seems fairly good. Of course one can’t master the technique the first day. </p>
      <p>This is the subject of the large drawing, <stress reason="career">but I’m doing it in a hurry and the sketch
                  is terrible</stress>. Even so, perhaps it gives you an idea, and in any case it’s already
                  on paper. I hear that someone called on me today, Mr Tersteeg, I think. I hope so,
                  because he promised me he’d stop by, and I wanted to discuss some things with him.
                  He’s supposed to be coming back tomorrow morning. Theo, I’m having a lot of
                  trouble with the models, I search for them and when I find them it’s a struggle to
                  get them to come to my studio, and sometimes they let me down. Like a smith’s boy
                  this morning, who couldn’t come because his father said that I had to pay a
                  guilder an hour, and of course I wasn’t inclined to do that. Tomorrow I have the
                  little old woman as a model again, but she couldn’t come for 3 days running. Well
                  then, when I go out, I quite often go to sketch in the soup kitchen or the
                  3rd-class waiting room or such places. <stress reason="environment">But it’s so damned cold outdoors</stress>,
                  especially for me, since I don’t yet draw as fast as more practised draughtsmen,
                  and actually have to work my drawings out in more detail for them to be of any use
                  to me. </p>
      <p>So you see I’m not standing still and am no longer dwelling on Etten, but am trying
                  to put down roots here. <stress reason="money">Naturally the models cost me money, and I must tell you
                  that I buy what’s necessary for myself, though the cheapest possible. (I go to the
                  soup kitchen to eat.) </stress>And yet I trust you won’t have any objections to my
                  continuing. But I repeat what I said in my last letter: let me know as precisely
                  as possible where I stand, and I think it would be fine if you could come to an
                  agreement with Mr Tersteeg, so that in case of difficulty I can go to him without
                  too many misgivings. For my part I promise you that I’ll work as much as I can,
                  though things like models often depend on the money I do or don’t have in my
                  pocket, whether I can set to work at full speed, half speed or sometimes not at
                  all. Now, for instance, I’m negotiating with a mother with a little child, though
                 <stress reason="money"> I’m afraid it will turn out to be too expensive for me</stress>. Be assured that I’d prefer
                  to go full speed but... anyway, you understand it all, <stress reason="money">I have to restrain myself
                  until I have more resources and freedom</stress>. Write to me again soon, and listen, send
                  the money as soon as possible in February, because I’m sure I won’t have a penny
                  by then. I’m planning to go on making small pen drawings whenever possible, but
                  different from the large ones I made this summer. A bit sharper and a bit angrier.
                 <work origin="existing" stage="sketch"> This is a sketch of Schenkweg</work>, the view from my window. Well, adieu, with a
                  handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
