<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>Thursday, 6 July 1882.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>Dear brother,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Having received your letter and the 100 francs enclosed, I thank you most sincerely and
            feel the need to write to you again straightaway. Because I think it would be a good
            idea if I explained, honestly and to the best of my knowledge and with all the
            earnestness in me, some matters which it’s important you should be fully aware of and
            understand. So I hope that you’ll read this letter at your ease and with patience,
            because for me so much depends on it. <bad_health>Tomorrow morning I’m going back to the hospital
            and I’ll lay my head down there calmly if I know that you’ve been informed about
            everything as fully and clearly as the distance permits</bad_health>. I would much, much rather that
            you’d been present, so that I could have shown you everything here this afternoon and
            discussed it with you. But let’s hope that will happen in August. Before going on to
            various other matters, <unstress reason="environment">I must tell you that I was very taken by one passage in your
            letter describing Paris by night. Because it evoked a memory of myself when I too saw
            ‘Paris all grey’ and was struck by that so very curious effect, with the little black
            figure and the distinctive white horse that brings out the delicacy of those curious
            greys exactly like that.</unstress> That touch of dark and that tonal white are the key to the
            harmony. But in the hospital just recently, as it happens, an artist who described that
            Paris all grey with the hand of a master made a great impression on me. In ‘Une page
            d’amour’ by Emile Zola I found several townscapes painted or drawn in a masterly,
            masterly fashion — entirely in the sentiment of the simple passage in your letter. And
            that small book by him is why I’m very definitely going to read everything by Zola, of
            whom I had only known a few fragments up to now: 1 for which I attempted to make an
            illustration, ‘Ce que je veux’, and another piece describing an old peasant that was
            exactly like a drawing by Millet. You have something mightily artistic in you, brother —
            cultivate it — let it first put down roots one way or another and then flower — don’t
            give it to just anyone — but seriously, for yourself, think about it, and don’t consider
            it a misfortune if it concentrates itself through that thinking and comes to occupy
            quite an important place in your activity. But I may be venturing into forbidden
            territory, so no more about that for today. Only, again, there is ‘drawing’ in your
            short description — for me palpable and comprehensible, even though you haven’t yet
            pursued your impression to the point where it would acquire a more robust body and stand
            on its feet visibly or palpably for everyone. The true pain and tension of creating
            begins at the point where you let go of the description – but you have the intelligence
            of creating in damned good measure. Now you can’t go any further because you don’t yet
            believe in yourself in this respect, otherwise you would take the plunge, that’s to say
            venture further. But enough. There’s a certain je ne sais quoi in your description, a
            scent — a memory — of a watercolour by Bonington, for example, only it’s still faint as
            if in a mist. Do you know that drawing in words is also an art, and sometimes betrays a
            hidden force latent inside, just as the blue or grey cloud of smoke betrays the hearth? </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="family">I most certainly do appreciate what Pa and Ma did</unstress> during<bad_health> my illness </bad_health>– you remember I
            wrote to you about it right away — <unstress reason="friendship">as much as I value the visit by H.G.T. </unstress>However,
            that’s not why I didn’t immediately write to Pa and Ma about Sien or anything else, and
            only sent a brief word to tell them of my recovery. And here’s why. Because something is
            left of what happened last summer and this winter that marks the line between past and
            present like an iron barrier. </p>
      <p>It isn’t in the least my intention to go in the same manner as last year to Pa and Ma to
            ask their advice or opinion, because it became clear to me then that there was a sharp
            difference in way of thinking and attitude to life. Nonetheless, it is my ardent desire
            to keep the peace and to convince Pa and Ma that it wouldn’t be right if they were to
            turn against me, in the belief that I was someone who only dreamed and didn’t know how
            to act — that, I say, they are mistaken in their view that my approach to situations is
            so impractical as to make it necessary for them to ‘guide’ me. You see, Theo, believe
            me, I don’t say this out of bitterness, contempt or disdain for Pa and Ma — or to
            glorify myself — but only to help you grasp one fact, namely this. <stress reason="family">Pa and Ma aren’t the
            sort of people to understand me — neither my faults nor my better side — they can’t put
            themselves in my position.</stress> Reasoning with them only leads to quarrels. What’s to be
            done??? Here’s my plan, which I hope you will approve. I hope to arrange things so that,
            next month for example, I can put aside 10 guilders, or preferably 15. Then — but not
            before — I want to write to Pa and Ma that I have something to say to them, that I
            invite Pa to repeat his journey at my expense and to stay with me for a few days. </p>
      <p>I want to show him Sien and her baby, which he won’t be expecting, as well as the house
            bright and the studio with all manner of work in progress, and myself, by then fully
            recovered, I hope. In my view all this will have a better and deeper and more desirable
            effect than words or writing. I’ll tell him briefly how Sien and I struggled through her
            anxious pregnancy last winter — how you helped and still help us loyally, even though
            you only heard about Sien later. That for me she is priceless, first through the love
            and attachment between us that circumstances have strengthened, and second because from
            the start she has devoted herself utterly, with great good will, intelligence and
            practical skill, to helping me in my work. And that she and I dearly hope that Pa will
            approve of my having taken her as my wife. I can’t put it any other way than ‘having
            taken’, because the formality of marriage is not what makes her my wife, since this is a
            bond that already exists — a feeling from both sides that we love, understand and help
            each other. As for what Pa will say about marrying itself, I believe he’ll say, ‘Marry
            her’. I would like Pa to have a fresh and clear impression of a new future for me, to
            see me here in surroundings very different from what he may imagine, for him to be
            completely reassured about my feelings towards him, for him to have confidence in my
            future and put wardship or Geel a thousand miles from his thoughts. You see, Theo, I
            know of no more direct or honest way or means than what I’ve described to restore
            relations soon and in a practical fashion. Write and let me know your feelings about
            this. </p>
      <p>Now, furthermore, I don’t think it superfluous to tell you again, although it’s difficult
            to express, what I feel for Sien. <unstress reason="love">I have a sense of being at home when I’m with her, a
            sense that she brings my ‘hearth and home’ with her, a sense that we have grown
            together.</unstress> This is an intensely deep feeling, serious and not without the dark shadow of
            her and my fairly sombre pasts, a shadow I’ve written to you about before, as if,
            indeed, something sombre continues to threaten us against which our life must be a
            constant struggle.<unstress reason="environment"> At the same time, though, I feel a great calm and clarity and
            cheerfulness at the thought of her and of the straight path lying before me.</unstress> You know
            that last year <unstress reason="love">I wrote to you a great deal about Kee Vos — so that, it seems to me, you
            have a clear picture of what took place within me. Don’t think that I exaggerated my
            feelings to you — it was a strong, passionate love I felt for her, unlike that for Sien.
            When I discovered in Amsterdam that she had a sort of dislike for me, which I didn’t</unstress>
            think was the case, to such an extent that she regarded my behaviour as coercion and
            wasn’t even prepared to see me, but ‘that she went out of the door of her own house as
            long as I was inside it’, then — but not before — my love for her received a mortal
            blow. Which I first became aware of when, recovering from my intoxication as it were, I
            was in The Hague this winter. At that time there was a sense of inexpressible melancholy
            in me which I find impossible to describe. I know that I then thought very, very often
            of a manly remark by père Millet: ‘It has always seemed to me that suicide is the act of
            a dishonest man’. </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>The emptiness, the inexpressible wretchedness inside, made me think</bad_health> — yes, I can
            understand why there are people who jump into the water — it’s just that I was far from
            approving of what those people did, and I found solidity in the words I’ve quoted, and
            thought it much the better approach to get hold of oneself and seek a medicine in work.
            The way, as you know, I tackled it then. It’s difficult, terribly difficult, indeed
            impossible, to think of something like my passion of last year as an illusion. That’s
            what Pa and Ma do, but I say, ‘Even if it will never be, it could have been’. It wasn’t
            an illusion, but the attitudes differed and the turn taken by circumstances was such
            that the ways diverged further and further instead of coming together. This is how I see
            it — these are my clear and honest thoughts — it could have been but now it never can
            be. Was Kee Vos right to have a dislike for me, was I wrong to persist? I declare I do
            not know. And it isn’t without pain and sorrow that I think back on it and write about
            it. I would like so much to understand better why Kee Vos was like that then and how it
            was that my parents and hers were so adamantly ominous and opposed, not so much through
            their words — although very certainly through them too, above all indirectly in the
            meaning more than the form — as through their complete lack of genuine, warm, living
            sympathy. I can’t soften these words, but I think of it as a mood of theirs that I would
            rather forget. Now, in the circumstances, it’s like a large, deep wound in me that has
            healed but is still palpable. </p>
      <p> At that time — in that winter — <stress reason="love">could I feel ‘love’ again straight afterwards? Certainly
            not.</stress> But was it wrong that the human feeling in me wasn’t extinguished or numbed, and
            that my sorrow indeed aroused a need for compassion with others??? I think not. So at
            first Sien was a fellow human being to me, as alone and unhappy as I was. Yet, not being
            in despair, I was in the right state of mind to be able to give her some practical
            support, which at the same time was a stimulus to me to carry on. But gradually, slowly,
            something else developed between her and me. <unstress reason="love">A certain need for each other. So that she
            and I stayed close together, entering each other’s lives more and more, and then it was
            love.</unstress> Theo, I must perhaps touch on a point that may be painful for you that may make
            you understand what I mean. In the past you had what Pa and Ma also call an ‘illusion’
            for a woman of the people, and the fact that nothing came of it wasn’t because you
            couldn’t take that path in life but because things took a different course, and you have
            since adapted to life in another class where you are now firmly established, so that for
            you it wouldn’t again be an illusion if you wanted to marry a girl from your class. In
            your case that wouldn’t arouse any comment, and although nothing came of that first
            love, something might come of a new love, and you would succeed. In my opinion, your way
            is definitely not to take a woman of the people: with you the so-called illusion was the
            woman of the people; the reality for you has now become the woman from the same kind of
            class as Kee Vos. For me, though, it’s the other way round: the illusion (ALTHOUGH I
            DON’T BELIEVE THAT WORD OR DEFINITION WAS APPROPRIATE OR ACCURATE, EITHER IN YOUR CASE
            OR MINE) was Kee Vos; the reality has become the woman of the people. </p>
      <p>There’s a difference between your case and mine in several respects. Your failure was
            when you were twenty, mine last year. But although both you and I may have had an
            illusion, failure or whatever — I really don’t know what to call it — that doesn’t rule
            out something more real, either for you or for me. For I’m quite sure that neither of us
            is cut out to be celibate. What I want to make clear is this: what there is between Sien
            and me is real; it’s not a dream, it is reality. I count it a great blessing that my
            thoughts and capacity for work have found a focus, a particular direction. While it may
            be that I felt more passion for Kee Vos, and that in some respects she was more charming
            than Sien, it is certainly not so that the love for Sien is therefore less sincere, for
            the circumstances are too grave, and it all comes down to taking action and being
            practical, and that has always been so since I first met her. You can see what the
            result is... now if you come you won’t find me dejected or melancholy, but you’ll enter
            a setting with which I believe you’ll be satisfied, or at least like. A young studio, a
            still young, fully functioning household. Not a mystical or mysterious studio, but one
            that has rooted itself in real life. A studio with a cradle and a close-stool. Where
            there’s no stagnation and everything prompts and urges and generates activity. </p>
      <p>Now if someone or other comes to tell me that I’m a poor financier, I’ll show him my
            place here. I’ve done my best, brother, to ensure that you can see (and not just you,
            but everyone with eyes in his head) that I strive and sometimes manage to tackle things
            practically. HOW TO DO IT. This winter we had the woman’s pregnancy and my expenses in
            getting settled. Now the woman has given birth, I’ve been ill for four weeks — and still
            not better — despite all that the place is clean and cheerful and bright and tidy, and I
            have a large part of my furniture, bedding and painting materials. It has cost what it
            cost, to be sure I won’t underestimate it, but your money hasn’t gone down the drain. A
            young studio has come from it which can’t yet do without your help, but from which more
            and more drawings will gradually emerge and which requires only essential furniture and
            tools, which retain their value. You see, old chap, if you come here now to a house full
            of life and activity, knowing that you are its founder — won’t that give you a proper
            sense of satisfaction, more so than if I were a celibate spending my life in bars? Would
            you have it otherwise??? You know that I wasn’t always happy, and sometimes truly
            wretched, and now through your help my youth is emerging, and my true development. </p>
      <p>Now I just hope that you won’t lose sight of this great change, even when people think
            you’re mad to have helped or to help me. And that you’ll continue to see in the present
            drawings the seed of later ones. A little longer in the hospital and then I’ll go back
            to work, and the woman and child will pose. It’s as clear as daylight to me that one
            must feel what one makes, that one must live in the reality of family life if one wants
            to portray family life intimately — a mother and child, a washerwoman, a seamstress,
            whatever. </p>
      <p>As a result of stubborn labour, the hand is gradually becoming obedient to that feeling.
            But if I were to snuff out this feeling, and the strength to have my own household,<stress reason="environment"> that
            would be suicide</stress>. That’s why I say — onward — despite dark shadows, cares and
            difficulties, also, alas, through people interfering and gossiping. Theo — make no
            mistake — although I, as you rightly say, stay out of it, it often pierces me to the
            soul. But do you know why I no longer argue with them and why I stay out of it? —
            because I must work and may not let myself be diverted from my path by the gossip and
            difficulties. But I don’t stay out of it because I’m afraid of them or am at a loss for
            words. Also, I’ve often noticed that they say nothing in my presence, and even claim
            never to have said anything. As for you, knowing that I don’t get involved in order not
            to make myself nervous and because of my work, you’ll be able to understand my attitude
            and not think it cowardly of me, won’t you? Don’t imagine that I think myself perfect —
            or that I believe it isn’t my fault that many people find me a disagreeable character.
            <bad_health>I’m often terribly and cantankerously melancholic, irritable — yearning for sympathy as
            if with a kind of hunger and thirst — I become indifferent, sharp, and sometimes even
            pour oil on the flames if I don’t get sympathy.</bad_health>
         <stress reason="friendship">I don’t enjoy company, and dealing with
            people, talking to them, is often painful and difficult for me.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>But do you know where a great deal if not all of this comes from? Simply from nervousness
            — <stress reason="environment">I who am terribly sensitive, both physically and morally, only really acquired it in
            the years when I was deeply miserable</stress>. Ask a doctor and he’ll immediately understand
            entirely how it couldn’t be otherwise than that nights spent on the cold street or out
            of doors, the anxiety about coming by bread, <stress reason="environment">constant tension because I didn’t really
            have a job, sorrow with friends and family were at least 3/4 of the cause of some of my
            peculiarities of temperament</stress> — and whether the fact that I sometimes have disagreeable
            moods or periods of depression couldn’t be attributable to this? But neither you nor
            anyone else who takes the trouble to think about it will, I hope, condemn me or find me
            unbearable because of that. I fight against it, but that doesn’t alter my temperament.
           <stress reason="environment"> And even if I consequently have a bad side, well damn it, I have my good side as well,
            and can’t they take that into consideration too?</stress> Write to me to say whether you approve
            of my little plan for telling Pa and Ma and establishing better relations. I don’t feel
            in the least like just writing about it or going to discuss it, and would probably then
            make my usual mistake of putting it in such a way that they take offence at some
            expression or other. There you are. I think when the woman is back with her child, I
           <good_health> fully recovered and back from the hospital</good_health>, the studio working, then I would like to say
            to Pa: come and resume your visit and stay with me for a few days to talk things over.
            And then send the travel expenses as a courtesy. I can’t think of a better plan. Adieu,
            thank you for everything, and a handshake, and believe me </p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
