<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>13 February <year>1882</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation> My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Even though I’m rather expecting a letter from you one of these days, I’ll write again
            anyway. I heard a few things about you from Mr Tersteeg when he returned from Paris. He
            told me that you were doing well, and he seemed to be rather pleased with his trip. When
            I went to see him I had a couple of drawings, and he said that they were better than the
            last ones and told me that I should again make a couple of small ones. I’m working on
            those now. And I’ve also been <work origin="new" stage="middle">working on a new pen drawing of an old woman knitting</work>. And
            I believe <unstress reason="career">it’s better than last summer’s, at least it has more tone</unstress>. When I have a
            couple of pen drawings that have turned out quite well, I believe I know an art lover
            who will take them. I also wrote to C.M. the other day to say I’d rented a studio here,
            and hoped that when he came to The Hague he’d let me know, or come and have a look.
            Uncle Cent also told me last summer that if I have a drawing, a little smaller than
            those of last summer and with more watercolour, I should simply send it and he would
            take it. Perhaps the time will soon come when my work will put some money in my pocket,
            which I’m badly in need of, precisely in order to tackle things more seriously. </p>
      <p>If you can find out about it, you must tell me what kind of drawings one might be able to
            sell to the illustrated magazines. It seems to me they could use pen drawings of types
            of the people, and I’d like so much to start working on them, in order to make something
            suitable for reproduction. I don’t think that all drawings are drawn directly on the
            blocks, there must be some means of getting a facsimile onto the block. Though I don’t
            rightly know. Sometimes I long so very much to see you and talk to you, will it be a
            long time before you come to Holland? I believe Pa half expected you to come for his
            birthday. I was very glad that Mr Tersteeg found the drawings a little better, well, I’m
            also beginning to feel more at home with my model, and that’s precisely the reason why I
            must continue with her now. In the last two studies I captured the character much
            better, everyone who saw them said so. <unstress reason="friendship">At the moment I quite often go to draw with
            Breitner, a young painter who’s acquainted with Rochussen as I am with Mauve</unstress>. He draws
            very skilfully and very differently from me, and we often draw types together in the
            soup kitchen or the waiting room &amp;c. He sometimes comes to my studio to look at
            woodcuts, and I go to see the ones he has as well. He has the studio that Apol used to
            have at Siebenhaar’s. </p>
      <p>Last week I went to an art viewing at Pulchri which had sketches by Bosboom and Henkes.
            Very beautiful; there were a number of drawings by Henkes, larger figures than one
            usually sees from him. He ought to make more of them, I think. Weissenbruch also came to
            see me. I<unstress reason="friendship"> look forward every day to a letter from you, because I hope you’ll send me
            something one of these days</unstress>. We must stick it out for a while, old chap, and persevere,
            you as well as I, and then we’ll both get pleasure from it sometime. I’m really very
            glad that I’ve gone on with the figure so far. If I’d been making only landscapes,
            perhaps I’d already be making something that would fetch a price, but later on I’d end
            up getting stuck anyway. Although the figure is more difficult and a more complicated
            matter, I believe it’s more solid in the long run. De Bock came here this afternoon just
            as I was working from the model, and when he saw the model he started saying that he’d
            quite like to draw figures too; all the same, he doesn’t do it. He recently made a
            beautiful drawing, though. </p>
      <p>In your last letter you told me something about the matter of your not being able to have
            any money before the inventory was finished. But if you don’t have it, be so good as to
            write to Mr Tersteeg about it immediately, because I have only three guilders or so left
            and it’s already nearly the middle of February. So at all events I’m expecting a letter
            from you any day now. I believe that I’ve got the proportions much better in my <work mention="unnamed"> last
            drawings</work> than in the <work mention="unnnamed">previous ones</work>, and that’s exactly what seemed to me to be the worst
            fault in<work mention="unnamed"> my drawings up to now</work>, but that’s changing, thank God, and then I won’t be
            afraid of anything. Adieu Theo, write soon, accept in thought a hearty handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
