<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>5 August <year>1882</year>. Saturday.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Still very much under the impression of your visit, <unstress reason="environment">and more than a little pleased
                  that I can go on painting with new vigour</unstress>, I’m writing you a few words. I had
                  wanted to take you to the train the next morning — but I thought you had already
                  given me so much time that it would have been impolite if I had asked you for the
                  following morning as well. <unstress reason="friendship">I’m very grateful to you for visiting me here</unstress> — it’s
                  wonderful to have the prospect of a year of steady work without disasters, and
                  thanks to what you gave me I now also have a new horizon in painting. I regard
                  myself as privileged above a thousand others in that you remove so many barriers
                  in my way.</p>
      <p>It goes without saying that many often can’t carry on because of the expense; well, I
                  can hardly put into words how <unstress reason="career">thankful I am to be able to keep on working
                  steadily</unstress>. I have to try twice as hard to make up for lost time because I began
                  later than others, and with the best will in the world I would have to give up if
                  I didn’t have you. Let me tell you about everything I’ve bought. </p>
      <p>First, a large moist colour box for 12 pieces or tubes of watercolour with a folding
                  lid that serves as a palette when open — there’s also room for 6 brushes. </p>
      <p>This is a valuable piece of equipment for working out of doors, in fact absolutely
                  essential, but it’s expensive and in my mind I had postponed it until later, and
                  until now worked with loose pieces on saucers, but they’re awkward to carry,
                  especially if you have other items as well. So it’s a fine thing to have, and once
                  you have one it will last you for a long time. At the same time I bought a supply
                  of watercolour and replaced my brushes and added some new ones. Moreover, I now
                  have all the essentials for proper painting. And a supply of paint — big tubes
                  (which work out much cheaper than small ones), but you will understand that I’ve
                  limited myself to simple colours in both watercolour and oil: ochre (red, yellow,
                  brown), cobalt and Prussian blue, Naples yellow, terra sienna, black and white,
                  supplemented with some carmine, sepia, vermilion, ultramarine, gamboge in smaller
                  tubes. But I refrained from buying colours one ought to mix oneself.</p>
      <p>I believe this is a practical palette, with sound colours. Ultramarine, carmine or
                  something else are added if absolutely necessary. </p>
      <p>I’ll start with small things — but before the summer ends I hope to practise bigger
                  sketches in charcoal with an eye to painting in a rather larger format later. This
                  is why I’m having a new and, I hope, better perspective frame made, which will
                  stand firmly on two legs in uneven ground like the dunes. </p>
      <p>Like this, for example. What we saw together at Scheveningen, sand — sea — sky — is
                  something I certainly hope to express one day. Of course I didn’t spend everything
                  you gave me all at once — although I must say the prices of things greatly took me
                  aback, especially bearing in mind that more items are needed than appears at first
                  sight. It would be a help if you could send the usual around the twentieth, not
                  because everything will be gone by then, but because I think it advisable to keep
                  a little in my pocket in case, while working, I find that I really need something
                  or other. That will help me to work calmly and in an orderly fashion.</p>
      <p>The moist colour box fits into the painting box — so that if need be I can carry
                  everything required both for watercolour and for painting in one object. I place
                  great value on having good materials, and would like my studio to look substantial
                  — but without antiquities or tapestries and drapery — but through the studies on
                  the walls and good tools. That will have to come with work and time. On the
                  subject of the village constable style — I feel less like a village constable than
                  like a Delft bargee, for example, and I don’t at all object to my place being like
                  a cosy tow barge. Yesterday afternoon I was in the attic of Smulders’ paper
                  warehouse on Laan. There I found — guess what — double Ingres under the name
                  Papier Torchon: it was a type with an even coarser grain than yours. I’m sending
                  you a sample to show you. There’s a whole batch — already old and mature,
                  excellent. I bought only half a quire for now, but I can always go back later. I
                  was there in search of something else, namely the Honig paper that I have now and
                  then, very cheap, from an undelivered order for the land registry. That is very
                  suitable for charcoal drawing, I believe, and comes in large sheets tinted rather
                  like the Harding type. As you see, this sample has a grain as coarse as a piece of
                  sailcloth. What you brought is a nicer colour and wonderful, for example, for
                  studies of the sides of ditches and soils. However, I’m glad to have discovered
                  this new batch. Well, old chap, many thanks for everything, a handshake in
                  thought; I’m going to start work. Give Pa and Ma my warmest regards, thank them
                  for what they gave you for me, and tell them I’ll write soon — but as agreed not
                  about special matters. Adieu — enjoy yourself, and have a safe return to your
                  ordinary work, and believe me </p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
