<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>26 July 1882. Wednesday morning</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
   <body>
      <p>It matters greatly to me that you shouldn’t get the idea that I’m in a dejected or abnormal
      mood. That’s why I wrote to you already about work in my last letter, and since I have a few
      more things to ask in that connection I haven’t waited long before writing again. By the time
      you come I’ll do my best to have several watercolours done in different ways ready for you to
      see, then we can discuss which seems best to you.</p>
      <p>So I’ll work regularly on <work origin="new" stage="middle"> this every day, and continue to do so until you come. I now have 3
      of Scheveningen — again the Fish-drying barn you know — drawn in as much detail — only now
      there’s colour as well</work>. As you well know, Theo, it isn’t harder to work in colour than in
      black and white, the opposite perhaps, but as far as I can see 3/4 comes down to the original
      sketch, and almost the whole watercolour depends on its quality. It isn’t enough to give an
      approximation, and my aim has been and still is to make it more intense. I believe that’s
      already evident in the black-and-white fish-drying barns, because there you can follow
      everything and see how it all fits together, and look, I think this is why I now work much
      more fluently in watercolour, because for such a long time I did my best to draw more
      correctly. </p>
      <p>Tersteeg said that what I was doing was a waste of time; soon you’ll see that I’ve saved a
      great deal of time. I already feel that, and you’ll see it for yourself when you come. </p>
      <p> This evening I went from one shop to another searching for thick Ingres, but in vain. They
      have the thin, but the dense or double is nowhere to be found. At the time I bought all that
      Stam had left, and it was wonderfully mature. Before you come, oh do your best to find some
      once more. And if you can’t get any, try asking for ‘papier de la forme’. That is with a
      yellowish tint — stiff — and you can use wash on it. I believe it’s also much cheaper than
      Harding or Whatman,<unstress reason="money"> so that in the end there’s quite a saving</unstress>. When you come I know of a few
      lovely paths through the meadows where it’s so quiet and peaceful that you’ll be delighted.
      I’ve discovered old and new labourer’s cottages there, and other houses that are distinctive,
      with small gardens lining the banks of the ditch — really charming. I’m going to draw there
      early tomorrow morning. It’s a path through the meadows from Schenkweg to Enthoven’s factory
      or Het Zieke. I saw a dead pollard willow there, just the thing for Barye, for example. It
      hung over a pond with reeds, all alone and melancholy, and its bark was scaled and mossy, as
      it were, and spotted and marbled in various tones — something like the skin of a snake,
      greenish, yellowish, mostly dull black. With white flaking spots and stumpy branches. I’m
      going to attack it tomorrow morning. I’ve also done a bleaching ground at Scheveningen, on the
      spot in one go, entirely in wash almost without preparation, on a very coarse piece of
      torchon. <work stage="sketch" origin="new">Here are a couple of small sketches of it.</work> I’ll make sure that several things are
      ready by the time you come. I think you’ll like the Fish-drying barn now that it’s with
      colours. </p>
      <p>Make no mistake, old chap, I’m fully back into my normal routine, and rest assured that
      everything else depends on work, and I see everything as directly related to that. The new
      studio makes a huge difference compared to the previous one in that it’s more pleasant to work
      in; for posing, especially, it’s a great improvement because one can stand further back. I’m
      sure it will be well worth the extra rent. I have one request for you, though. I would
      entirely understand and would find it quite natural if, instead of sending the money on 1
      August, you were to give it to me yourself when you arrive on, say, 7 August. As soon as I
      received your last letter, however, I made some purchases of paper and paint and brushes, and
      by 1 August I’ll certainly need some more things. So I want to ask you to be so kind as to
      send something all the same just before 1 August, if possible, even though you’ll be coming
      soon afterwards, because I’ve worked it out exactly, exactly, and after the first few days of
    <stress reason="money">  August I’ll certainly be absolutely broke</stress>. I hope this won’t inconvenience you: of course,
      more is not the intention; it’s the time that matters, namely 1 August, if possible, and
      otherwise only a few days later. I also have a second of the Rijswijk meadows in which the
      same subject takes on an entirely different aspect through being seen from a different height
      and viewpoint. As you see, I’ve become very caught up in landscapes. The reason is that Sien
      can’t pose yet, but otherwise the figure must remain the chief concern. </p>
      <p>When you come I’ll take care to be close to home as long as you’re in the city and that you
      know where I am, and otherwise I’ll carry on with my normal routine while you do your business
      and pay visits. I can find you wherever you suggest a meeting, but for various reasons I
      believe it’s better for both of us if I don’t go with you to the Plaats, say, or to Mauve, for
      example. I’m so used to my working clothes, in which I can sit or lie in the sand or grass as
      I please (for in the dunes, for example, I hardly ever use a chair, except perhaps an old fish
      basket), that my outfit is rather too Robinson Crusoe-like for me to accompany you much on
      your rounds. I say this in advance so that you’ll know I won’t be an embarrassment to you, but
      otherwise you understand that I long for every half hour you can spare. I think we’ll be more
      at ease if we’re completely taken up by painting and drawing, and talk mainly about that.
      Unless you’re not bored or embarrassed by other matters, if not, then of course I have no
      secrets from you, and you have my complete confidence in everything. I also long to show you
      the woodcuts. I have another splendid one, a drawing by Fildes, ‘Dickens’s empty chair’ from
      The Graphic of 70. I could have bought 3 etchings by Meryon for 2 guilders for all three, but
      I let them go. They were good though, but I have so few etchings and want to concentrate on
      woodcuts if I buy anything else. But I wanted to tell you about them — Blok has them, and I
      don’t know if all Meryons are rare and valuable. They’re from an old volume of L’Artiste. I’m
      still under the spell of Zola’s books. How painted those Halles are. <good_health>My health is good</good_health>, though
      I still feel the odd thing and will probably continue to do so, at least for some time yet.
      Sien and the child are also well; they’re getting stronger and <unstress reason="love">I love them dearly</unstress>. I must have
      another go at the cradle (when it’s a rainy day and I can’t go outside), entirely in
      watercolour. But for the rest, when you come I want to show you — landscape watercolours —
      nearer winter I hope to have figure watercolours, that is, after I’ve been here a year. First
      I’ll have to draw more nudes and a lot more in black and white, it seems to me. We’ll discuss
      all that, and I don’t doubt that your visit will be a great help in keeping things in order
      and making work go smoothly. Adieu, with a handshake. </p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>By quietly carrying on with my work I have every hope I’ll gradually acquire a new circle of
      friends to make up for the <stress reason="friendship">loss of the friendliness of Mauve, HGT and others</stress>. But I’ll take no
      steps to bring that about, none at all, for it must come through the work. What has happened
      to me with H.G.T. is nothing out of the ordinary; everyone experiences things like that in
      life. It’s impossible to say exactly what the cause is. But in the case of H.G.T. it’s an old
      grievance. I know now with near certainty that he said things about me long ago which did much
      to cast me in a bad light. However, I needn’t be concerned about that — what could hurt me in
      the past can’t do so now. When you come to the studio you’ll see for yourself how utterly
      absurd it is for him to say: oh, your drawing will never amount to anything. But it’s
      difficult to counter a pronouncement like that, because as soon as one does so it’s seen as
      conceit, and people cite the very greatest names and say: he thinks he’s so-and-so or
      so-and-so. </p>
      <p>But, again, anyone who works with love and with intelligence has a kind of armour against
      people’s opinion in the sincerity of his love for nature and art. Nature is severe and hard,
      so to speak, but never deceives and always helps you to go forward. So I don’t count it a
      misfortune if I find myself out of favour with HGT or anyone else, however much I regret it.
      That can’t be the direct cause of unhappiness — if I felt no love for nature and my work, then
      I would be unhappy. But the less I get on with people the more I learn to trust nature and to
      concentrate on it. All these things make me fresher and fresher inside — you’ll also see that
      I’m not afraid of a fresh green or a soft blue and the thousand different greys, for there’s
      hardly any colour that isn’t a grey: red-grey, yellow-grey, green-grey, blue-grey. This is
      what all colour mixing comes down to. When I went back to the Fish-drying barn, a luxuriant
      and indescribably fresh green from a wild vegetable or oilseed had shot up in the baskets
      filled with sand in the foreground that serve to stop the sand of the dunes blowing about. Two
      months ago it was all barren except for a bit of grass in the small garden, and now that
      rough, wild, luxuriantly sprouting green produced a most pleasant effect as a contrast to the
      bareness of the rest. I hope you’ll like that drawing. The vista — the view over the roofs of
      the village with the small church tower and the dunes — was so attractive. I can’t tell you
      with how much pleasure I drew it. So come soon — I believe you’ll be completely content with
      the change of studio when you see how infinitely better it is for my work — more space, better
      light, greater distance. </p>
      <p>Yesterday evening I got a parcel from home. Among other things, it contained a sort of
      demi-saison which is very useful. It was very kind of them. And there were tobacco and cigars,
      a cake and underwear. In short, a whole package. Don’t you think that’s kind? It’s more that
      I’m pleased by it showing their warm feelings than by anything else. I’ve also had another
      letter from Rappard.<unstress reason="friendship"> I take enormous pleasure in the fact that that chap is so fascinated by
      his English woodcuts.</unstress> I got him going in the beginning, but now he needs no further
      encouragement; <unstress reason="environment">now he’s almost as enthusiastic as I am. </unstress>
      </p>
      <p>When you come I’ll show you a few prints which, once seen, won’t lightly fade from memory.
      Among them there are things very different from the school of Boughton, say, although he’s
      certainly one of the leaders. I mean things remarkable at once for their reality and their
      style, drawn like Albrecht Dürer but with lots of local colour and chiaroscuro. You don’t
      often see those prints any more these days; for you have to look for them in magazines of 10
      or 15 years ago. For example, during the war of 70-71. </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
