<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>Saturday, 27 May 1882.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Today, Saturday, I had a visit from Rappard, and I’m glad that now he has been here.
                  He also asked after you with great interest. He saw <work mention="vague">the drawings</work> I’m doing for
                  C.M. among other things, and they seem to please him, especially a large one of
                  the courtyard or back yard at the house where Sien’s mother lives. I would like
                  you to see that one, as well as another of a carpenter’s shed and yard with small
                  figures at work. The perspective is rather more complicated than in the Laan van
                  Meerdervoort I sent you, and I’ve laboured long and hard on it. I must tell you
                  that these days I’m already out of doors by 4 o’clock in the morning, because
                  during the day it’s too difficult to be on the street on account of the passers-by
                  and the urchins, and because that’s the best time to see the broad outlines while
                  things still have tone. But, old chap, this has been an anxious fortnight for me.
                  When I wrote to you around the middle of May, all I had left was 3 or 3.50
                  guilders after paying the baker. I had practically nothing else to eat but dry
                  black bread with a little coffee, and Sien too. Because we’d bought linen for her
                  baby and she’d been to Leiden &amp;c. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">The rent is due on 1 June, and I have nothing, literally nothing.</stress> I hope you’ll send
                  something. <bad_health>A week ago I was terribly weak due to constant sleeplessness</bad_health>. But now
                  I’m making good progress with<work origin="new" stage="middle"> several drawings</work>, so that the order for C.M. is well
                  advanced, and as a result I’m in better spirits,<good_health> I’m somewhat calmer again</good_health>. Still,
                  old chap, write to me soon and save me from the landlord, because, as you know,
                  their kind brook no delay. <unstress reason="friendship">Rappard’s visit cheered me up</unstress>; he seems to be working
                  hard. He gave me 2.50 guilders because he saw a tear in a drawing and said, you
                  should have that repaired. I know, I said,<stress reason="money"> but I haven’t got the money and the
                  drawing must be sent off.</stress> Then he said straightaway that he’d be glad to give it
                  to me, and I could have had more but I didn’t want to, and I gave him a pile of
                  woodcuts and a drawing in return. It was one of those meant for C.M., and so I was
                  very glad to be able to get it repaired, because it was the best of them all. </p>
      <p>That same drawing may be sold later for 50 guilders or so, and now — I hadn’t got the
                  money to have a tear in it repaired. Anyway.</p>
      <p>I do hope, brother, that you don’t think badly of Sien and me. That lass has put up
                  with my disagreeable side, and in many respects she understands me better than
                  others. She’s so willing to help in everything that I can’t tell you how useful
                  she is to me. If I get angry while she’s posing or about something else, she knows
                  how to take it, and has seen that it doesn’t go deep with me. <unstress reason="love">Equally, if I fret
                  or grumble about something that isn’t going well, she often manages to calm me
                  down, which I couldn’t do mysel</unstress>f. And she’s thrifty and accepts our piece of black
                  bread if need be, without becoming despondent. And so do I, as long as we get by.
                  I hope that you’ve received <work origin="existing" stage="finished">the drawings I sent around 10 May, I think, two dozen
                  in a portfolio</work>. I’ve heard nothing about it yet. I do wish there were a few more
                  people I could do work for on the same sort of conditions as for C.M. And above
                  all that C.M. perseveres, for these drawings are much better than the first, and
                  gradually I’ll produce even better ones. And at that price, he can’t go wrong. </p>
      <p>You know all about it: I’ll be in good spirits as long as you don’t desert me because
                  of Sien. I’m at work on the dot of 4, so with a little sympathy from those who
                  know me I’ll get on top of things. I’m hoping for your letter. Accept a handshake
                  in thought, but above all write soon and save me from the landlord. Adieu.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
