<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>Saturday, 25 February 1882.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I received your last letter with the 100 francs enclosed in good order, and I
                  sincerely thank you for sending it. I’d have sent you news of its safe receipt
                  immediately, but I’ve been very busy with a <work mention="unnamed">couple of drawings</work> for which I had a
                  model. For I’ll have you know that if you’re busy, so am I, and will be so more
                  and more, because I’m getting more of an eye for my work, and so can tear myself
                  away from it only with a great effort in order to write or to go and visit someone
                  if necessary. <unstress reason="friendship">What made me happy was that you write that you may be coming to
                  Holland soon</unstress>. When you’ve seen what I’ve been doing recently, perhaps we’ll have a
                  better idea of the future. When you come, I hope we’ll have some quiet time
                  together in the studio, and I also hope that you’ll write to me in advance, so
                  that I can arrange with the model not to come during the days of your visit.</p>
      <p>You write about Pa’s birthday, I must say that I feel so good to have done with
                  everything, it’s such a tranquillity, which I need so much in my work, my head
                  can’t hold more than it does. And now I dread starting up a new correspondence, so
                  much so that I’m quietly leaving things as they are for the present. <stress reason="career">When I was
                  still at home I worried about it, but now that things have come to this, what can
                  one do</stress>? Ignore everything and pretend that nothing happened – Pa and Ma might be
                  able to do that, but I can’t – I feel that, sadly, something did in fact happen.
                  When I think of Etten, a kind of shiver runs down my body as though I were in a
                  church. In short, what can be done, and again, what can be done?</p>
      <p>Besides, you mustn’t blame me, Theo, or think that I’m carping, but you wrote
                  something to me which you perhaps thought would make me happy, but it didn’t make
                  me happy. You said that that <work mention="unnamed">small watercolour </work>is the best thing of mine you’ve
                  seen – well, that isn’t true, because those studies of mine you have are much
                  better, and the pen drawings of last summer are also better, because that little
                  drawing means nothing; anyhow, I only sent it to you to show that my working with
                  watercolour at some point wasn’t an impossibility. But there’s much more serious
                  study and more substance in those other things, despite the fact that they still
                  look yellow-soap-like. And if I had something against Mr Tersteeg (but I don’t
                  have anything against him), then it would be the same thing. Namely that he
                  encourages me not to undertake difficult study from a model but rather to adopt a
                  procedure that’s actually only half suited to the rendering of what I want to
                  express, according to my own character and according to my own temperament. It
                  goes without saying that I’d be very happy to sell a drawing, but it makes me much
                  happier if a true artist like Weissenbruch says of an unsaleable (???) study or
                  drawing, that’s faithful and I’d be able to work from that. You see, although I
                  place great value on money, especially now, still, for me the No. 1 thing is to
                  make something that’s reasonable. Well, something like what Weissenbruch said of a
                  landscape, a peat moor, Mauve said it of a figure, namely an old peasant sitting
                  by the fireplace, thinking or daydreaming, as though seeing things from the
                  distant past taking shape in the glow of the fire or the smoke. It may take a
                  longer or shorter time, but the way is really to penetrate deeply into nature. To
                  be true is what remains, says Gavarni. One may be caught up for a time in petty
                  pecuniary vexations, but one will surmount them, and the drawings that were
                  rejected earlier will then be sold. </p>
      <p>I’ve written to C.M. to tell him that I’d taken a studio here, and he wrote back
                  saying that he expected to be coming to The Hague soon and would come and visit
                  me. Recently I was also given regards from my old friend Wisselingh from London,
                  who’s also supposed to come, and he was glad that I was working. Well, I hope
                  you’ll succeed in escaping, because I’m longing to see you. I think that when
                  you’ve seen my recent studies you’ll agree completely with my taking a model
                  regularly. The better I get to know the models, the better I can draw them, of
                  course. And I’ve been rather lucky in finding models. Today, now as I’m writing to
                  you, I have a child that has to rest once in a while for half an hour, and I’m
                  using that half-hour for this letter. Thanks again for what you sent, and a
                  handshake in thought, adieu,</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>P.S. I’ve made two studies of the child today. It’s getting dark now. Good-night.
            </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
