<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>, <date>1 July 1882</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I’ve been back in my studio for a few hours and am writing to you immediately. <good_health>I
                  can’t tell you how wonderful it is to be better again</good_health>, or <unstress reason="environment">how beautiful everything
                  looked on the road from the hospital to here</unstress>. And how the light seemed brighter
                  and the spaces bigger, and all the objects and figures more important. There’s a
                  ‘but’, though, and that ‘but’ is that I’ll <bad_health>again have a catheter or a thick lead
                  probe in my bladder, for next Tuesday I have to go back to the doctor and tell him
                  how I’ve been getting on, and he has prepared me for the fact that I may then have
                  to go into hospital for another fortnight, possibly longer, possibly shorter,
                  depending on what’s needed</bad_health>. At any rate I would be absolutely delighted if I
                  didn’t have to go in again. As soon as I feel anything wrong I have to go back,
                  and even if I don’t notice anything I’ll go on Tuesday to be examined again. The
                  channel through which the urine passes must gradually be widened, but this can’t
                  be forced or rushed. The probes gradually become thicker, and each time a new one
                  goes in everything is stretched a little further, and that’s painful, but above
                  all extremely unpleasant, particularly because the thing is left in place for a
                  time. Blood comes out when it’s removed, and then you feel relatively free for a
                  few days, while the pain it causes disappears. I’m now here in one of those
                  intervals. Meanwhile I can now pass water quite easily once more,<unstress reason="environment"> which makes me
                  feel on top of the world</unstress>, as if it were something very special. But it must become
                  entirely normal, and that will take time. Yet the sense of getting better makes
                  you forget all the catheters and probes and instillations... until you see the
                  doctor approaching with them again. And that isn’t a very pleasant moment. Well,
                  such are the petty troubles of life. But what one might call a ‘great trouble’ is
                  pregnancy and delivery — <stress reason="friendship">the latest letter from Sien was very melancholy</stress>. She
                  hadn’t yet given birth but was expecting to at any hour, and I feel very worried,
                  because this waiting has been going on for days. It was chiefly to be able to
                  visit her that I asked the doctor to change the walks in the garden into a short
                  leave of absence, if it was at all possible. So tomorrow morning I’m going to see
                  her with her mother and child, Sunday being the only day on which she’s allowed
                  visitors. Her last letter to me wasn’t written by herself but by the nurse, who
                  herself asked that we should come sometime. Yet we may still find that we aren’t
                  allowed in. Poor lass, she’s full of courage and not easily frightened, but
                  according to that last letter there was nothing in particular wrong except for
                  inner frailty. I can’t tell you how I longed for her in the hospital and how I
                  long for her now, and at times I wasn’t sorry that <bad_health>I had to cope with some
                  suffering myself</bad_health>, rather than standing there in excellent health, for then it
                  would have been very unevenly divided. If all goes well, though, Sien will be back
                  this month, may that prove to be the case. But the proverb says ‘A mother’s pains
                  are long-lasting’. This casts a dark shadow over the wonderful feeling of getting
                  better. I’m longing for tomorrow and dreading it at the same time. </p>
      <p>The first person I came across here in Schenkweg was my friend the carpenter, who has
                  helped me on several occasions with one job or another to do with making
                  instruments for perspective. And who’s also the foreman for the owner of the
                  studio I wrote to you about. His boss was just at the yard (the drawing of which
                  you have, with meadows in the distance), and they coaxed me into going along, and
                  showed me how they had left the room that would be the studio unpapered pending my
                  decision. I said I still couldn’t decide. Fine, said the man, but I could choose
                  what I wanted from a batch of wallpapers, then he would put it up and I wouldn’t
                  be under any obligation. And even though I said I didn’t want that, since I had to
                  go back to the hospital, they’ve already started work, because they insist on
                  showing me it before Tuesday. I must say the house is very comfortable and looks
                  really large and smart. The huge, fully panelled attic alone would make a superb
                  studio if need be, although the room facing north was going to be the studio. And
                  the price is unusually low for here; in the city it would be about double. Three
                  guilders a week for a large upstairs flat is very little, even in comparison with
                  neighbourhoods like Noordwal or the Buitensingels. And the location is excellent
                  for a painter. There’s one view from the attic window that’s enchanting. Still, I
                  didn’t want to take a decision <bad_health>because both Sien and I are sick</bad_health>. But I’ll take the
                  matter up again as soon as we’re better. There is air and space, wonderful to work
                  in and keep healthy. Light from the north, and in the other room roughly from the
                  south. There’s a small kitchen I really hope to draw a lot, also with a little
                  window overlooking a sort of courtyard. I mustn’t forget to tell you that, most
                  unexpectedly, I had a visit in the hospital from Mr Tersteeg, <unstress reason="friendship">which gave me great
                  pleasure in one sense</unstress>, although we didn’t talk about anything special, nor is that
                  necessary. But I thought it very kind. Then a few days later Iterson came as well,
                  about which I cared much less.</p>
      <p> And then Johan van Gogh, who I thought was in Helvoirt but turns out to be living in
                  Stationsweg these days. He told me that he, too, had had a bunch of catheters and
                  other musical instruments in his bladder once. Given that he appears to be free of
                  them now, I hope there’ll be an end to it in my case as well. It would be too bad
                  if a person had such adornments for a long time — it would be hard to climb stairs
                  or show yourself in public. If you send me something at the beginning of this
                  month, you should address the letter to the hospital. It will be all right,
                  because the porter has promised me to keep letters if I’m away (this is allowed
                  under hospital rules as long as one isn’t finally discharged and puts in a
                  request). On Tuesday I have to pay for the hospital again, and the rent that I owe
                  as well. <unstress reason="career">But the finest thing of all about getting better is that my drawing is
                  coming back to life</unstress>, together with my feeling for things, which was drugged, so to
                  speak, for a time, and was a great void. I again enjoy everything I see. And then,
                  I haven’t smoked a pipe in about a month — that’s another old friend back. I can’t
                  tell you with what pleasure I sit here again in the studio after spending so long
                  in an environment of chamber-pots &amp;c., even though the hospital is also
                  beautiful, truly beautiful. Especially the garden with all the strollers, men,
                  women, children. I have a few scratches, but as a patient you aren’t free to work
                  as it ought to be done, and not up to it either. Well, adieu, write soon, and
                  believe me, with a handshake</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
