<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>Wednesday, 3 January <year>1883</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I wrote to you yesterday, but I’m doing so again today to report the safe
    arrival of your letter and to thank you for it, and to tell you that <unstress reason="friendship">what you wrote raised my
    spirits.</unstress> I was a bit concerned that, because you’ve seen so little of my work recently, this
    might make you think that I’d begun to slacken off. I have in fact been slogging away lately,
    and am still wrapped up in various things in which I begin to see light as to how to do them,
    but which I haven’t yet got the hang of as I would like. In my last letter I told you I was
    experimenting in Black and White with lithographic crayon. You speak too highly of me in your
    letter, <unstress reason="love">but the fact that you think highly of me is an added reason for me to try not to be
    entirely unworthy of it.</unstress> And as for my saying I believed I had made some progress through those
    experiments, it may be that I can’t see my own work properly. Perhaps it’s a step forward,
    perhaps not. Tell me your opinion about that based on the <work origin="new" stage="middle">accompanying two studies, which I made
    in the past few days, together with some others.</work>
      </p>
      <p>While I search for a more powerful process than
    the one I’ve worked with up to now, I try to be guided to some extent by the English
    reproductions made using the process you described — together with the black scratches Buhot
    made on the sample paper — as to the strength of black. And if you get a chance, speak to an
    expert about whether it would be possible to reproduce drawings like these (as distinct from the
    second question of whether these or similar ones were to their particular taste). As for their
    sentiment, I would like to know what YOU think about that, because, as I said, I myself can’t
    judge whether there’s more in them or not. Or rather, my position is that for my part I’d rather
    see studies like these, even though they’re unfinished and even if much is completely neglected,
    than drawings that have a subject, because through them I get a vivid memory of nature itself.
    You’ll understand what I mean.</p>
      <p>True studies have something of life itself, and the person who
    makes them will respect not himself but nature in them, and hence prefer the study to what he
    may make of it later. Unless something entirely different arises from it as the final outcome of
    many studies, namely the type distilled from many individuals. That is the highest art, and in
    that art is sometimes above nature — — — as, for instance, in Millet’s sower, in which there is
    more soul than in an ordinary sower in the field.</p>
      <p>But what I’d like to know from you is whether
    you think that this way of working would perhaps remove some of the objections you had to
    pencil. They’re a few ‘heads of the people’, and my intention would be to find a large number
    like these to try to form a sort of entity that wouldn’t be entirely unworthy of the title
    ‘heads of the people’. Through working hard, old chap, I hope to make something good one day. I
    haven’t got it yet, but I’m hunting it and fighting for it, I want something serious, something
    fresh — something with soul in it! Onward, onward. You’ll see clearly enough from what I’ve said
    above that I’m more eager to put together a serious work for reproduction than to have the
    satisfaction of seeing one drawing printed some day. But any information and tips as to
    processes are very welcome.</p>
      <p>In the window at G&amp;Cie I saw a large etching by Fortuny, An
    anchorite, as well as his two beautiful The dead Kabyle and Watching over the dead man — then I
    deeply regretted saying to you not long ago that I didn’t find Fortuny beautiful – this I found
    extremely beautiful. Well, you’ll understand that yourself. It’s the same with Boldini too. But
    that seriousness that Fortuny had, for instance, in those three etchings is just what’s missing
    with many of his followers, who completely follow in his wake with a manner for which F. set the
    example in, say, ‘The choice of a model’ &amp;c. And that is the direct opposite of the sombre,
    noble quality of Brion, of Degroux, Israëls &amp;c. When you can, do send me an issue of the
    current Vie Moderne, look for one with reproductions like the ones you wrote about. The magazine
    is nowhere to be found here (and what I have ((a few issues)) is years old). I’ll show you more
    when you come, sooner or later — and then we can talk about the future.</p>
      <p>You know well enough how
    little suited I am to approaching either dealers or art lovers, and moreover how it goes against
    the grain for me. I so dearly wish that we could always carry on as in the past, <stress reason="friendship">but I’m often
    so sad about having to trouble you again and again.</stress> But who knows whether in time it mightn’t be
    possible for you to interest someone or other who could take the load off your shoulders that
    you’ve borne in the most difficult time. That could be done when it’s clearly evident that my
    work is serious, at which time it will have more appeal than this. I’m too fond of my very
    simple life to want to change it, but later on we’ll have to incur greater expenses to do
    greater things.</p>
      <p>I believe I’ll always work with a model a lot — always and always. And I must
    get things to the point where not everything rests on your shoulders. This is only a beginning —
    later you’ll get fine things from me, old chap! For the time being, let me know whether you
    think some of the objections to using pencil alone could be removed somewhat by using crayon as
    well. Don’t you also agree that by making these drawings I may also indirectly learn things
    about lithography proper? </p>
   </body>
   <close>Adieu, thanks again for your letter, with a handshake.</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent.</sig>
</letter>
