<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>11 July 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I had already been looking out for your letter, more or less, and was again glad of
                  it. Thank you. I find what you write about the exhibition most interesting. What
                  was that old painting by Dupré that you thought especially beautiful? You must
                  write again to tell me. Your description of Troyon and Rousseau, for instance, is
                  lively enough to give me some idea of which of their manners they are done in. </p>
      <p>There were other paintings from the time of Troyon’s municipal pasture that had a
                  certain mood that one would have to call dramatic, even though they aren’t figure
                  paintings. Israëls put it perfectly in the case of a Jules Dupré (Mesdag's large
                  one): ‘It’s just like a figure painting’. It’s that dramatic quality that causes
                  one to find a je ne sais quoi in it that makes one feel what you say, ‘It
                  expresses that moment and that place in nature where one can go alone, without
                  company.’ </p>
      <p>Ruisdael’s Bush has it strongly too. </p>
      <p>Haven’t you ever seen old Jacques that were perhaps a little overdone, a little
                  straining for effect — but not really — and for that reason were thought
                  particularly beautiful, even though not everyone considered them to be among the
                  finest Jacques? </p>
      <p>Speaking of Rousseau, do you know Richard Wallace’s Rousseau? An edge of a wood in
                  the autumn after rain, with a vista of meadows stretching away endlessly, marshy,
                  with cows in them, the foreground rich in tone. To me that’s one of the finest —
                  is very like the one with the red sun in the Luxembourg. </p>
      <p>The dramatic effect of these paintings is something that helps us to understand ‘a
                  corner of nature seen through a temperament’ and that helps us understand that the
                  principle of ‘man added to nature’ is needed more than anything else in art, and
                  one finds the same thing in Rembrandt’s portraits, for example — it’s more than
                  nature, more like a revelation. And it seems good to me to respect that, and to
                  keep quiet when it’s often said that it’s overdone or a manner. Oh, I must tell
                  you that De Bock came round — very pleasant. <unstress reason="friendship">Breitner, whom I didn’t in the least expect because he had apparently
                        broken off contact completely some time ago, turned up yesterday. That
                        pleased me because in the past — when I was first here — he was very
                        pleasant to go walking with. I mean to go out together not in the country
                        but in the city itself, to look for figures and nice scenes.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>Here in The Hague there isn’t a single person I've ever done that with in the city
                  itself; most think the city ugly and pass by all of it. And yet it’s really
                  beautiful in the city sometimes, don’t you agree? </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">Yesterday, for example, I saw workmen in Noordeinde
                        pulling down that part opposite the palace, chaps covered in white from the
                        clouds of plaster dust with carts and horses. It was cool, windy weather,
                        the sky grey, and there was great character in the scene.</unstress> I saw
                  Van der Velden once last year — at De Bock’s one evening when we looked at
                  etchings. I’ve already written to you that he made a very favourable impression on
                  me at the time, although he said little and wasn’t much company that evening. But
                  the impression he immediately made on me was that he was a solid, genuine
                  painter.</p>
      <p>It’s a square, Gothic head — something bold or daring, and yet gentle in his look.
                  Very broad build, in fact the exact opposite of Breitner and De Bock. There’s
                  something manly and strong in him, even if he says nothing and does nothing
                  special. I do hope I’ll get in closer touch with him at some point, perhaps
                  through Van der Weele. Was at Van der Weele’s last Sunday; he was working on a
                  painting of cows in the milking yard, for which he has several substantial
                  studies. He’s moving to the country for some time.Of late I’ve done a few
                  watercolours outdoors again for a change, <work origin="new" stage="finished">a
                        cornfield</work> and <work origin="new" stage="finished">a bit of a potato
                        field</work>. <work mention="vague">And also drawn a few small landscapes,
                        to have something to go by for the settings of a few figure drawings that
                        I’m looking for.</work>
      </p>
      <p>These are the designs of the figure drawings, very superficially. Above, weed
                  burners, below, coming back from the potato field.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">I’m seriously considering painting a number of
                        figure studies, mainly with a view to raising the standard of the
                        drawings.</work> It’s good news for me that you’re planning to come to
                  Holland at the beginning of August, for I’ve said often enough that I dearly long
                  to see you.</p>
      <p>I’m looking forward to hearing from you sometime as to how informed your woman is
                  about art. In any event, much will have to be done and cultivated in that respect,
                  I imagine. So much the better. In any case I hope she’ll get a sort of album, for
                  which I hope you’ll find a few sheets among the smaller studies. Sometimes there
                  are sheets in a sketchbook which still say something, even though they’re only
                  scratches. I’ll gather one or two things together before you come. </p>
      <p>Well, I’ve spoken to De Bock again and I can leave my stuff with him when I go to do
                  studies in Scheveningen. </p>
      <p>I also hope to go and see Blommers again soon. I talked to De Bock about his painting
                  at the Salon, November, which I thought so beautiful, and the reproduction in the
                  catalogue. He should still have a sketch of it, and I’d like to see it. </p>
      <p>As for going to London sooner or later for a while, long or short, I too believe that
                  there would be more chance of doing something with my work over there; I also
                  think that I could learn a great deal if I could make the acquaintance of some
                  people there. And there I wouldn’t be short of subjects to do, I assure you. There
                  would be beautiful things to do on the wharves beside the Thames. Anyway, we must
                  talk about various things again when you come. I hope you won’t be in too much of
                  a hurry; we’ll have rather a lot to deal with. I’d like to be able to get some
                  studies in Brabant again in the autumn. </p>
      <p>Above all I’d like to have studies of a Brabant plough, of a weaver and of that
                  village cemetery at Nuenen. Again, everything costs money.</p>
      <p>Well, regards, and thanks again for your letter and the enclosure. I wish you well.
                  Do you think about bringing the woman to Holland, or is that not advisable as yet?
                  I hope it happens. Adieu, old chap, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>I’m adding a word here to tell you something more about Breitner as well — since I’ve
                  just come back from his temporary studio here (you know that he really lives in
                  Rotterdam these days). You know Vierge or Urrabieta, the draughtsman for
                  L’Illustration. Well, at times B. reminds me of Vierge, but very rarely. </p>
      <p>When he’s good it looks like something done in haste by Vierge; but when he, that is
                  B., is too hasty or doesn’t work things through, which is usually the case, it’s
                  difficult to say what it resembles, for it looks like nothing — except like strips
                  of an old, faded wallpaper from I don’t know which era, but in any event a very
                  singular one, probably from long ago. Imagine, I go to the garret that he has at
                  Siebenhaar’s. It was furnished mainly with various matchboxes (empty), and then
                  with a razor or something, and a cupboard with a bed in it. I see something
                  leaning against the chimney, 3 endlessly long strips that I at first think are sun
                  blinds. But on closer inspection they turn out to be canvases in this format. As
                  you see from the above illustration, painted with a not unmystical scene, probably
                  taken from Revelation, one would imagine at first sight. </p>
      <p>Yet I’m informed that they are artillery manoeuvres in the dunes. Off the cuff I
                  would put it at over 4 metres long by 3/4 of a metre. </p>
      <p>The second was a story of a man who was leaning against the wall on the extreme left
                  of the painting, while on the far right various types of ghostly women stood
                  gawking at him, while care had been taken to leave a substantial space between
                  these two groups. I was then informed that what was depicted in the lefthand
                  corner was a drunkard, and I wouldn’t venture to doubt that this may just as well
                  have been the maker’s intention as something else.The third is almost better, and
                  is a sketch of the market that he did last year, but since then it seems it’s
                  meant to depict a Spanish instead of a Dutch market, in so far as one can make
                  anything of it. </p>
      <p>Whatever merchandise is sold at the market (wherever it’s located, I for one doubt
                  whether it’s meant to be on this earth; it’s much more likely to strike the naive
                  beholder as portraying a scene on one of those planets visited by Jules Verne’s
                  miraculous travellers (by projectile)) – whatever merchandise really is being
                  traded is impossible to make out, but it’s faintly reminiscent of a huge mass of
                  preserves or sweets. You see, try to picture such a thing, but it couldn’t be more
                  absurd, and heavyhanded as well, and you have the work of Friend Breitner. </p>
      <p>From a distance they’re areas of faded colour as on bleached and rotting and
                  mouldering wallpaper, and in that sense there are qualities in it that are
                  absolutely unpalatable to me.</p>
      <p>I utterly fail to understand how anyone could possibly come up with something like
                  that. It’s the sort of thing one sees when one has a fever — or impossible and
                  meaningless as in a dream that makes no sense at all. I take the view, quite
                  simply, that Breitner isn’t yet cured, and actually did it while he had a fever.
                  Which, given his illness last year, may be considered entirely possible. Last year
                  when I was cured but still couldn’t sleep and was feverish, I too had moments when
                  I wanted to force myself to work all the same and did some things, though thank
                  God not so absurdly big, and later on I couldn’t understand why I’d done them.</p>
      <p>This is why I think that B. will be all right in the end, but I find this absurd. In
                  a corner lay a crumpled watercolour study of some birches in the dunes that was
                  much better and had nothing abnormal about it. But those big things are nothing. </p>
      <p>I saw another one at Van der Weele’s, very ugly, and a head, very good, but a
                  portrait of Van der W. — that he’d started — again bad. </p>
      <p>So he’s making a terrible mess on a very big scale. I like the work of Hoffmann and
                  Edgar Poe on occasion. (Contes fantastiques, Raven &amp;c.) But I find this
                  unpalatable because the fantasy is heavyhanded and without meaning, and there are
                  almost no correspondences to what exists. I find it very ugly. </p>
      <p>But I regard it as a period of illness. Van der Weele has two rather curious drawings
                  by him, elegantly done in watercolour, which have a certain je ne sais quoi of
                  what the English call ‘weird’.</p>
      <p>I learned a lesson today from that visit, namely that one can count oneself lucky if
                  one is in relatively normal surroundings in today’s society, and doesn’t have to
                  seek refuge in a coffeehouse life which will make one begin to see things ever
                  more cloudily and confusedly. For the latter is his situation, about that I have
                  no doubt. Imperceptibly he has strayed terribly far from a calm, rational
                  contemplation of things, and now he can’t put down a single calm, reasonable line
                  or brushstroke as long as this stress continues. </p>
      <p>I wish I could offer him some company and diversion, I wish I could often take a turn
                  with him and perhaps make him a little calmer. You remember the painting The
                  madness of Hugo van der Goes by Wauters? In some things B. faintly reminds me of a
                  state of mind like Van der Goes’s. I’d not like to be the first to say this, but I
                  believe his work has already been discussed in these terms for some considerable
                  time.The remedy would be to look at length at the potato leaves that are so deep
                  and elegant in colour and tone at present, instead of driving himself mad looking
                  at lengths of yellow satin and pieces of gilt leather. </p>
      <p>Anyway, we’ll see how it goes. He’s intelligent enough, but it’s a kind of bias
                  towards eccentricity that he persists in regardless. If he deviated from the
                  normal for a reasonable motive, well and good, but here it’s a question of not
                  taking any trouble with his work either. I find it truly wretched and I hope he
                  recovers, but he has lost his way badly.</p>
      <p>This week I’m going to start in Scheveningen. I would have liked there to be room for
                  a little extra, then I would have bought some painting materials. </p>
      <p>I’m going to have photographs taken of a few drawings in cabinet format or slightly
                  larger (to see how they’d look on a small scale) by a photographer who has
                  photographed those drawings by Ter Meulen, Du Chattel, Zilcken. He does it for 75
                  cents, that’s not expensive, is it? I’ll have the sower and the Peat diggers done
                  for now, the one with many smaller figures, the other with 1 large figure. And if
                  they work, later on when I have drawings I’ll be able to send you photos to show
                  to Buhot, say, to see if he thinks he can place them. They could have the drawings
                  themselves of the ones they want for reproduction or I can redraw them on their
                  paper. </p>
      <p>Regards again, Theo. Best wishes. </p>
      <p>Do write again soon. I’ll have the photos taken, for we must stick to our guns with
                  Buhot &amp; Cie. I must try to earn a little so that I can make a start on
                  something new and do some painting too, for I’m just in the mood for that. Mauve
                  not only had some unpleasantness with me but also, to give an example, had
                  unpleasantness with Zilcken. It’s only now that I’ve seen Z.’s etchings, and just
                  now photos of drawings by Zilcken at the photographer’s. Leaving myself out of it,
                  I hereby declare that I don’t understand what M. has against Z. His drawings were
                  good and not in the least bad; it’s capriciousness on Mauve’s part. <stress reason="friendship">After all, I don’t think it very nice of C.M. that I
                        haven’t received one syllable in reply to my letter, in which I took the
                        trouble to do two croquis of the drawings in question.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="friendship">Nor do I think it nice of H.G.T. that he didn’t pay a
                        call after I’d made an attempt to break the ice.</stress> It’s rubbish to
                  say that he’s busy, because that’s not the reason in this case, he could find the
                  time to come once a year.I’m adding half a page to talk about Brabant. Among the
                  figures of types from the people that I did there are several with a certain, what
                  many would call oldfashioned, character, also in the approach. For example, a
                  digger who’s more like those one sometimes finds in the basreliefs carved in wood
                  on Gothic pews than a contemporary drawing. I very often think of the Brabant
                  figures, which I find especially sympathetic.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">Something I’d like to have terribly much, and
                        which I feel I can do, given certain conditions of patient posing, is the
                        figure of Pa on a path on the heath, the figure severely drawn with
                        character and, as I say, a stretch of brown heath with a narrow, white,
                        sandy path running across it, and a sky applied with some passion and evenly
                        expressed.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">Then, for instance, Pa and Ma arm in arm — in an
                        autumn setting — or with a beech hedge with dry leaves.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">I’d also like to have the figure of Pa when I do a
                        country funeral, which I’m definitely planning, although it would be a great
                        deal of trouble.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Leaving aside irrelevant differences in religious views, to me the figure of a poor
                  village pastor is one of the most sympathetic in type and character that there is,
                  and I wouldn’t be myself if I didn’t attack it sometime. </p>
      <p>When you come I’d truly like to consult you on what to do about travelling over
                  there. When you see my drawings of orphan men, for instance, you’ll understand
                  what I want and how I mean it. My aim is to do a drawing that not exactly everyone
                  will understand, the figure expressed in its essence in simplified form, with
                  deliberate disregard of those details that aren’t part of the true character and
                  are merely accidental. Thus it shouldn’t, for example, be the portrait of Pa but
                  rather the type of a poor village pastor going to visit a sick person. The same
                  with the couple arm in arm by the beech hedge — the type of a man and woman who
                  have grown old together and in whom love and loyalty have remained, rather than
                  portraits of Pa and Ma, although I hope they’ll pose for it. But they must know
                  that it’s serious, which they might not see for themselves if the likeness isn’t
                  exact.</p>
      <p>And should be a bit prepared, in the event that this happens, for having to pose as I
                  say and not change anything. Well, that will be all right, and I don’t work so
                  slowly as to make it a great effort for them. And for my part I would greatly
                  value doing it. Simplifying the figures is something that very much preoccupies
                  me. Anyway, you’ll see some for yourself among the figures I’ll show you. If I
                  went to Brabant, it should certainly not be an excursion or pleasure trip, it
                  seems to me, but a short period of very hard work at lightning speed. Speaking of
                  expression in a figure, I’m becoming more and more persuaded that it lies not so
                  much in the features as in the whole manner. I find few things as horrible as most
                  academic facial expressions. I would rather look at ‘Night’ by Michelangelo, or a
                  drunk by Daumier, or The diggers by Millet, and that large woodcut by him, The
                  shepherdess. Or at an old horse by Mauve &amp;c.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
