<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>on or about Sunday, 20 May <year>1883</year>.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I wanted to let you know in just a word or two that Rappard has been to see me
    and that I’ve borrowed 25 guilders from him, with the promise of repayment in the autumn. I was
    delighted by his visit — he came in the morning and stayed until the last train in the evening,
    and we spent the whole day looking at one thing and another, and he did a sketch using printer’s
    ink and turpentine to try it out. Now I’m going to him tomorrow to see his work and his studio.
    <unstress reason="environment">It was a truly enjoyable day</unstress> — he was rather changed in both his appearance and his manner — for
    my part I find him much better like this than before. He’s broader in the shoulders, and in his
    views on many matters as well, I believe.</p>
      <p>Well, the money from him has helped me to get many
    things I needed; it was badly needed. I used it, among other things, to have large sketchpads
    made for outdoors. I had to keep back some money for a pair of trousers, though, and tomorrow
    there’s the cost of travelling to Utrecht. But it still helps. In addition, I was surprised by a
    very brief visit from Pa. Neither he nor I mentioned your news about the woman. Pa probably
    thought I didn’t know yet, and I kept to our agreement. I think Pa was rather taken by the
    figures of workmen I’m working on. Among the pads I’d made with the money from R. there’s one
    for watercolours too. <work origin="new" stage="finished">I tried it out straightaway, a hut in the dunes with a wheelbarrow &amp;c.
    in the foreground, a figure of a digger in the background.</work> Ah, Theo. I’ll get the hang of
    watercolour one day or another.</p>
      <p>In the last few days, or rather weeks, I’ve had the very pleasant
    company outdoors of a young surveyor who was trying his hand at drawing. He showed me drawings
    which I thought poor, and I told him why I thought they were poor. After that I naturally
    expected to hear no more from him — <unstress reason="friendship">but one fine day he approached me again, he had time now and
    might he come with me outdoors?</unstress> Well, Theo, that chap has got the hang of landscape drawing so
    well that these days he brings along truly attractive sketches of meadows and woods and dunes.
    He has to take an examination in October, however, and his father doesn’t want him to spend so
    much time on it. But in my view he can easily combine his profession of surveyor with drawing.
    He’s the same sort of young chap as Rappard when we first met him. What he did before I knew him
    were horribly botched paintings, generally atrocious. I began by telling him that first he
    should only draw for a while — I had to make him draw lots of things, which he didn’t enjoy but
    he trusted me in that. Well, this morning he asked if he might have another go at painting, and
    that went extremely well now and he has scraped off all his old things.</p>
      <p>Am longing for a letter
    from you. Rappard sends his regards. Are things going well for you, and for your patient? Pa did
    say that you’d written to them about coming this summer. I can hardly tell you how I long for
    that. Saw The harvest by Lhermitte in the Salon illustrated catalogue. It looks beautiful; how
    it captures the truth of the work and of the peasant figure. Well, adieu, I hope your letter
    comes soon for I have need of it again. I saw Arnold in town with someone else, perhaps Tripp —
    they were walking with Mauve. But saw them in the far distance. Because Mauve was in the middle
    I thought of Christ between two thieves, or else the group, in dark silhouette against a sunlit
    wall, looked like someone being taken in by two gendarmes. Anyway, those are figments of one’s
    imagination, things as they might be seen.</p>
   </body>
   <close>I wish you well, old chap, with a handshake.</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent </sig>
</letter>
