<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Hoogeveen</location>
      <date>26 September 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>Dear brother,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Because I have a need to speak frankly, I can’t hide from you that I’m
                overcome by a feeling of great anxiety, dejection, a je ne sais quoi of
                discouragement and even despair, too much to express. And that if I can find no
                consolation for it, it might all too easily overwhelm me
            unbearably.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="friendship">It really bothers me that I have so little success with
                people in general, I’m very concerned about this, and all the more so because rising
                above it and getting on with the work is at stake here.</stress>
         <stress reason="love">The fate of the woman, moreover, the fate of my sweet, poor little
                lad and the other child, cut me to the quick. I’d still like to help and I
                can’t.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>I’m at a point where I need credit, trust and some warmth, and you see
                there’s no trust in me. You’re an exception to this, but precisely because
                everything falls on you it makes it even more apparent how dismal everything is in
                my case.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>And if I look at my things, they’re too poor, too inadequate, too much exhausted. <stress reason="environment">We’re having gloomy, rainy days here, and when I come into the
                corner of the attic where I’ve installed myself it’s all remarkably melancholy there
                — with the light from one single glass roof tile that falls on an empty painting
                box, on a bundle of brushes with few decent bristles remaining, well it’s so
                curiously melancholy that luckily it also has a funny enough side not to weep over
                it but to regard it more cheerfully.</stress> But even so, it’s in a very strange
            relationship to my plans — in a very strange relationship to the seriousness of the
            work, and — this is where the laughing stops.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">What else can I do? — last year ended with an even bigger deficit
                than I told you, for I’ve already paid off more than I mentioned to you, including
                Rappard,</stress> and <stress reason="friendship">still however owe Rappard above
                all, and that worries me the most because he’s a friend,</stress> and although at
            this moment I’ve paid off everything that was in the slightest bit urgent I’m faced with
            the problem that I still have to pay for other things before the paint that I would
            otherwise buy, or rather I don’t dare take it on credit, which would again cause me a
            considerable bill in time. You know yourself how we weren’t exactly in the mood to be
            able to say more during your visit, but I tell you now that The Hague has been too much
            for me, and I had already put off and put off the separation for one particular specific
            reason, even though the deficit was inevitable if I persisted. <stress reason="love">This was that, rather than separating, I would have risked one more attempt by
                marrying her and going to live with her in the country, although not without telling
                you how things stood. But I believed one thing, that this was the right course, even
                despite the temporary financial drawbacks, and that not only could it have been her
                salvation but would also have put an end to great inner struggle for me, which has
                now, unhappily, doubled for me. And I would rather have seen it through to the
                bitter end.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">If either Pa or you had been able to feel it thus, perhaps — I
                don’t say that I would have been happier or unhappier as a result, and if the roles
                had been reversed, you in my place, I in yours, I don’t know whether I would have
                been able to act other than as you did — but perhaps, I say, she would have been
                saved because of it.</stress> I therefore regard it as something where the decision
            depended not on you two, but on myself (except that I can’t give myself my father’s
            consent to marry, this single point is beyond me, and in response to a determined
            question Pa answered me in generalities in which, however, there was no hint of
            consent), and so I decided, because I already had debts and the future was dark.
                <bad_health>But this decision is not yet a renewal, and doesn’t take away the
                exhaustion that a year of too many cares brings in its train, while I’m also left
                with a wounded heart and a feeling of emptiness and disappointment and melancholy —
                not so easy to cure.</bad_health>
         <unstress reason="money">I may be here now, and may almost have covered the financial
                deficit, and in a while it could be entirely covered,</unstress>
         <unstress reason="environment">and nature is wonderful here and exceeds my
                expectations.</unstress>
         <bad_health>Yet I’m far from being comfortably settled again and getting on, because the
                little glimpse of my attic I’m giving you is drawn from life.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>If I’d known all these things in advance, I would have moved here with the woman last
            year when she came out of hospital, then there would have been no deficit and then we
            wouldn’t be separated now, for she’s less guilty of her wrongdoing than her family, who
            have intrigued very meanly, ostensibly for her but fundamentally against her. Meanwhile,
            I’ve sometimes wondered, for instance, whether the mother wasn’t also being backed in
            turn by a priest, because too much has been done on their part to influence the woman
            for me to explain. <stress reason="love">All the more so because I’ve still heard
                nothing from her, although before I left I told her that I would give the carpenter
                next door my address as soon as I knew it myself; I sent it to him and asked him to
                tell her, and I’ve still heard nothing, except just from this carpenter that she’s
                collected all her things (more than she brought with her, after all).</stress> Now
            you understand that I’m concerned about her fate, although I believe that if she were
            simply in need she’d have written, but now there must be something wrong behind it. You
            will understand my feeling about it, I rather fear that the family is saying to her:
            he’ll surely write and then... we’ll have him under our thumb — in short they’re
            presuming on my weakness and I am not going to walk into that trap. And today I’m
            writing not to her but to the carpenter to tell him that he must make sure she knows my
            address, but I will not write to her first, and if she writes will see how things
            actually stand. When I would definitely try to help is if her family were to cast her
            off entirely, and if it’s the case that her family is helping her, I understand well
            enough that she’s too much in agreement with them, and has been for a long time, so that
            I may not or cannot have anything more to do with it. Or, I’ve thought, if there’s a
            priest behind it, she’s being helped but only on condition that she has nothing more to
            do with me, and that’s the reason for her silence.</p>
      <p>But I’ll say that I haven’t yet got so far that I can resign myself to the idea of
            separation, at present I’m still very, very concerned about her fate, precisely because
            she’s leaving me in the dark about it.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>And over and above all this, I’ve been overwhelmed these past few days by
                sombre feelings about the future, and also about the miserable state of my equipment
                as far as painting materials are concerned, the impossibility of doing the most
                essential, most useful things as they really should be done.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">Since I can already see straightaway that there’s so much
                beauty here,</unstress> if I could afford it I would send for my things that are
            still there in The Hague, and I would either fit up this same attic here as a studio (by
            letting a bit more light in) or look for another place. And then I’d like to renew and
            replenish all my equipment. I wish that for once I could do this really thoroughly, and
            if I could find someone who would trust me that far, my greatest concerns would be
            allayed. <stress reason="money">But either everything falls on you or I find no one who
                trusts me, this is the circle in which my thoughts revolve, and I see no way
                out.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>A painter who has no means of his own can’t get by without sometimes rather large credit
            with people, credit that not only the profession of painter requires, but that the
            professions of cobbler, carpenter, smith would equally require, I believe no more nor
            less, if they had to set themselves up or reestablish themselves somewhere. <stress reason="environment">It’s above all in this rainy weather, of which we have months
                ahead of us, that my hands are really tied.</stress> And then, what else can I do?
                <bad_health>— sometimes my thoughts take on a form — I’ve worked and economized and
                still not been able to avoid debt, I’ve been faithful to the woman and yet lapsed
                into disloyalty, I’ve abhorred intrigues and yet I have virtually no credit or
                possessions. I don’t regard your trust in me lightly, on the contrary, but I rather
                wonder whether I shouldn’t say to you, forget about me for we won’t get there — it’s
                too much for one, and there’s no chance of getting any relief from another quarter —
                is this not proof enough that we should give up?</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>Oh, old chap, I’ve become so melancholy — <unstress reason="environment">I’m in
                magnificent countryside,</unstress>
         <stress reason="career">I have a desire, indeed an absolute need to work — at the same
                time I’m absolutely at a loss as to how we’re going to get on top of it, when I
                think that my things are in the most miserable state and I’m here without a studio
                or anything, and will be embarrassed everywhere until I can improve matters. The
                models — they refuse to pose if there are bystanders around, and this is the
                greatest difficulty that makes a studio desirable.</stress> I have the same feeling
            now as I did when I set up the studio in The Hague — ‘if I don’t do it, I’ll certainly
            not be able to manage’. And even now, given The Hague, I don’t regret that I did as I
            did in those circumstances, only I wish I had come here 1 1/2 years earlier and set up a
            studio here instead of there.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Pa wrote to me saying that he wanted to help me, but I didn’t let
                him know anything about my worries, and I hope that you won’t say anything to Pa on
                this subject either. Pa has his own worries, and would only have even more worries
                were he to find out that things aren’t going well.</stress> So I merely wrote to Pa
            that everything turned out much better than I expected, which is also perfectly true as
            far as nature is concerned. As long as the weather was good I wasn’t aware of things
            because I saw so much that was beautiful, but now that it’s been pouring with rain
            incessantly for several days I increasingly see how I’m actually stuck here, and I’m
            embarrassed. What’s to be done? Will things worsen or improve with time? I don’t know,
            but I feel really miserable and can’t shake it off.In every life some rain must fall</p>
      <p>And days be dark and drearythat is true, it cannot be otherwise, yet I wonder if the
            number of dark and dreary days can’t sometimes get too great? Nevertheless, I’ve had a
            model again in the barn, but in very trying light. After all, I don’t refuse to do what
            can be done, but can I do what MUST be done in the circumstances? And this letter is a
            sigh for space, and if the winter has to be like these days, I would be in a bad way.
            It’s beautiful, though, indeed extremely beautiful in the rain, but how does one work,
            how when one lacks too much? Adieu, old chap, I wish everything would turn out all
            right, but we need more trust from other people, otherwise I fear it won’t work. I hope
            to hear from you soon. <work mention="vague">Did you receive studies?</work>
      </p>
      <p>With a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
