<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>7 July 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo.</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>If you’re like me you sometimes have a sudden desire to look up someone you haven’t
                  seen in a long time. This is what happened to me with De Bock, and I wanted to
                  write to you about what I saw at his place. Because you also know him from the
                  past, even better than I do. The first thing I saw there in the hall was a large
                  sketch — an enormous windmill, entirely covered in snow, beside a kind of canal or
                  waterway. Half romantic, half realistic — a combination of styles I find not
                  unsympathetic. But it was far from finished — but energetically tackled, and there
                  was a fine, forceful effect in it. Anyway, something that one always sees with
                  pleasure, and it doesn’t bother me that it isn’t finished — I’d like to have that
                  piece by him hanging in my studio just as it is, because it’s so expressive.
                  Another sketch, that of the painting in the Salon, was also beautiful, I thought,
                  but even more romantic. There were also a few paintings with blonder accents,
                  various pleasing studies.</p>
      <p>The impression I got of him himself was just about the same as last year, perhaps a
                  shade more positive and more serious. I thought some sketches maturer and more
                  correct in tone and colour than last year, and the grounds firmer. But in my view
                  too much of the relative proportions of the planes and masses is still left vague;
                  keeping an eye on this sort of proportion is the hallmark of Corot and Rousseau
                  and Diaz, Daubigny, Dupré. What they all have in common, in my view, is that they
                  pay careful attention to that, and with them the backgrounds are always expressive
                  and not so disengaged.</p>
      <p>There are very spirited things in De Bock’s work, though, and one would view it with
                  more pleasure if the way things stand in their place was less visionary. He ought
                  to be rather more of a realist and then his work would be more brilliant. </p>
      <p>I also can’t understand why he doesn’t have some more variety. To give an example,
                        <work origin="new" stage="sketch">this week I did a few landscape studies as
                        well, one yesterday at De Bock’s, a potato field in the dunes; the day
                        before a spot under the chestnut trees; another, a yard with heaps of
                        coal.</work> Now it’s relatively rare for me to get round to drawing
                  landscape, but when I get round to it I immediately have 3 very different
                  subjects. Why doesn’t he, a specialized landscape painter, do that much, much more
                  instead of it always being a dune with a tree and a bit of marram grass? All very
                  fine in itself, but there’s so much that is just as fine and ought to attract him,
                  one would imagine. </p>
      <p>Anyway, you know all about that, again my impression of him is that he has most
                  certainly not gone downhill. Well, I wrote to you recently that I had been
                  thinking about moving, mainly in order to be closer to the sea. <stress reason="money">I talked to Bock about houses in Scheveningen, but I must
                        stop saying the rent for my studio is high when I compare it with the costs
                        that others have; for instance, the house where Blommers used to live is to
                        let — the rent is 400 guilders and I pay 170 guilders a year.</stress>
                  Moreover, the studio is no bigger than mine, and as for the suitability of the
                  house I would stick to what I have now. De Bock himself pays the same as Blommers.
                  And this is in line with what I heard last year about average rents. If it was a
                  question of going to live by the sea, Scheveningen wouldn’t be possible and one
                  would have to go further away, Hook of Holland, say, or Marken. </p>
      <p>Now, though, I’m thinking of asking De Bock to let me have a corner of his attic as a
                  piedàterre and then leaving my equipment there so that I don’t need to lug it
                  around. If one arrives tired (if one didn’t need to work immediately that slight
                  fatigue wouldn’t matter, of course), the work is sometimes weak and the hand is
                  none too steady. One is just hot and tired enough to be bothered by it if one
                  walks and has to lug everything around. </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">So that piedàterre at De Bock’s and taking the tram
                        more often might perhaps be enough to be able to do something with the sea
                        and Scheveningen after all, more seriously than I’ve done so far.</unstress>
                  De Bock is to come to my place this week and we’re to discuss it further. He’s
                  thinking of moving himself and has rented until May, and said that his house might
                  stand empty for several months after all. We’ll see. He asked after you warmly,
                  and I said you’d probably visit him this summer. His big painting in the Salon not
                  sold of course. What did you think of that? The reviews were rather mixed. I think
                  it will work out, to be at Scheveningen often this autumn with a piedàterre at his
                  place. We’ll see — but I yearn very much to do something with the beach. </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="sketch">Did a study this week of a barge puller and a peat
                        carrier</work> and <work origin="existing" stage="middle">I’m still working
                        on the potato grubbers.</work> I hope that, taking a turn now with Bock,
                  I’ll be able to get on with him; it could do both of us no harm, and perhaps we
                  can learn from each other. </p>
      <p>He’s bought a lot of antiques and his place looks very attractive, but I imagine it
                  must have cost him a great deal.</p>
      <p>Will you write soon? Now I’ve written to you about Bock as I did recently about
                  Rappard, that way you hear something about our acquaintances. Rappard is
                  travelling, still he wrote to me that he had got round after all to using
                  printer’s ink as I told him, and that it worked much better that way, namely with
                  turpentine. You know that I’ve always said my present studio was good, especially
                  after the alterations. <unstress reason="environment">Really, if I think now of
                        changing — I would much rather arrange things so that I don’t need to move,
                        because compared with others I’m very well off. Well, one is always attached
                        to something one has furnished oneself and one feels at home
                        there.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>See that you send me something soon, old chap, for I need it badly. </p>
      <p>De Bock has also taken to reading Zola and had read Le Nabab by Daudet as well. Do
                  you know Germinie Lacerteux by Jules and E. de Goncourt? That’s supposed to be
                  very good, in the manner of Zola. I’m going to get hold of it. </p>
      <p>I’ve ordered an instrument that’s known as a fixer which enables one to fix a
                  charcoal drawing out of doors while one works, then one can work it up. Am looking
                  forward to it. With Bock I’ve found splendid potato fields in the dunes behind the
                  lighthouse. </p>
      <p>Regards, old chap, I wish you well, and write soon. Adieu, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>Of late I’ve been absorbed in a drawing by Régamey of a diamond mine. At first sight
                  it’s no different from one of those superficial drawings the illustrated magazines
                  are full of — one is inclined to skip it — but if one looks at it for a moment
                  everything becomes so beautiful and so curious that one is entirely won over.
                  Régamey is clever. This print is by Félix, who often does the Japanese things.
            </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
