<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Hoogeveen</location>
      <date>24 September <year>1883</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <work mention="vague">Today I’m sending a package of 3 studies which I hope are dry
                enough.</work> However, if they stick to the sheet of paper I laid on them as a
            precaution, soak them off with lukewarm water. The smallest one, in particular, has sunk
            in a lot, go over it with the white of an egg in about a week, or some varnish in a
            month’s time, to lift them. I’m sending them to let you take a look, and better after
            this — really.</p>
      <p>I forgot to reply to what you write about sending the you know what. For the time being
            would you send a postal order like the last, until I know of an exchange office — deduct
            expenses, though. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Received a letter from home that Pa had been unwell as a result
                of a fall — I hope it isn’t more serious than they say.</stress> Do you know
            anything more about it?</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">Went further into the peat fields last week — marvellous
                scenes, the longer I stay here the more beautiful I find it, and from the outset
                I’ll try to stay here in this region.</unstress>
         <unstress reason="career">For it’s so beautiful here that at the same time a great deal
                of study is needed to capture it, and only solid work can give a truer understanding
                of things as they are at bottom, and of their serious, sober nature.</unstress> I
            came across superb figures — but again, a nature that has so much nobility, so much
            dignity and gravity must be treated with maturity and patience and prolonged work. This
            is why, in my view, from the outset I mustn’t regard it as just coming to take a look
            around here, but it’s in the nature of the thing, if all goes well and we’re granted a
            little good fortune, that I’ll stay for good. Write again soon, won’t you —
                <bad_health>I’m longing to hear, for despite all the beauty outside I still feel
                dejected.</bad_health> Adieu, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>My regards to Wisselingh when you see him, and tell him I’m here.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
