<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>6 September <year>1883</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I couldn’t yet go into detail about my plans in my last letter, but now I can in some
            respects.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="love">I’ll begin my telling you that I now know for certain that one
                thing and another that I already suspected as regards the woman is true — that
                recently she was negotiating about her future even before I’d come to the decision
                to separate. I had to decide to separate, precisely because I was almost as certain
                of that then as I am now that I know more exactly what the plans were.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Having taken the decision, I wanted to go ahead with my travel plans without delay. </p>
      <p>The first measure to be taken was to give notice to the landlord — that has now been
            done. </p>
      <p>The second measure is what to do with my things, which would be an encumbrance and lead
            to costs at a time of not knowing exactly where I’ll stay for long. They’ll stay here in
            this house in the attic, since I’ve agreed this with my landlord. You will ask, do I
            have plans to come back to The Hague then? No. </p>
      <p>But in, say, 1/2 a year or 1 year I may have to get in touch with some painters here,
            when I’ve got much further, when I have a batch of studies of the real countryside. </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="money">And then for a while I’ll probably take a room or rather an
                annexe well suited for use as a studio from the same landlord in his own house in
                VOORBURG, not in The Hague, which will be much cheaper for me than living here in
                the city, which I shan’t readily do again.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>So I’m relieved of superfluous encumbrances, and know at once where to head for if I
            reach a point (certainly not for the time being, of course, but say in 1 year) when a
            temporary return here would be feasible. <unstress reason="career">Why? — because, for
                instance, by that time I might be able to become a member of the Drawing Society,
                just to mention one thing. Which is one of the things I might desire and could
                achieve then.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>You’ll agree with me that The Hague is a very remarkable place. It really is the centre
            of the art world in Holland, and at the same time the surroundings are varied and
            extremely beautiful, so that one can always work there.And so — though certainly not for
            the time being — after a period of 1 year, say, there will probably be a reason for
            being here for a brief or a longer stay. And through this arrangement regarding my
            things I stay in touch with someone who knows me and so can at any rate find me a place
            to live, if I ask. </p>
      <p>So I’m a free man without encumbrances, I can leave when I like. </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="money">And I can now do more with the 150 francs from you than when so
                much had to come out of it.</unstress>
         <good_health>And because I have some relief from worries that were
                nerveracking.</good_health>
      </p>
      <p>The travel costs are made much simpler in this way. <stress reason="love">The only
                ‘drawback’, ‘disadvantage’ or whatever you want to call it is that, for my part, I
                really did have hope that the woman would turn out all right in Drenthe, and now
                have grave doubts about that. It’s certainly her own behaviour that made me decide
                to act, but if I’d been able to find the means I’d have taken her to Drenthe
                nonetheless, in a final attempt for her.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Well, I had to decide, because every week of delay got me more entangled in thorns here,
            without any progress with her. </p>
      <p>If I took my things, a 1/2 wagon to Drenthe would certainly cost something more than 25
            guilders, according to a revised calculation by Van Gend &amp; Loos, because there’s
            also the cost of delivering to and collecting from home, although this isn’t all that
            much. </p>
      <p>Well, some packing cases would be needed, which I would have to buy, and that’s another
            expense. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">It would have been convenient to have my things, but it works out
                too expensive, and especially if one moved about over there.</stress>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">I would first like to have a look at Katwijk, to do
                some sea studies, and because that at any rate is within reach, even if the journey
                to Drenthe has to wait a while on account of the money.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Oh, Theo, you’ll understand my feelings in recent days, a great melancholy about the
            woman and the children, but it couldn’t be otherwise — at the same time all my thoughts
            are about work and I’m really eager, because now I can do things which would have been
            impossible for me otherwise. </p>
      <p>Dear brother — if you could feel precisely what I’m feeling, and how I’ve devoted a piece
            of myself, so to speak, to the woman, namely forgetting everything else and
            concentrating on getting her back on her feet — if you could feel precisely a kind of
            sadness about life, which doesn’t, however, make me indifferent to it, on the contrary,
            I would rather have my sorrow about one thing and another than forget or become
            indifferent — <bad_health>if you could feel precisely the extent to which I draw my
                serenity from worship of sorrow and not from illusion — perhaps even for you
                brother, my inner self would be very different and more detached from life than you
                can now imagine.</bad_health> I’ll certainly not say much more about the woman, but
            I’ll still continue to think about her often. From the beginning, with her, it was a
            question of all or nothing when it came to helping. I couldn’t give her money to live on
            her own before, I had to take her in if I was to do anything of use to her. <stress reason="love">And in my view the proper course would have been to marry her and take
                her to Drenthe. But, I admit, neither she herself nor circumstances allow it. She
                isn’t kind, she isn’t good, but neither am I, and serious attachment existed
                throughout everything as we were.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I need to work and I also need you to write soon. Adieu, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
