<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>The Hague</location>
      <date>on or about Thursday, 10 May 1883.</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I received your letter in good order with the 50 francs enclosed. Which were a
    deliverance for me, at any rate a respite. I’ve also heard from friend Rappard — but nothing
    definite as yet. A letter that’s a reply to my letter, and that he will help me and come as
    well, but, he writes, my health is letting me down again. Ends with: I enclose the money
    herewith. Postscriptum: oh, I’ll come immediately and bring it myself — I’ll come tomorrow. This
    is followed by a telegram the next day. Not coming, letter follows later. <stress reason="money">So, despite having
    heard something, it’s still the same as with a game of goose,</stress> if you remember how one can land
    on a goose, thus go forward, but unfortunately just then land on a new goose with its beak
    pointing in a direction one doesn’t want to take, and so one must count back to one’s original
    position. Yet it isn’t his fault, for he’s been really very ill and is still feeling the
    remnants or after-effects of that. Moreover, his sister had a fairly similar illness, and they
    were most concerned about her, but she recovered too. Nonetheless, I do believe this of friend
    Rappard, that he does things that cost him a great deal of energy and nervous tension and aren’t
    worth the powder he expends on them. Thus before his illness I heard about decorations for the
    centenary of the Utrecht painters’ society, and now this time it was church ornaments. By chance
    I wrote to him that I thought they were both unwise, and he fell ill last time and now this
    time. I would approve if he overworked himself on normal things, but, as I said, this isn’t
    worth the powder expended on it, and I wrote again to him: you’re a soldier and one of the few
    who have cartridges in their box at the present time. Use them only in cases where a shot is
    unavoidable.</p>
      <p>I fear — dear brother — that the money you loaned to our dear cousin H. has
    currently taken the form of a vicious gun dog, for instance, or some similar curiosity, since I
    believe he’s quite often mistaken about such purchases — and then later it’s sometimes
    impossible for him to bring it back from that form to the state of banknotes or to cash it in
    because, like other lovers of horses and hounds, he’s caught in the snares of some crooked
    dealer. I’m one of those who wish him as much good fortune as possible in these negotiations,
    and would like to see nothing better than that their outcome is that he may speedily return what
    he owes you. At one time there were big plans to populate the plantation with countless dogs.
    This livestock farming is highly commendable, but at present I want to say no more about it than
    that I hope it may prove exceedingly profitable.</p>
      <p>Is your patient already discharged from
    hospital? But there may still be worrying days, no less grave than when she was in there.
    Michelet says rightly: a woman is an illness. They are changeable, Theo — they are changeable
    like the weather. Now those with an eye for it see something beautiful and good in all weathers,
    find snow beautiful and burning sun beautiful and storm beautiful and calm beautiful, cold good
    and heat, are fond of all seasons and don’t want to miss a single day of the year, and are
    fundamentally content and resigned to things being as they are — yet even if one looks at the
    weather and the changing year like this — and the changing female nature in the same way —
    believing that in the essence of that nature, in its mysteriousness, there is a Reason —
    accepting where one doesn’t understand — even, I say, if one should view it in that way, our own
    nature and vision isn’t always and at every moment in harmony and accord with that of the woman
    with whom we’re united, and individually one feels either concern or dissatisfaction or
    vacillation, despite the belief and the good spirits or serenity one may have. I was told by the
    professor who delivered her that the complete cure of my woman would take years. That is, the
    nervous system remains tremendously sensitive, for example, and she has that changeableness of
    women very strongly. The great danger is — as you will understand — tumbling back into old
    mistakes.</p>
      <p>This danger, although of a moral nature, has links with the physical constitution. And
    I have constant and sometimes serious concerns about what I would call these lurches between
    getting better and lapsing back into old bad habits. <stress reason="love">Her mood can be such that it’s almost
    unbearable, even for me,</stress> quick-tempered, wilfully wrong, in short, sometimes I despair. It
    passes — and more than once she has said to me later — I DON’T MYSELF KNOW WHAT I’M DOING
    THEN. Do you remember writing to me last year that you feared that I would be burdened with the
    mother? Sometimes I wish things had taken that turn. The mother is very sturdy when she wants to
    be, and could have done so much better than she has. Now she sometimes obstructs more than she
    helps. Anyway, when the woman does something wrong it’s sometimes the mother’s fault, and when
    the mother does wrong it’s sometimes the family who are behind the mother. Things which aren’t
    so bad in themselves but which prevent progress and overwhelm or neutralize better influences.
    My woman has certain faults and defects in the way she acts — that’s bound to be the case. THAT
    DOES NOT MAKE HER BAD in my view. Still, those defects must be eliminated — habits of laxity,
    indifference, lack of activity and deftness, oh, a mass of things. But all with the same root —
    wrong upbringing, years of an utterly wrong view of life, fatal influences of bad company.</p>
      <p>I
    tell you this in confidence, mind — and not out of desperation but so that you will understand
    that for me this love isn’t a bed of roses, but something as prosaic as Monday morning. A small
    painting by Tissot showed a figure of a woman in the snow amid withered stalks. Way of flowers,
    way of tears. Well, my woman no longer walks on a way of flowers as she did when she was younger
    and pleased herself and followed her inclination, but life has become thornier for her and
    become a Way of tears, especially last year — yet this year has thorns too, and the following
    years as well — still, by persevering she will overcome them. <stress reason="love">But sometimes there’s a crisis</stress> —
    particularly when I venture to raise the matter of some fault of hers that I’ve been quietly
    observing for a long time. For example, just to mention one thing, mending the clothes and
    making the children’s clothes herself. But that ends with her getting down to it one day, and
    she’s already much improved in this respect and in other respects. I must change so much in
    myself too, but I must ensure that in me she has an example of working and of patience, <stress reason="love">and
    that’s damned difficult, brother, to be so that one can indirectly show someone how to do
    something, and I too fall short sometimes,</stress> I must raise myself to something better in order to
    awaken her interest.</p>
      <p>The boy, above all, is doing extremely well, though — the girl was very ill
    in the past and neglected. But the little lad is a miracle of high spirits, already appears
    inclined to oppose social institutions and conventions. For instance, as far as I know all
    children are brought up on a kind of bread porridge. But he has refused that with the greatest
    determination. Although as yet without teeth, he bites firmly into a piece of bread and gets
    down all kinds of eatables while all the time smiling and crowing and making noises, but his
    mouth stays firmly shut for porridge &amp;c. &amp;c. He often sits with me in the studio on the
    floor in a corner on a couple of sacks or something, he crows at the drawings and is always
    quiet in the studio because he looks at the things on the wall. Oh, he’s such an agreeable
    little lad.</p>
      <p>The number of studies keeps growing — when you come I think you’ll find some to put
    in a portfolio in your room perhaps, anyway that’s up to you, as long as you clearly understand
    that you may of course regard anything you take a liking to as your own. Other things must come
    forth from the studies, though, and better studies come from the old ones. I myself don’t know
    exactly how. But I do long for you to see them again. I saw with great interest a publication,
    Le Salon 1883, a first issue of a series of illustrations, some deuced good. Done with that new
    way of reproduction. I’ve subscribed to it, although I have enough expenses, with a view to what
    I’m doing myself at present with the printer’s ink and lithographic crayon. Listen, I definitely
    believe that some of my things would do well if reproduced in that way — particularly those that
    have the more intense blacks obtained by lithographic crayon and printer’s ink; I can also get
    the brownish wash that I often come across in the above prints. Well, when you come perhaps we
    can arrange one thing and another. And perhaps I’ll write down a detailed statement of several
    matters about which I need information, and you could take some of my studies together with that
    to show to Buhot, for instance, who would then probably shed light on a few things for me.</p>
      <p>Recently read Un mâle by Camille Lemonnier — very strongly done in the manner of Zola.
    Everything observed from nature and everything analyzed. Saw a big Fromentin, a battle of
    fellahs, in the window at G&amp;C. Also saw the nouveautés, perhaps not all of them. I again
    came across Julien Dupré, whom I wrote to you about, in two things that I found less beautiful
    and more conventional than what I saw by him in an illustrated magazine in the winter. Did you
    already know that Rappard’s painting has been accepted this time in Amsterdam? Well, it’s late
    already — thanks for your timely dispatch — <stress reason="friendship">I just hope that R’s ‘letter follows’ doesn’t take
    too long,</stress> or that H. v. G.’s livestock farming may prosper.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Adieu — good fortune in all things, especially the woman.</close>
   <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>Still, Fromentin is clever — and a seeker, and someone
    who carries through, and conscientious too.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
