<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nieuw-Amsterdam</location>
      <date>3 October 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>This time I’m writing to you from the very back of beyond in Drenthe, where I arrived
                  after an endless trip through the heath on the barge.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">I see no way of describing the countryside to you as
                        it should be done, because words fail me. But imagine the banks of the canal
                        as miles and miles of Michels or T. Rousseaus, say, Van Goyens or P. de
                        Koninck.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>Flat planes or strips differing in colour, which grow narrower and narrower as they
                  approach the horizon. Accentuated here and there by a sod hut or small farm or a
                  few scrawny birches, poplars, oaks. Stacks of peat everywhere, and always barges
                  sailing past with peat or bulrushes from the marshes. Here and there thin cows of
                  a delicate colour, often sheep — pigs. The figures that now and then appear on the
                  plain usually have great character, sometimes they’re really charming. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">I drew, among others, a woman in the barge with
                        crepe around her cap brooches because she was in mourning,</work>
         <work origin="new" stage="sketch">and later a mother with a small child — this one
                        had a purple scarf around her head.</work>
      </p>
      <p>There are a lot of Ostade types among them, physiognomies that remind one of pigs or
                  crows, but every so often there’s a little figure that’s like a lily among the
                  thorns. <good_health>In short, I’m very pleased about this trip, for I’m full of
                        what I’ve seen.</good_health>
         <unstress reason="environment">The heath was extraordinarily beautiful this
                        evening.</unstress> There’s a Daubigny in one of the Albums Boetzel that
                  expresses that effect precisely. The sky was an inexpressibly delicate lilac white
                  — not fleecy clouds, because they were more joined together and covered the whole
                  sky, but tufts in tints more or less of lilac — grey — white — a single small rent
                  through which the blue gleamed. Then on the horizon a sparkling red streak —
                  beneath it the surprisingly dark expanse of brown heath, and a multitude of low
                  roofs of small huts standing out against the glowing red streak. In the evening
                  this heath often has effects that the English would describe as weird and quaint.
                  The spiky silhouettes of Don Quixotelike mills or strange hulks of drawbridges are
                  profiled against the teeming evening sky. In the evening a village like that is
                  sometimes really snug, with the light from the little windows reflected in the
                  water or in mud and puddles.</p>
      <p>
         <work mention="vague">Before I left Hoogeveen I painted a few more studies there,
                        among them a large farmhouse with a mossy roof.</work>
         <good_health>For I’d had paint sent from Furnée’s, because I thought the same
                        about it as you say in your letter, that by making sure I become absorbed in
                        the work and lose myself in it so to speak, my mood would change, and indeed
                        it’s already a good deal better.</good_health>
      </p>
      <p>But at times — like those moments when you think about going to America I think about
                  going to the East as a volunteer. <bad_health>But they’re those wretched, sombre
                        moments when things overwhelm one,</bad_health>
         <unstress reason="environment">and I would wish that you might see the silent
                        heath that I see through the window here, because such a thing soothes one
                        and inspires more faith, resignation, calm work.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work mention="vague">I drew several studies in the barge,</work> but I’m staying
                  here to paint. I’m close to Zweeloo here, where Liebermann, among others, has
                  been, and besides there’s an area here where there are large, very old sod huts
                  where there isn’t even a partition between the barn and the living room. My plan
                  for these first days is to visit that region.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">But what tranquillity, what breadth, what calm there
                        is in nature here, one doesn’t feel it until one has miles and miles of
                        Michels between oneself and the everyday.</unstress> I can’t give you a
                  definite address at the moment because I don’t know exactly where I’ll be for the
                  next few days, but I’ll be in HOOGEVEEN on 12 October, and if you send your letter
                  at the usual time to the same address I’ll find it there in Hoogeveen on the
                  twelfth. The place where I am now is NieuwAmsterdam.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="money">I received a postal order for 10 guilders from Pa, which
                        with what I got from you means that I can now do some painting.</unstress>
                  I’m thinking of returning to this inn where I am now for a long stay if I can
                  reach the area with the large old sod huts easily from here, since I would have
                  better light and space here. For as to that painting by that Englishman with the
                  thin cat and the little coffin, although the idea first came to him in that dark
                  room, he would have found it very difficult to paint in that same place, at least
                  one usually works too light if one sits in a room that’s too dark, so that when
                  one brings it into the light one sees that all the shadows are too weak. <work mention="vague">I experienced this only recently, when I painted an open
                        door and the view through into the little garden from inside the
                        barn.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Well, I just wanted to tell you that I’ll also be able to overcome this drawback,
                  because I could get a room here with good light and where a stove can stand in the
                  winter. Now, old chap, if you think no more about America, and I no more about
                  Harderwijk, then I hope things will work themselves out. I admit that your
                  explanation of C.M.’s silence might be the case, but sometimes nonchalance can
                  also be deliberate.</p>
      <p>You’ll find a few croquis on the back. I write in haste, or rather it’s already
                  late.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">How I wish that we could walk together here and — paint
                        together.</stress> I believe that the countryside would win you over and
                  convince you. Adieu, I hope that you’re well and will have a bit of good fortune.
                  I thought about you again and again on this trip. With a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
