<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nieuw-Amsterdam</location>
      <date>2 November <year>1883</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation>Dear brother,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Just wanted to tell you about a trip to Zweeloo, the village where Liebermann stayed for
            a long time and made studies for his painting of the washerwomen at the last Salon.</p>
      <p>Where Ter Meulen and Jules Bakhuyzen also spent some time.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">Imagine a trip across the heath at 3 o’clock in the morning in an open cart (I went with
            the man where I lodge, who had to go to the market in Assen). Along a road, or ‘diek’ as
            they say here, which they’d put mud on to raise it instead of sand. It was much nicer
            even than the barge. When it was only just starting to get a little lighter and the
            cocks were crowing everywhere by the huts scattered over the heath, the few cottages we
            passed — surrounded by slender poplars whose yellow leaves one could hear falling — an
            old squat tower in a little churchyard with earth bank and beech hedge, the flat
            landscapes of heath or wheatfields, everything, everything became just exactly like the
            most beautiful Corots. A silence, a mystery, a peace as only he has painted.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>It was still very dark, though, when we got to Zweeloo at 6 o’clock in the morning — I
            saw the real Corots even earlier in the morning. <unstress reason="environment">The ride into the village was really so
            beautiful. Huge mossy roofs on houses, barns, sheepfolds, sheds. The dwellings here are
            very wide, among oak trees of a superb bronze. Tones of golden green in the moss, of
            reddish or bluish or yellowish dark lilac greys in the soil, tones of inexpressible
            purity in the green of the little wheatfields. Tones of black in the wet trunks,
            standing out against golden showers of whirling, swirling autumn leaves, which still
            hang in loose tufts, as if they were blown there, loosely and with the sky shining
            through them, on poplars, birches, limes, apple trees. The sky unbroken, clear,
            illuminating, not white but a lilac that cannot be deciphered, white in which one sees
            swirling red, blue, yellow, which reflects everything and one feels above one
            everywhere, which is vaporous and unites with the thin mist below. Brings everything
            together in a spectrum of delicate greys.</unstress> I didn’t find a single painter in Zweeloo,
            though, and the people said they never come there in the winter. It’s precisely in the
            winter that I hope to be there. Since there were no painters, I decided to walk back and
            do some drawing on the way instead of waiting for my landlord’s return.<work origin="new" stage="sketch">So I started to
            make a sketch of the very apple orchard where Liebermann made his large painting.</work> And
            then back along the road we had driven down early on. At the moment that area around
            Zweeloo is entirely given over to young wheat — vast, sometimes, that most tender of
            tender greens that I know. With above it a sky of a delicate lilac white that gives an
            effect — I don’t think it can be painted, but for me it’s the basic tone that one must
            know in order to know what the basis of other effects is.</p>
      <p>A black earth, flat — infinite — a clear sky of delicate lilac white. That earth brings
            forth that young wheat — it’s as if that wheat is a growth of mould. That’s what the
            good, fertile fields of Drenthe are, au fond — everything in a vaporous atmosphere.
            Think of the Last day of creation by Brion — well, yesterday I felt that I understood
            the meaning of that painting.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">The poor soil of Drenthe is the same, only the black earth is even blacker — like soot —
            not a lilac black like the furrows, and melancholically overgrown with eternally rotting
            heather and peat. I see that everywhere — the chance effects on that infinite
            background: in the peat bogs the sod huts, in the fertile areas, really primitive hulks
            of farmhouses and sheepfolds with low, very low walls, and huge mossy roofs. Oaks around
            them. When one travels for hours and hours through the region, one feels as if there’s
            actually nothing but that infinite earth, that mould of wheat or heather, that infinite
            sky. Horses, people seem as small as fleas then. One feels nothing any more, however big
            it may be in itself, one only knows that there is land and sky. However, in one’s
            capacity as a tiny speck watching other tiny specks — leaving aside the infinite — one
            discovers that every tiny speck is a Millet. I passed a little old church, just exactly,
            just exactly the church at Gréville in Millet’s little painting in the Luxembourg; but
            here, instead of the little peasant with the spade in that painting, a shepherd with a
            flock of sheep came along the hedge. One didn’t see through to the sea in the background
            but only to the sea of young wheat, the sea of furrows instead of that of the waves. The
            effect produced: the same. I saw ploughmen, very busy now, a sandcart, shepherds, road
            workers, dungcarts. In a little inn along the way drew a little old woman at the
            spinning wheel, little dark silhouette — like something out of a fairy tale — little
            dark silhouette against a bright window through which one saw the bright sky and a path
            through the delicate green and a few geese cropping the grass.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">And then, when dusk fell — imagine the silence, the peace of that moment! Imagine, right
            then, an avenue of tall poplars with the autumn leaves, imagine a broad muddy road, all
            black mud with the endless heath on the right, the endless heath on the left, a few
            black, triangular silhouettes of sod huts, with the red glow of the fire shining through
            the tiny windows, with a few pools of dirty, yellowish water that reflect the sky, where
            bogwood trunks lie rotting. Imagine this muddy mess in the evening twilight with a
            whitish sky above, so everything black on white. And in this muddy mess a rough figure —
            the shepherd — a throng of oval masses, half wool, half mud, that bump into one another,
            jostle one another — the flock. You see it coming — you stand in the midst of it — you
            turn round and follow them.With difficulty and reluctantly they progress along the muddy
            road. Still, there’s the farm in the distance — a few mossy roofs and piles of straw and
            peat between the poplars. Again the sheepfold is like a triangle in silhouette.
            Dark.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>The door stands wide open like the entrance to a dark cave. The light from the sky behind
            shines through the cracks in the boards at the back. The whole caravan of masses of wool
            and mud disappears into this cave — the shepherd and a woman with a lantern shut the
            doors behind them.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">That return of the flock in the dusk was the finale of the symphony that I heard
            yesterday. That day passed like a dream, I had been so immersed in that heartrending
            music all day that I had literally forgotten even to eat and drink — I took a slice of
            coarse peasant bread and a cup of coffee at the little inn where I drew the spinning
            wheel. The day was over, and from dawn to dusk, or rather from one night to the other
            night, I had forgotten myself in that symphony.</unstress>
         <unstress reason="career">I came home and, sitting by the fire, it
            occurred to me that I was hungry, and I found I was terribly hungry. But that’s how it
            is here. One feels exactly as if one had been at an exhibition of one hundred
            masterpieces, for example. What does one get out of a day like that? Just a few
            scratches. And yet one gets something else out of it, too — a calm passion for work.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>Above all, do write to me soon. It’s Friday today but your letter isn’t here yet; I’m
            looking forward to it eagerly. It takes time to get it changed, since it has to go back
            to Hoogeveen again and then back here again. We don’t know how it will work out, but
            apart from that I would now say — the simplest thing perhaps would be to send money once
            a month. In any event write again soon. With a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent.</sig>
</letter>
