<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, Wednesday, <date>30 April 1884</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Many happy returns of the day.</p>
      <p>It really was important news in your last letter — and I think you’ll be glad that
                  the situation has at least become clearer.</p>
      <p>Am really looking forward to your next letter.</p>
      <p>As regards the work, <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’m doing a fairly large painting of a weaver — the loom
                  straight on from the front — the little figure a dark little silhouette against
                  the white wall.</work>
         <work stage="middle" origin="existing">And at the same time also the one I started in the winter, a loom
                  on which a piece of red cloth is being woven — there the loom is seen from the
                  side. </work>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’ve also started on two others of effects on the heath. And a thing with
                  Pollard birches.</work>
      </p>
      <p>I’ll have a lot more hard graft on those looms — but in reality the things are such
                  almighty beautiful affairs — all that old oak against a greyish wall — that I
                  certainly believe it’s right that they should be painted. We must make sure that
                  we get them so that the colour and tone match with other Dutch paintings, though.
                 <work stage="planned" origin="new"> I hope to start on two more of weavers soon, where the figure will appear very
                  differently, that’s to say where the weaver isn’t sitting behind it but is
                  arranging the threads for the cloth.</work> I’ve seen them weaving by lamplight in the
                  evening, which creates very Rembrandtesque effects. Nowadays they have a sort of
                  hanging lamp — but I’ve just got a little lamp from a weaverlike the one in The
                  evening by Millet, for instance. This is what they used to work by.</p>
      <p>I recently also saw coloured pieces woven in the evening — where I’ll take you
                  sometime should you come here. When I saw it, they were also just arranging the
                  threads, so dark, bowed figures against the light, which stood out against the
                  colour of the piece. Great shadows cast on the white walls by the laths and beams
                  of the loom.</p>
      <p>Regards — do write soon if you can.</p>
   </body>
   <close> Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
