<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>
      <date>6 December <year>1883</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>You’ll have been rather surprised that I dropped you a line that I would go home
            sometime, and am now writing to you from here. </p>
      <p>But first I must thank you for your letter of 1 December, which I’ve just received here
            in Nuenen.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>The last 3 weeks I was actually rather unwell — was troubled by various things that arose
            out of having caught a cold, and nerves as well.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>One must try to break something like that, and I felt that I would get worse if I didn’t
            have a change.Well, I decided to go home for various reasons — something I was actually
            very loath to do.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">My journey began with a walk of more than 6 hours — mostly across the heath — to
            Hoogeveen. On a stormy afternoon with rain, with snow. This walk cheered me up no end,
            or rather my feelings were so in sympathy with nature that it calmed me down more than
            anything else.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>I thought that being at home again might give me a more accurate insight into the
            question of what I should do.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Drenthe is superb, but staying there depends on many things — depends on whether one has
            the money for it,</stress>
         <stress reason="friendship">depends on whether one can endure the loneliness.</stress>
         <stress reason="family">Pa would consider
            that question settled, I believe, with a conclusion that one would reach in a
            conversation, but for my part I’m in no hurry to make a decision about it, and I’ll have
            to see what I think about it, for instance, when I’ve been here for a week or so.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>However, for the time being I’m in the dark as to what I should do in this respect. I see
            more and more that when one thinks or speaks about something, one by no means arrives at
            a satisfactory conclusion. At one moment it seems more possible than at another. And for
            my part I don’t let these things go at once but keep thinking about them, sometimes long
            after other people consider that they’re already decided.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">But, old chap, it’s so difficult for me, because for me it becomes so much a matter of
            conscience that I would be too much of a burden to you — perhaps abuse your friendship
            if I accept money for an enterprise that may not pay.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>You write again about Moniteur Universel. Do you think it too gloomy of me when I tell
            you that I regard it as possible that in a relatively few years’ time a number of large
            art businesses — for example Moniteur Universel — in a word others that have also
            expanded enormously — will decline — fall into decline as quickly as they came up?</p>
      <p>In a relatively short space of time, everything that is the art trade developed in
            rapport with art itself. But it became all too much a sort of bankers’ speculation and
            it still is — I do not say entirely — — I simply say much too much. Why, in so far as
            it’s a bubble company, shouldn’t it go the same way as, for instance, the tulip trade?
            You’ll point out to me that a painting isn’t a tulip. Of course there’s a universe of
            difference, and naturally I, who love paintings and tulips not at all, am very well
            aware of this. But I contend that many rich people who buy the expensive paintings for
            one reason or another don’t do it for the artistic value that they see in them — the
            difference between tulip and painting that you and I see isn’t visible to them — they,
            the speculators and blasé sots and a lot of others, would buy tulips now too, just as in
            the past, provided there was a certain cachet to it.</p>
      <p>True, there are real, sterling art lovers. But it’s perhaps only 1/10th of the total of
            the business that’s done, perhaps it’s even a much smaller proportion — of which it can
            be said: this or that transaction was genuinely out of belief in art.</p>
      <p>I could expand on this forever of course, but without going on about it any more I
            believe that you agree with me that there’s a great deal in the art trade that could
            prove to be hot air in the future. Things that are very highly priced now can go down.
            If you ask me, can Millet and Corot go down, I say, yes, IN PRICE.</p>
      <p>Anyway, from an artistic point of view, Millet is Millet, Corot Corot, fixed — as the sun
            itself, in my view.</p>
      <p>Five years ago I thought differently about it, in so far as I thought that Millet, say,
            would remain fixed, EVEN in price, but since then — precisely because I see Millet is
            usually just as much utterly misunderstood now that he’s less concealed and is more in
            evidence in reproductions, for instance, as when he was despised — I fear he’ll remain
            somewhat outside public taste and — it isn’t certain that those who understand him best
            will have to pay as much money for him later as they do now. Rembrandt fell too — in
            price — in the periwig age. I just want to ask you frankly, do you believe that the
            prices that are still being paid now will stay? I tell you frankly, I do not believe
            it.</p>
      <p>Yet at the same time, to me Millet is Millet, Rembrandt Rembrandt, Israëls Israëls
            &amp;c., whether it costs ten cents or a hundred thousand to buy one of his
            paintings.</p>
      <p>Consequently I don’t think about the art trade much.</p>
      <p>Only when my thoughts turn to you and I come to ask you whether you can take pleasure in
            it, or whether, especially later, you won’t see all too much that goes against the grain
            with you to stay in it.</p>
      <p>You’ll say, one can get used to anything, or rather you’ll say, one must endure until the
            heart breaks in us. So be it, I agree with you in that — but if the heart does break in
            us, we’re still free to act in one way or another. And as regards you or me, we are what
            we are, and because we’re enthusiastic about art, we would each in our own way also
            remain constant in our opinion about Millet, say, even if the most absurd things were to
            happen.</p>
      <p>But I ask: in the event of a gradual cooling off in the expenditure of tremendous sums
            for paintings, how are the huge firms which have colossal sums in outgoings etc. every
            year, which cut into their profits, going to succeed? They’ll soon find themselves with
            enormous deficits. Trees like this don’t fall at the first blow, but they can rot away
            inside and ultimately fall because of the wind alone, without a single blow from an axe.
            When? I have absolutely no idea of the exact date. If you will, just write to me about
            this question in general, for example what you think of the staying power — in the long
            run — of an establishment such as you say Moniteur Universel is — or Petit — or Arnold
            &amp; Tripp. I tell you frankly, I don’t see that it can keep going in the long run. I
            believe something like this has to collapse.</p>
      <p>In my view, it can’t be very pleasant to be on hand for this — I’d rather sit by a peat
            fire, painting. <stress reason="money">The art trade, one feels a sort of ‘what do I care’ about it, except —
            except — except — that I personally find it very unpleasant if I’m really very short of
            money.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>You’ve always remained calm in Paris, very simple and certainly cooler than a man like
            Tripp, say.</p>
      <p>You’re out to see things as they are, you — like me — can’t help analyzing. And yet, even
            you don’t in the first place bring what you know of a situation to bear in order to
            profit from that situation all the same.</p>
      <p>I mean, it isn’t in your nature to fish in troubled waters.</p>
      <p>But I ask you frankly, what’s the position? Do you really believe that the people at
            Moniteur Universel will ask something different of employees from what G&amp;Cie
            asks?</p>
      <p>Moniteur, G&amp;Cie, Tripp, Petit, to me they’re all similar firms. I believe in my own
            case that, having been thrown out by one, I would be thrown out by them all. If old
            Goupil says, you’re no good to us, I believe other bosses would also think more or less
            the same.</p>
      <p>Well, as to you, I believe that it would be the same for you with another house as it is
            with G&amp;Cie. In my opinion, setting up for oneself at a time when a cooling off and
            decline could be foreseen is something that one cannot do with any enthusiasm.</p>
      <p>So do you believe in these times, do you believe that the trade will stay at this level?
            If you believed this, I would respect your opinion and keep quiet, but I don’t know
            whether you know that I don’t really believe that the very large firms can keep going.
            Do write to me about it, then it will be so much easier for me to talk about it. <stress reason="family">I feel
            rather embarrassed with you at the moment, and I want you to know my perhaps nervous
            opinion that firstly I don’t believe that these highly inflated firms can keep going
            and, secondly, even should they prove to keep going, I wouldn’t enjoy being involved in
            them, directly or indirectly.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Another thing is, if I can provide for myself by doing this or that here or there, I
            won’t look such a gift horse in the mouth. If it proves to be my duty to do this or
            that, very well, I won’t refuse the work, not even unpleasant work.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I thought of you brother, on my long trudge across the heath on that stormy evening. I
            thought of a passage, I don’t know which book it’s from, two eyes awake, brightened by
            genuine tears — <bad_health>I thought, I am disillusioned, that is — I thought — I have believed in
            many things that I now know are in a sorry state at bottom — I thought, these eyes of
            mine, here on this gloomy evening, awake here in the solitude, if there have been tears
            in them from time to time, why should they not have been wrung from me by such sorrow
            that it disenchants — yes — and banishes illusions — but at the same time — awakens one?</bad_health>
            I thought, is it POSSIBLE that Theo is easy about many things that I’m uneasy about. </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Could it be just melancholy, that I can’t take the old pleasure in this or in that?</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>In short, I thought, can I be mistaking gold for gilding? Am I mistaking something that’s
            in full growth for something withering? I couldn’t come up with an answer for myself.
            Can you? Do you know for sure that there isn’t already faradvanced, unrelenting decline
            on all sides?</p>
      <p>Give me courage if you yourself have courage — but I say to you in my turn ‘don’t flatter
            me’. <stress reason="money">I tell you that, as far as I’m concerned, even if I become clever (which I am not
            noticeably as yet), I believe — firmly believe — that I’ll always be very poor — it will
            exceed my expectations if I manage to keep out of debt.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>The coming men in Holland after those mastodons Mesdag, Israëls, Mauve, Blommers, Maris
            &amp;c. will, under no circumstances, still be able to earn what was earned in those
            days, that is the last 20 years, say. And especially not if they’re clever. One of the
            drawbacks of a period like the one we’re entering is that a time when prices are
            inflated so high is, as it were, taking a lien on the future, which makes the future
            dark for posterity. So, old chap, perhaps Arnold &amp; Tripp have never treated you
            personally anything other than very courteously or, in short, with due form. That
            doesn’t alter the fact that you, who are just as clever as Uncle Cent, for instance,
            won’t be able to do what Uncle Cent did. Why not? Because there are too many Arnold
            &amp; Tripps in the world. Insatiable moneygrubbers, that’s to say, compared with whom
            you are a sheep.</p>
      <p>Please don’t take this as an insult, brother, that I make this comparison. It’s better to
            be a sheep than a wolf, it’s better to be the one who is killed than the one who kills —
            namely better to be Abel than Cain. And — and — I myself am not a wolf either, I hope,
            or rather I know.</p>
      <p>Suppose that both you and I are ‘sheep’ in society, not in our imaginations but in truth.
            Very well — given fairly hungry and vicious wolves — it wouldn’t be beyond the bounds of
            possibility that we’d be gobbled up. Well, even then, although I don’t think this would
            be exactly pleasant, in short it’s surely still better after all to be ruined than to
            ruin someone else. I mean, it’s no reason to lose one’s serenity if one should realize
            that one might have to lead a life of poverty while one had the skills, the talents, the
            aptitude with which others grow rich. I’m not indifferent to money, but I don’t envy the
            wolves. Now, with a hearty handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent.</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>If you will, answer me some of these things while I’m here at home; I’m here to get some
            rest and resolution. </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
