<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nieuw-Amsterdam</location>
      <date>31 October 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear brother —</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I cannot count the grains of corn in a sack of corn just by smelling it — I cannot see
      through the planks in the barn door — but I can sometimes see from the bulges whether it’s a
      sack of potatoes or corn; or again, even if the barn door is shut, I can tell from the
      squealing that the pig’s being slaughtered.</p>
      <p>And so I can only, will only consider the situation in which you presently find yourself in
      so far as I have information, albeit vague, to make sense of it, and it isn’t by way of
      prediction.</p>
      <p>But to the point. Consider coolheadedly whether what you’re facing here is what they call
      fatality on the field of battle. Consider the faces of your friends, false friends, enemies,
      consider all the — je ne sais quoi’s — consider whether a certain void is forming around you
      so that you no longer have any handholds, at least are able to tie things up less easily. In
      short, consider whether fatality is For or decidedly Against.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Tell me this one thing, whether it’s a mistake on my part when I
        think that I see in some phenomena that you’re dealing here with one of those malignant
        crises that sometimes tend to crop up in big businesses and big cities? Again, is the aspect
        of the things — fatal? — do you feel: there’s nothing to be done about this? — or do you
        feel: redress is possible, there’s no reason to change as yet?For myself, unless you were to
        write to me yourself: no it isn’t that bad — for myself I see that the affair has a fairly
        fatal look.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Think about it coolheadedly — I know that you have your calmness, your presence of mind — I
      know that you’re trying to analyze it, and so I just wanted to know whether you yourself see
      anything of that which I fear is the case.</p>
      <p>Now, old chap, as long as the situation was tolerable — as long as business could be done,
      well I’ve never dared to come right out and say, get out of it, above all respecting your
      position, because you didn’t do it for your own pleasure but for the sake of the welfare of us
      all. But your former duties, which, moreover, you assumed voluntarily, cease to be duties in
      the event that the state of affairs is such that going on wouldn’t only be fighting a losing
      battle, but at the same time would inevitably result in your being crushed.</p>
      <p>In short, there’s a thus far and no further, and my premonition is that you’re close to
      it.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Look here — about now or ever — making yourself scarce or
        disappearing — neither you nor I must ever do that, any more than a suicide. I myself also
        have my moments of great melancholy, but the thought: disappear, make yourself scarce, must,
        I repeat, be regarded by me and by you as not befitting us.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Against the risk of going on all the same when one feels it isn’t possible, going on with the
      desperate feeling that it must end in a disappearance, our conscience argues with a BEWARE!!!
      If I’m wrong, if my premonitions don’t square with the facts I’m asking you about, if they do
      or do not have the decidedly fatal aspect — well then I’ll believe your simple statement: ‘I
      do see a chance of one thing and another working out’ (or similar information) when you write
      to tell me so. If it’s a fait accompli that here you’re dealing with one of those vicious
      crises such as Paris, London produce — if that’s so decidedly in the air that you feel that
      it’s a force that would crush, if by trying to oppose it, one would force the worst to happen
      — then, abandon the wreck and concentrate your attention and energy not on preserving your
      present position, but on creating something completely new.</p>
      <p>For a long time now it has seemed to me that your duty was too complicated — my view is that
      your duty should be a simple thing, and the present situation would become more complicated
      the longer it went on, and more doubtful as to whether or not it really was duty; furthermore
      that through painting you’ll presently find a very clear duty, a very simple, straight path
      for your feet. <stress reason="money"> My idea is that continuing as at present would prove to
        be not only more and more intolerable but moreover less and less profitable. I don’t say
        this about G&amp;Cie alone, but also about you as a dealer in general. I don’t say that you
        and I will get rich together, but we’ll be able to maintain our aplomb and equilibrium, even
        though — this I cannot deny — we’ll have a very hard struggle in the first few
        years.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Yet, above our enterprise of painting I see not fatality against but
        for, but you would, I fear, crush not just yourself but me too by wanting to go ahead with
        what, in my opinion, really goes against the grain. In the first place we wouldn’t be able
        to support each other and each of us would stand too much alone. In the second place, we’d
        cause each other to waver by working in diametrically opposed directions so that, despite
        our friendship, we’d turn our backs on each other now and then.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Well, old chap, for me painting is too logical, too reasonable, too straightforward for me to
      make a change. Well, you yourself helped me carry through the idea of a craft; I know that
      basically it’s your own idea too, and so it seems to me that we should go on to work together.
      My reason, my conscience compels me to tell you what in part are also your own ideas, there’s
      nothing for it but to undertake a radical renewal. I know that my words will stand out oddly
      against what other people would say if you consulted them; they’d dismiss it with ‘it will
      turn out all right’, ‘the desired changes will happen’. I wasn’t to flatter you; very well, I
      don’t flatter. And as far as inspiring you with courage, yes, I do dare to do that, I dare to
      inspire you with the very highest, most cheerful courage and serenity, but only for painting,
      and as to Paris only this — take a good look and see whether you don’t have fate against you
      on that battlefield. Now, with a hearty handshake</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>—Now then, the countryside here is very singular.</p>
      <p>Just suppose you were asked whether you’d want to be a painter if you could suddenly be
      transported to the era 40 years ago, when things were as they were when Corot &amp;c. were
      young – also that you wouldn’t be alone but would have a comrade. Why I ask this — because in
      the countryside here, where people haven’t yet progressed beyond diligence and barge, where
      everything is much purer than I’ve ever seen anywhere, I feel exactly as though I myself had
      been transported to the aforementioned time.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">You have seen Drenthe — from the train, in haste, long ago.
        But remotest Drenthe, if you come here, will make a very different impression on you, and
        even you will feel just as if you were living in the age of Van Goyen, Ruisdael, Michel; in
        short, in what one scarcely finds now even in presentday Barbizon. It seems to me that this
        is something important, because nature like this can sometimes awaken in a mind things that
        would otherwise never have woken. I mean something of that free, cheerful spirit of the
        past, I mean that nervous wavering can be silenced that way.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Yet I believe that alone in a region like this one could be held up
        and become dull through lack of company. And for myself, I really long for your
        collaboration.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I think about you, however, not first and foremost for my sake; I think about you first and
      foremost for your sake, although these also run together, although they also enhance each
      other. What I see is that hanging on in Paris, even if you could keep it up for years more,
      will nonetheless not bring you peace, and will also not be as useful to other people as
      painting. I see that Paris will put you in what I would call a false position in regard to
      your own duty. I’ll leave being useful to others out of it, I don’t know whether this would
      truly remain sound in the long term because you focus other, stupider minds on Paris, a
      thought that upsets those very people, because they’d be intoxicated by it.</p>
      <p>Make no mistake: everything had its reason until now, but in my view the signs of the times
      point to a change of direction now, in a very different and much more decisive way than ever
      happened before.</p>
      <p>This is not about weakening or giving up; on the contrary it’s about striking calamity to the
      heart, planting in better soil the same energetic principle of wanting to rise.</p>
      <p>The calamity leaves us our same courage and serious will.</p>
      <p>Let the world spitefully say what it wouldn’t refrain from saying, that can leave you and me
      cold. And on the contrary, for ourselves, we’re counting on a difficult life which has a goal
      other than earning as much money as we might perhaps do.</p>
      <p>Our goal, first and foremost, is to reform ourselves through craft and contact with nature,
      believing that it’s our duty first and foremost, precisely so that we can remain straight with
      other people, and consistent.</p>
      <p>Our goal is ‘walking with God’ — as against living amid the affairs of the big cities.</p>
      <p>We’ll do no one any harm by it. Our belief is that, yes – although, to some people, it seems
      hypocritical to say this — our belief, I say, is that God helps those who help themselves in
      so far as they concentrate their endeavours and attention on that and roll up their sleeves to
      that end. The longer I think about it the more I see that Millet believes in a something on
      High.</p>
      <p>He speaks of it very differently from Pa, for instance — for he leaves it more vague, yet I
      see more in Millet’s vagueness than in Pa. And I see the same as in Millet in Rembrandt, in
      Corot, in Breton, in Brion, in short in the work of several people, although I don’t hear them
      hold forth about it.</p>
      <p>The end of things doesn’t have to be an ability to explain but to base oneself on it
      effectively.</p>
      <p>In short, Theo, a certain indeterminate but nonetheless fixed feeling in me that it’s the
      first duty to direct the heart upwards leads me, as brother and as friend to a brother and a
      friend, to ask you to consider directing yourself towards a life founded on simpler
      principles.</p>
      <p>Principles that I can’t define other than: sensing that duty is unlikely to bring someone to
      the Paris business, but rather points to retiring from it.</p>
      <p>Can you share this sense to some extent? Think about it, reflect on it; if you need time for
      it, put yourself to the test and take your time. Any hesitation along the lines of ‘I’m not an
      artist’, though, only seems justified to me in so far as it doesn’t stand in the way of doing
      what you have to do and I have to do to become one. Neither we ourselves nor other people can
      fully explain the extent to which we are not one, the extent to which we are. Only the How to
      do it system involves saying I’ll do my best to do it, asking no such questions; in my view
      the How not to do it system is only that which says ‘I know in advance that I can’t do it
      anyway’. One isn’t sure of one’s case all at once, one knows nothing in advance other than
      very vaguely, but nevertheless something called conscience is a sort of compass for man to
      distinguish between this direction and that — between north and south, between right and left
      — broadly. Consequently, in spite of chance currents, in spite of deceptively friendly-looking
      coasts, to say, yes, but fundamentally this isn’t the right direction. And there you have it,
      earning money in Paris, even for other people, particularly given your recent experiences,
      seems to me to be a deceptive fata Morgana, a coast that would recede further and further away
      the more you continued to try to land there, meanwhile carrying you further and further away
      from your proper direction.</p>
      <p>I respect all your hesitations and doubt, I respect your weighing up the pros and cons, I
      don’t seek to force you to decide at once. But I just point out to you very, very seriously
      and decidedly that it seems to me to be a fact that you’re standing at a fork in the road and
      must reflect before you set out, before you just persevere with Paris. The signs of the times,
      not I, tell you: Hold on! what do you want? <stress reason="family">If you want Paris, very
        well — if you can make up your mind to that, so be it — then I wouldn’t interfere in it, but
        it won’t be that easy, and I’m afraid you could run up against fatality. I strongly doubt
        whether you’ll preserve your peace as a result.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I see everything against painting except fatality, I see everything for Paris except
      fatality.</p>
      <p>Fatality in which I see with an inexpressible feeling God, Who is ‘the white Ray’ and has the
      last word: what isn’t good through and through isn’t good and doesn’t endure; and against whom
      even the black ray is powerless.</p>
      <p>What you’re facing is something terrible, something awful — things are so inexpressible that
      I have no words for them, that were I not your brother and your friend, who would regard
      keeping silent as ungrateful and hardly humane, I would say nothing. Well, seeing as you say,
      in the first place inspire me with courage, in the second place don’t flatter me, I say: well
      then, I see this and that in it, here on the silent heath where I feel God high above you and
      me. With a hearty handshake.</p>
      <p>Ever yours,</p>
      <p>Vincent</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
