<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Monday, <date>24 November <year>1884</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">I suppose you already know that Pa has turned down Helvoirt.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>The people here gave Pa a present of about 200 guilders, that’s most kind and I’m
                  pleased for them.</p>
      <p>The decision wasn’t a matter of indifference to me — since I wouldn’t have gone with
                  them to H. in any case, and would either have stayed here in my studio — or would
                  have left for Antwerp. <unstress reason="friendship">Now — as far as I can see, the best thing for me is simply
                  to carry on as things are — and stay here. It has truly not been going too badly
                  for me lately. It’s true that I can’t make anything financially from my work here
                  — but I’m making really good friends here — and I believe they’ll become even
                  better.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">Last week I painted still lifes day in and day out with the people who are painting
                  in Eindhoven.</work> The new acquaintance — the tanner — whom I told you about, is really
                  doing his best.</p>
      <p>But for my part, I also have to do something to keep on good terms with them.</p>
      <p>But I can’t see that I lose by it, since I work more enjoyably because I have some
                  conversation. Hermans has so many beautiful objects — like old jars and other
                  antiques — that I wanted to ask you whether I could oblige you by painting a still
                  life for your room of some of these objects — Gothic things, for instance.</p>
      <p>The ones I’ve been making with Hermans so far are simpler. But just today he said to
                  me that if I ever want to make a painting for myself of things that are still too
                  difficult for him to do as a study, I can take the objects with me to the studio.
                  Please let me have an answer to this — and if you would like it, I’ll make it for
                  you and shall select really nice things.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="finished">By the way, I’ve already finished a small one.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Now, as to what I asked you about covering the end of this month if possible by
                  sending me 20 francs extra, I wish you could do that.</p>
      <p>
         <good_health>It’s getting better for me</good_health> —<stress reason="money"> although my expenses aren’t getting any smaller</stress> — but
                  we’re definitely making progress just by working very hard now. So help me with
                  what I asked if it’s at all feasible for you. Because otherwise it will soon
                  become very difficult, and the work will suffer more than necessary.</p>
      <p>And I’ll give it back to you with my work. That’s all I can say about it.</p>
      <p>At all events I’ll ask Hermans for those objects — and make something for you with
                  them — you’ll see for yourself what I told you about the colour, that it’s getting
                  better.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="middle" origin="new">I’m also working on a watercolour of the water mill.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Regards, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>Cor was unwell for a few days, and at home — but he’s better now. I know that it’s a
                  difficult time for you — but we must progress and it will change a little for the
                  good — you’ll see.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
