<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nieuw-Amsterdam</location>
      <date>1 December <year>1883</year></date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Thanks for your letter and the enclosure. Your letter explains your silence to me.</p>
      <p>You thought that ‘feeling that I was flush’, I was giving you an ‘ultimatum’ — in the way
            — similar — that the nihilists, say, might send them to the Tsar. Well, fortunately both
            for you and for me, there’s no question here of anything of the kind or similar.</p>
      <p>However, I do understand your interpretation now that I know what it is, but I had to
            know. <stress reason="family">For a start I meant something different — it was simply: ‘I wouldn’t want to
            flourish if you had to wither in consequence; I wouldn’t want to develop the artistic in
            me if you had to suppress the artistic in you for my sake. I wouldn’t approve if you
            were to suppress the artistic in you for anyone’s sake, even for the sake of father,
            mother, sister, brother or wife’. There you have my meaning — perhaps expressed
            nervously and in the wrong words — most decidedly there was no more nor anything else
            behind it than that.</stress> You understand it well enough now, don’t you?</p>
      <p>As to what I wrote in my last letter, it arose out of your silence, an absolute mystery
            to me, absolutely inexplicable to me until I knew what the matter was. I already had an
            answer as far as Marie is concerned before I ever received your letter, simply because I
            remembered what you wrote to me in the past about your meeting with her and thought,
            that has to be all right, that can’t be what’s wrong. <stress reason="family">So even my letter on the subject
            was meant like this: brother, you seem to abandon me without warning; if you did this on
            purpose it would be treachery in my view, but I CAN not think that, so ‘explain it to
            me’ — no more nor less than this was behind that, and as to what I said about Lady
            Macbeth, you’ve interpreted it correctly, as a hint in general that was not even a
            question but only to make you feel: either it has to be like this or it is a
            misunderstanding.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Be aware of this, though, brother, that I’m absolutely cut off from the outside world —
            except for you — so that for me it was enough to make me crazy when your letter didn’t
            come at a moment when, far from being ‘flush’, I was in dire straits — although I didn’t
            mention that — because I reckon that I’m somewhat above the cares that peck at my
            vitals, regarding this torture as understandable, so be it, although not as deserved.</bad_health> As
            to ‘I wouldn’t want to flourish if someone else had to wither in consequence’, I hope
            that I would say this — which lay in what you conceived to be an ultimatum —whether I
            was ‘flush’ OR in ‘agony’.</p>
      <p>It seems to me that the conclusion that I spoke as if I was ‘flush’ was rather shallow or
            hasty on your part — although it must have been in the way I expressed it, for it was
            certainly not what I felt. <stress reason="money">I just want to tell you that since I’ve been here I’ve had to
            see to it that my equipment was organized, that I had paint, that I went to see this and
            that, that I paid for my lodgings, that I sent the woman something, that I paid off some
            debts. All this keeping me very hard up all the time — to put it mildly.</stress>
         <stress reason="friendship">Add to this
            that singular torture... loneliness, and you really will no longer be able to think that
            there’s any possibility of my feeling ‘flush’ for the time being — or that I felt it
            then.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I say loneliness and not even in peace — but that loneliness which a painter in an
            isolated region encounters when every Tom, Dick and Harry takes him to be a madman — a
            murderer — a vagabond &amp;c. &amp;c. Granted it may be a petty vexation, but a vexation
            it is. Being a stranger, doubly strange and unpleasant — <unstress reason="environment">however stimulating and
            beautiful the countryside may be.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>But I see in this only a bad time that one has to get through. <stress reason="career">Something, though, which
            one can do very little about oneself — that is, about the attitude of the people whom
            one would so much like to have as models and can’t get.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">With hindsight, I see clearly enough how you and I came to misunderstand each other.
            There was a moment when you were very melancholy, and you wrote me the following: the
            gentlemen are making it almost impossible for me, and I actually believe that they would
            rather dismiss me than that I should resign (the underlined precisely my case at the
            time). And you said, ‘sometimes I think I should just disappear’ — and you said — there
            were things about the idea of painting to which you were at least not averse.</stress>Very well —
            then I candidly told you all my thoughts about the possibility of your becoming a
            painter, I said you can do it provided you want to, and I believe in you as an artist,
            from the moment you pick up a brush, even if no one else does.</p>
      <p>What I said about that, I’ll say to you in the future should a misfortune — a calamity —
            strike you — what is now stopping you from ‘a complete renewal’ is indeed a misfortune.
            If a calamity were to strike you, I believe that you as a person would become a greater
            person as a result, with — with — with — an eternally painful wound at the same
            time.</p>
      <p>I would expect of you that it would raise you up, not ‘drag you down’, that wound which
            can only be caused by a calamity. But your later letters differ so much in tone and so
            much in content that I now say: if your rigged ship is sound, very well, then stay on
            it.</p>
      <p>However I’ll always maintain what I said should a calamity put you in a different
            position in relation to society. Were that ever to happen, I say in that regard: let it
            be a sign for you to make a complete change of profession, rather than starting all over
            again doing the same thing.</p>
      <p>But as long as you have your rigged ship, I don’t say that I advise you to put to sea in
            a fishingboat. Although I wouldn’t wish for G&amp;Cie’s rigged ship back, as far as I
            personally am concerned. At the time I thought, for God’s sake, calamity — do your
            worst!</p>
      <p>At first I didn’t know what to think about the change in the tone of your letters. Now,
            looking back, I think as regards your somewhat melancholy but for me so touching letter,
            written at a time when G&amp;Cie were being terribly nasty to you (a moment COMPARABLE
            to what I experienced myself) — now in hindsight I think, I say, that you took a
            different view of that moment when I said to the G&amp;Cie gentlemen ‘if you force me to
            go, I won’t refuse to go’, and that things really have calmed down, perhaps for good —
            and with your consent — so be it — I won’t object. Well, I do not take it amiss of you —
            because I believe that in such a case certain conditions that really are acceptable can
            be laid down — and I think that you would not have accepted them were there to have been
            anything dishonest in accepting them. <stress reason="family">But why I said something like, ‘if you stay then
            I’ll refuse your financial support,’ was because you had said ‘let me stay where I am
            because I have to take care of Pa, Ma, Wil and Marie’, and (although you didn’t mention
            me) me as well. Tact on your part not to mention me, to which I had to respond with tact
            on my part — I don’t want that — you sacrificing yourself in so far as you would stay
            there against your will for the sake of others. There you have what you interpreted as
            giving you an ultimatum.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>If you stay there because ‘you have a renewed pleasure in it’ — it’s all to the good as
            far as I’m concerned, and I congratulate you on your newly rigged ship, although for
            myself I have no desire to go back. What you write about Serret interests me greatly. A
            man like that who eventually produces something heartrending as blossom from a hard and
            difficult life is a phenomenon like the blackthorn, or better yet a gnarled old apple
            tree which suddenly bears blossoms that are among the tenderest and most ‘pure’ things
            under the sun.</p>
      <p>When a rough man blossoms — it’s indeed a beautiful sight — but HE has had to endure an
            awful lot of cold winters before then — more than even the later sympathizers know.</p>
      <p>The artist’s life and WHAT an artist is, that’s very curious — how deep is it —
            infinitely deep.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Because of your silence, inexplicable to me, and because I also associated it with the
            possible resumption of difficulties with the gentlemen, because for my part I was
            intolerably hardpressed as a result of the mistrust of the people in the lodgings, I
            dropped Pa a line that, not having heard from you, I didn’t know what to think and asked
            Pa for a loan.</stress>
         <stress reason="family">I added that I was uneasy both about you and about myself, particularly
            when I thought about the future, and I wished that both you and I had become painters
            when we were boys, and actually saw no reason why we two brothers shouldn’t be painters
            even now if G&amp;Cie were not to remain what it once was to you.</stress> Should Pa ever write
            to you about it, you know the reason for it, but I’ll write to Pa myself (I haven’t had
            a reply from Pa yet) that your last letter has made it plain to me that for the time
            being G&amp;Cie remains G&amp;Cie. I add this to you, not to Pa: since G&amp;Cie
            exercises an influence on our family, strangely compounded of good and evil; good,
            certainly, in any event because it prevents much stagnation (evil not being in question
            for the moment).</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>That my heart perhaps has and feels bitterness of its own is something that in my view
            you both understand and consequently forgive me out of yourself.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>Ultimatum — YOU speak of it — NOT I (at least my intention was something very different)
            — if you want to interpret it that way — then it’s all right with me, but I shall not be
            the first — nor have I been — for the moment your interpretation runs very far ahead of
            my intention. I would perhaps not contradict you any more than I did G&amp;Cie in the
            past, if you wanted to carry it through. Then I would say again, you said ultimatum
            first, NOT I. If you want to interpret it thus, then I don’t oppose this interpretation.
            With a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="family">Brother — after your last letter all my worst vague anxieties have been quieted — I mean
            that I have complete confidence in you as a man and in Marie.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">But I simply think that you’ll run into certain financial difficulties because of the
            course of events.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I advise you, if you can economize on something, then economize, that’s to say if you can
            put something by, then put something by.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">I myself have nothing at the moment — but I’ll see if I can arouse some interest in
            certain plans of mine — or if no one wants to come back to Drenthe with me later on,
            then at least see if I can’t find some credit for myself so that I can settle there. I’m
            not flush, I have nothing.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">I’ve seen how shaky your finances have been for a long time — you had too much on your
            shoulders — you think now that the future will put it right — I think you’ll find the
            future hostile in Paris.</stress> Again, if I’m wrong you can all laugh at me and I’ll laugh
            about it myself. If it’s just my nerves deluding me, well then, it’s my nerves — but I
            fear you all too effectively have a fatality against you.I’ll be able to write to you
            more calmly from home. <stress reason="money">There’s certainly a working environment for me in Drenthe, but
            preferably I’ll have to be able to look at things rather differently from the outset and
            have a little more certainty in my finances. I have to watch the cents — on a small
            scale; at present, for instance, obviously I concede that this is the first time you
            have definitely skipped — the difference of some 25 guilders is something that may stump
            me again for 6 weeks perhaps.</stress> I can readily believe that you can’t imagine this — you
            cannot know what sort of difficulties over and over again, each very small in itself,
            make something possible or impossible. Don’t take it amiss of me, but believe me that I
            have to try to take some steps in order to accomplish what I want. <stress reason="money">Last week, for
            instance, I got a note from my former landlord, who gave me the impression that he could
            seize my things that I left behind (including all my studies, prints, books — that I
            could hardly do without) if I didn’t send him 10 guilders that I’ve promised him as
            payment for the use of an attic room for my belongings, and some rent that it was
            doubtful he was entitled to claim, but I agreed on condition of an arrangement to store
            my things. I have to pay for other things by the New Year, I still have to pay Rappard,
            and I economized on everything I could. In short, it’s not the same as feeling flush.
            Things can’t remain as they are at present. I have to find a way out. I don’t say that
            you’re to blame, of course, but even last year I couldn’t have economized more than I
            did. And the harder I work, the more hardpressed I become. We’re now at a point where I
            say: at present I cannot go on.</stress>
      </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
