<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Saturday, <date>25 October <year>1884</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <work origin="existing" stage="finished">Here are a couple of smaller photos of the studies of which you already have the
                  larger ones. I’m sending them because — should it ever come to it — I want you to
                  be able to show something of mine.</work> Rappard is still here and will be staying for
                  another week since the work is going extraordinarily well. He’s making women
                  spinning and various studies of heads, has already made 10 studies or so, all of
                  which I consider fine.</p>
      <p>We’ve talked together quite a lot about Impressionism — I think that you would
                  classify his work as that. But here in Holland it’s hard to work out what
                  Impressionism is actually trying to say. But both he and I are greatly interested
                  in what the present aim is. And it’s certain that unexpected new ideas are
                  beginning to emerge. That paintings are once again beginning to be painted in very
                  different tone from a few years ago.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">The last thing I made is a rather large study of an avenue of poplars with the yellow
                  autumn leaves, where the sun makes glittering patches here and there on the fallen
                  leaves on the ground, which are interspersed with the long shadows cast by the
                  trunks. At the end of the road a peasant cottage, and the blue sky above it
                  between the autumn leaves.</work>
      </p>
      <p>I think that in a year’s time — having spent that year once again painting a great
                  deal and constantly — I’ll change my manner of painting and my colour a great
                  deal, and that I’m likely to become slightly more sombre rather than lighter. The
                  spectrum of Rappard’s work has also become much lower.</p>
      <p>The heads that he’s painting at present are reminiscent in their effect of certain
                  studies of heads by Courbet, say. But it’s becoming devilish good, that I can
                  assure you.</p>
      <p>Because of one thing and another I discussed with him, it may well be that I prefer
                  to stay here and carry on working here rather than go somewhere else.<good_health> As a result
                  of his visit I’ve again got new ideas for my own work, and have so many things in
                  my head which I’d like to make that, after all, I can’t easily postpone getting on
                  with them right away.</good_health>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Besides, I want to settle my paint bills before the New Year, and can’t afford any
                  extra expenditure. </stress>Because if I went to Antwerp I’d obviously want to do a lot of
                  work and would need models for it, which I fear would work out too dear for the
                  moment.</p>
      <p>But in general Rappard advises me not to do it right away, but after having painted
                  here for another few months, and to try to get a piedàterre to make nude
                  studies.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">But I’ll be able to benefit more from Antwerp if I first paint another 30 heads here
                  — and I’m starting on those 30 heads now, or rather I’ve already started with a
                  large bust of a shepherd.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Rappard has done the same in Drenthe and on Terschelling this summer, and it has
                  helped him to make a good deal of progress.</p>
      <p>I’ve just seen a reproduction of a Lhermitte — The inn — two workmen and a woman, do
                  you know it? The last few days R. and I have been on some long excursions, and
                  visited people house by house — we’ve seen lots of beautiful things, just because
                  of the magnificent autumnal effects. And also discovered new models. Perhaps a few
                  other painters might come to this region next year. I wish they would, because one
                  shouldn’t go for too long without ever seeing any painters.</p>
      <p>Well — as to that — I’ll get new acquaintances before too long in any event.</p>
      <p>Regards, from Rappard too.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
