<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Sunday, <date>20 July <year>1884</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <good_health>I was delighted to learn from your letter to Pa and Ma that you plan to go to London</good_health>
                  on 4 Aug. and then to come on here from there. I’m again looking forward very much
                  to your arrival and to finding out what you’ll think of the work that I’ve done
                  since. <work origin="existing" stage="finished">The last things I did are a couple of rather large studies of oxcarts, a
                  black ox and a red and white one.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">And have also been working again on the old tower in the fields in the evening; I’ve
                  made a larger study of it than my previous ones — with the wheatfields around
                  it.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Rappard sent me back the little book by Vosmaer that belongs to you — I started to
                  read it but — is it just me? — find it almighty boring and actually written in an
                  academic, sermonizing tone. Perhaps you will too when you look at it again. Have
                  you read Sapho by Daudet? <unstress reason="environment">It’s very beautiful, and so vigorous, and so close to
                  life that the female figure lives, breathes, and one can hear, literally hear the
                  voice, and forgets that one is reading.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>You’ll also <work stage="finished" origin="new">see a couple more new weavers </work>when you come.</p>
      <p>Nature is certainly pure here — I’m still very pleased with the studio, too.We must
                  visit some farms and weavers together when you come.</p>
      <p>Rappard’s plan is to come back again in October; he’s probably in Drenthe again
                  now.</p>
      <p>Well, I write in some haste because I’m hard at work. <good_health>I work a good deal early in the
                  morning or in the evening, and then sometimes everything is so inexpressibly
                  beautiful.</good_health>
      </p>
      <p>Regards, believe me</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
