<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>
      <date>8 December 1883</date>
   </head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>It’s still early; I wanted to add a word or two to my letter of yesterday in order to try
            to make a few things clearer to you. But I ask you to regard what I tell you in this
            letter as something I would keep silent about if I didn’t think I could rely on your
            discretion and intelligence.</p>
      <p>I haven’t said a word to Pa and Ma about the real question of two years ago. I have,
            though, spoken about a side issue at that time.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">For their part, Pa and Ma don’t even mention her name. Very well — they don’t have to
            speak to me about it, nor I to them. I did touch on it indirectly, though; I told Pa
            that in my view it was a great mistake that at a certain point (two years ago) I was
            forced to leave the house.</stress>
         <stress reason="money">I said that not only had considerable financial harm been the
            consequence, but also that, driven to the limit, I had been forced to go to extremes
            much more, to much greater intransigence than I would have displayed of my own free will
            alone.</stress> I pointed to the example of the Rappard family in contrast to the Van Gogh
            family. I pointed out how Rappard also has differences with his father about this or
            that, but that they always avoid extremes not only for the world but also for themselves
            and, although he doesn’t earn a penny from his work (which is nonetheless very sound,
            very fine even), Rappard can still always face the world with dignity, also in so far as
            equipment and studio &amp;c. are concerned. And how the family makes sure there are no
            debts anywhere with colourmen &amp;c. I told Pa how noble, how stalwart and how
            clearsighted I thought it was of you, Theo, that you’ve always helped me in so far as it
            was at all possible for you. <stress reason="family">I pointed out how, if Pa hadn’t been so steely and
            obstinate and in short unintelligent then, your help would have been effective, whereas
            now your help wasn’t effective and we’ve only half succeeded.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>So to that extent I certainly did touch on the past. <stress reason="family">At the same time I pointed out that
            at this moment it’s again difficult for me to avoid extremes, since the relationship to
            the family in general in which I feel I stand is so bad that it’s becoming clear to me
            that the bond between you and me cannot endure if everything is always just left as it
            is. That when I think about whether it’s right or wrong to accept money from you, I have
            to take appearances into consideration.I tell you frankly that I find the spirit in our
            family, particularly Pa’s and also, for instance, C.M.’s, more and more wrong.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>My position visàvis you now is this: on the one hand I believe that there’s still a
            possibility that your character, like mine, will go back on many of the things we were
            taught; yes, I say, I think it possible that you’ll have a change of heart, be it
            gradual, be it sudden, so that you’ll find yourself compelled to adopt another outlook
            on life, and that perhaps the upshot will be that you’ll yet become a painter.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, this is in stark contrast, for example, to what you said this summer:
            ‘I’m becoming more and more like Pa’.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">In the event of this last — that is, that you became more and more a ‘Van Gogh’, became a
            character like Pa or C.M. and by always being involved in business acquired an outlook
            on life entirely different from mine — a trader’s spirit, that is became a more or less
            political person — well, to be quite frank, then I’d rather not be intimate with you,
            then I’d find it better that, rather than strengthening bonds, we should let each other
            go, understanding we didn’t belong together.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>At present I’m observing Pa — I see, I hear, I feel what Pa is — and I don’t like it —
            decidedly not. If you are thus, if you’re becoming more and more thus — then it’s wise
            to part. Now I return to what I said to Pa, that it was a mistake that we quarrelled so
            seriously two years ago that the house has been barred to me since then — (whose fault
            it was doesn’t even matter that much; it would have been in accordance with Pa’s own
            principles — if he had maintained them consistently — that the quarrel itself should
            have been avoided — avoided come what may). What does Pa say to this? Yes, but I can’t
            take back anything I did then, I’ve always done everything for your own good, and I’ve
            always acted on my sincere opinion. To which I replied that a person’s ‘opinion’ may
            sometimes be diametrically opposed to his conscience, I mean what one THINKS one should
            do and what one ought to do may be diametrically opposed to one another. I told Pa that
            terms may be found in the Bible itself to judge whether our ‘opinions’ are fair and
            just.</p>
      <p>And that Pa was all too much in the habit of failing to do this and going on hotheadedly
            — in my view very unjustly, very arbitrarily, very reprehensibly — according to his
            ‘opinion’ — not — according to his conscience.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">Enough, so I was faced with an iron barrier of irreconcilability indeed, although Pa
            tried to mask it, tried to lead me around it and to divert me from pursuing it. But I
            didn’t allow myself to be put off by this, and said — Pa, this is about your
            selfrighteousness, which was and is fatal for you and for me. Then Pa said, ‘did you
            think I would go down on my knees to you?’ I said I took it very ill of Pa, thought it
            extremely crude, that Pa saw only that in it, and that I wouldn’t waste my breath on it
            any longer. Pa doesn’t have to tell me that he acted badly towards me, but Pa should
            have learnt what I learnt in those two years — that it was a great mistake in itself,
            and that it should have been redressed immediately without asking whose fault it was. So
            brother, in my view Pa eternally descends into pettymindedness instead of being more
            open, more liberal, broader, more humane. It was minister’s vanity that drove things to
            extremes then, and it’s still the same minister’s vanity that will still cause more
            mischief in the present and the future.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I don’t ask you to intercede, I ask you for something more personal, I ask you frankly:
            how do we stand towards each other; are you a ‘Van Gogh’ too?</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">I always regarded you as ‘Theo’. In character I’m quite different from the various
            members of the family, and I’m actually not a ‘Van Gogh’. But if you were to become a
            personality — played a part in the world like Pa or C.M. or Uncle V. even, very well, I
            wouldn’t interfere with that, I would accept you as you were, I would keep silent about
            it, but our paths would diverge too greatly for me to be able to continue regarding the
            financial tie advisable, as it stands now.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I hope you’ll understand me. If not, we’ll have to give it time. Who knows if, in the
            next 3 years, you won’t start to view some questions more or less as I do. Why? Because
            you’ll also be influenced by art and by mixing with artists, and in short may perhaps
            become squarer and broader in consequence instead of narrower and more constricted.</p>
      <p>Well old chap — if you can, see to it that I can get away from here — regards and believe
            me</p>
   </body>
   <close>Ever yours,</close>
   <sig>Vincent.</sig>
</letter>
