<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Sunday, <date>2 March 1884</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Thanks for your letter — Ma’s doing well — at the outset the doctor said it would be
                  six months before the leg had healed — now he’s talking about a good 3 months —
                  and he said to Ma — ‘but that’s your daughter’s fault, for I seldom, very seldom,
                  see such good care as she gives’. What Wil does is exemplary, exemplary, I shan’t
                  easily forget that.</p>
      <p>Almost everything has fallen on her shoulders from the outset, and she’s spared Ma a
                  great deal of misery.</p>
      <p>To mention just one thing, it’s definitely her fault that Ma has so few bedsores
                  (which started very badly at the beginning and had deteriorated). And I assure you
                  that the chores she has to do aren’t always pleasant.</p>
      <p>Now listen — when I’d read your letter about the drawings, I immediately sent you <work origin="new" stage="finished">a
                  new watercolour of a weaver</work> and <work stage="finished" origin="existing">five pen drawings</work>. <stress reason="career">For my part, too, I’ll tell you
                  frankly that I think that what you say is true, that my work will have to get much
                  better,</stress> but at the same time also that your efforts to do something with it might
                  also be a little more decisive. <stress reason="family">You have never yet sold a single thing of mine —
                  not for a lot or a little — and IN FACT HAVEN’T TRIED TO YET. As you can see, I’m
                  not getting angry about it — but — there’s no need to beat about the bush. I
                  certainly wouldn’t put up with it in the long run.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>For your part, you can also continue to speak frankly.</p>
      <p>As far as saleability and unsaleability are concerned, that’s an old file I don’t
                  intend to blunt my teeth on.</p>
      <p>Well, you see that my answer is that I send some new ones — and I’ll very willingly
                  go on doing so — Id like nothing better than that. Only you must be totally frank
                  for once — which is what I’d prefer — as to whether you think you’ll bother
                  yourself with them in the future, or whether your dignity won’t permit it. Leaving
                  aside the past — I’m facing the future, and not counting what you think of them, I
                  fully intend to try to do something with them.</p>
      <p>You recently told me yourself that you’re a dealer — very well — one doesn’t lapse
                  into sentimentality with a dealer; one says, sir, if I give you drawings on
                  commission, may I count on your showing them? The dealer has to decide for himself
                  whether he wants to say yes — no — or something in between.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">But the painter would be foolish to send them on commission if he could tell that the
                  dealer considered his work to be something that shouldn’t see the light of
                  day.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Now, old chap — we both live in the real world — and precisely because we don’t want
                  to put a spoke in each other’s wheels, we must speak candidly. If you say — I
                  can’t be bothered with them — very well, I won’t get angry about it — but then I’m
                  not obliged to believe that you’re an absolute oracle either, am I?</p>
      <p>You say: the public will be annoyed by this little spot. Now listen, that may be so,
                  but this or that bothers you, the dealer, much more than the public in question,
                  I’ve already remarked on that so often — and you start with that. I have to fight
                  my way through, too, Theo, and with you I’m still at precisely, precisely the same
                  level as a few years ago. What you say of my current work — ‘it is almost saleable
                  but’ — is word for word the same as what you wrote to me when I sent you my first
                  Brabant sketches from Etten. So I say — it’s an old file. And my reasoning is that
                  I foresee that you’ll always say the same thing — and that <stress reason="career">I, who until today have
                  been consistently rather chary of making approaches to dealers, will now change
                  tactics and become very assiduous in trying to sell my work.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>I do understand that you couldn’t care less about my doings. But if you couldn’t care
                  less, for my part I always find it fairly wretched and rather dread things that
                  will probably crop up — namely that people will ask me: what, don’t you do
                  business with your brother or with Goupil? Well, then I’ll say — it’s beneath the
                  dignity of those Messrs Gie, Van Gogh Co. This will probably create a bad
                  impression of me — which I’m quite prepared for — but which I foresee will
                  consequently make me cooler and cooler towards you too</bad_health>.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="finished">I’ve now painted the little old church and another new weaver.</work> Are the studies from
                  Drenthe really so very bad? I don’t feel inclined to send you the painted studies
                  from here, no, let’s not start on that — you can see them if you come here
                  sometime in the spring, perhaps.</p>
      <p>What you write about Marie is quite understandable — if a woman isn’t very milk and
                  water I can very well imagine that she has little inclination to mope around with
                  cantankerous fathers and pious sisters, at least a woman as much as a man would
                  feel a fairly pressing temptation to end that stagnation, come what may.</p>
      <p>Stagnation that begins with a resignation that is perhaps fine in itself, but which
                  alas one must come to regret, usually, when one feels one would eventually freeze.
                  Read something by Daudet about pious women, ‘Those two faces looked at each other
                  — they exchanged a spiteful, cold, closed look — what’s the matter with him/her?
                  Always the same thing’. There you have it, that singular look of Pharisees and
                  devout ladies. Yes, therefore we always lack — the same thing. Yes — what am I
                  supposed to think about what you say about my work? For example, <work stage="finished" origin="existing">I’ll now turn
                  specifically to the studies from Drenthe — there are some among them that are very
                  superficial, I said that myself — but what do I get served up for the ones that
                  were simply painted quietly and calmly outdoors, trying to say nothing in them but
                  what I saw? </work>I get in return: aren’t you too preoccupied with Michel? (I’m talking
                  here about the study of the little hut in the dark and about the largest of the
                  sod huts, namely the one with the little green field in the foreground.) You would
                  certainly say exactly the same thing about the little old churchyard.</p>
      <p>And yet, neither looking at the little churchyard nor at the sod huts did I think
                  about Michel, I thought about the subject I was looking at. A subject indeed such
                  that I believe, if Michel had passed by, it would have brought him to a halt and
                  struck him.</p>
      <p>For my part, I certainly don’t put myself on a par with master Michel — but I
                  definitely don’t therefore imitate Michel either.</p>
      <p>Well, I may perhaps try to sell something in Antwerp, and I’d like to put a couple of
                  those selfsame Drenthe studies in black wooden frames — which I’m looking for at a
                  carpenter’s here — I prefer to see my work in a deep black frame, and he makes
                  them cheaply enough. You mustn’t take it amiss that I mention it, brother.</p>
      <p>I’m seeking something calm and something cool in my work. No more than I approve of
                  its just lying about, do I want my work to be displayed in fluted frames in the
                  leading galleries, you see. <stress reason="family">And now it’s time to begin on that middle way, in my
                  view, and I have to know fairly definitely how I stand with you, or rather I tell
                  you that, although you’re still evading the issue in what you say, I believe that
                  you will not in fact show it. And I don’t even believe that you’ll change your
                  mind for the time being.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Whether you’re right or wrong about this — I’m not going into that. You’ll tell me
                  that I’ll be treated by other dealers exactly the same as by you, except that,
                  <stress reason="money">although you can’t be bothered with my work, you furnish me with money anyway, and
                  other dealers certainly won’t do that, and without money I’ll become completely
                  stuck.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I say in reply that things aren’t as clearcut as that in real life, and that I’ll see
                  how far I get living from day to day. I told you beforehand that I wanted to
                  settle these matters this month, and so it must be done.<stress reason="career"> Well, because you
                  probably plan to come as early as the spring I don’t insist that you make a final
                  decision immediately, but realize that I can’t accept it as it is now — for
                  myself, wherever I go and especially at home, too, I’m always being watched — what
                  I do with my work, whether I get anything for it and, in short in society almost
                  everyone looks out for it all the time and wants to know all about it.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>And this is very understandable. Well, it’s very wretched for me always being in a
                  false position.</p>
      <p>Come on — things can’t stay the same as they are now. Why not? Because they
                  can’t.</p>
      <p>If I’m as cool as can be to Pa — to C.M. — why should I behave any differently
                  towards you were I to observe in you precisely the same tactics of never speaking
                  out. Do I consider myself better than Pa or you? Perhaps not, perhaps I divide
                  things less and less into good and bad — but I do know that these tactics don’t
                  befit a painter and that, as a painter, one must speak out and resolve certain
                  things. In short — I believe that a door should either be open or shut.</p>
      <p>Well, I think you do understand that a dealer cannot be neutral towards painters —
                  that it makes exactly the same impression whether you say no with or without
                  mincing your words, and that it may be even more infuriating when it’s said
                  wrapped up in compliments.</p>
      <p>Now here’s something that you’ll perhaps understand later on better than you do now —
                  I pity dealers when they get old — even if they’ve already made their piles — that
                  doesn’t solve everything — at least not then. Everything has its price, and an
                  icecold wilderness is what it often becomes for them then.</p>
      <p>Well — but you’ll perhaps think differently about it. And you’ll say that it’s also
                  pretty sad when a painter dies miserably in a hospital and is buried with the
                  whores in the common grave — where a lot of them lie, after all — <bad_health>particularly
                  when one considers that dying may not be as difficult as living.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>Well, one can’t take it amiss that a dealer doesn’t always have the money to help,
                  but one can, in my view, take it amiss if one notices that this respectable dealer
                  or that speaks very cordially, but he’s ashamed of me in his heart and he
                  completely ignores my work. <stress reason="career">So frankly, I won’t take it amiss if you say straight
                  out that you don’t think my work is good enough or that there are, moreover, yet
                  other reasons why you can’t be bothered with it, but if you leave it in a corner
                  somewhere and you don’t show it, this isn’t kind if it’s accompanied by the
                  assurance — WHICH IS NOT LIKELY — that you yourself see something in it. I don’t
                  believe that — you mean practically none of it. And precisely because you say
                  yourself that you know my work better than anyone else, I may assume that you must
                  think very badly of it indeed if you don’t want to soil your hands with it. Why
                  should I force myself on you?</stress> Well, regards.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Apart from a few years which I find hard to understand myself, when I was confused
                  by religious ideas — by a sort of mysticism — leaving aside that period, I’ve
                  always lived with a certain warmth. Now it’s all becoming bleaker and colder and
                  duller around me. </bad_health>And when I tell you that in the first place I WILL not stand it
                  like this, never mind whether or not I can, I refer to what I said right at the
                  very beginning of our relationship. What I’ve had against you in the last year is
                  a sort of relapse into cold decency, which I find sterile and of no use to one —
                  diametrically opposed to everything that is action, especially to everything that
                  is artistic. </p>
      <p> I say it as I see it, not to make you wretched but to get you to see and feel if
                  possible the reason that I no longer think of you as a brother and friend with the
                  same pleasure as before. There has to be more zest in my life if I want to get
                  more brio into my brush — I won’t get a hair’s breadth further by exercising
                  patience. If, for your part, you relapse into the abovementioned, don’t then take
                  it amiss if I’m not the same towards you as I was in the first year, say. About my
                  drawings — at this moment it seems to me that <work stage="finished" origin="existing">the watercolours, the pen drawings
                  of the weavers,</work>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">the latest pen drawings I’m working on now,</work> aren’t so dull on the
                  whole that they’re nothing at all. But if I come to the conclusion: they’re no
                  good, and Theo is right not to show them to anyone — then — then — it will be all
                  the more proof that I have good reason to dislike our present false position, and
                  will try all the more to change, come what may — better or worse, but not the
                  same. Now if I saw that, if you didn’t think I’d improved enough, you did
                  something about it to get me further along by introducing me to another capable
                  painter, for instance, because Mauve has dropped out, or anyway something, some
                  sign or other that proved to me that you really believed in my progress or
                  promoted it. <stress reason="money">But no, there’s — yes, the money — but otherwise nothing except that
                  ‘just keep on working’, ‘be patient’ — as cold, as dead, as arid and as
                  insufferable, just as if, for instance, Pa said it. I can’t live on that — it’s
                  too lonely, too cold, too empty and too lacklustre for me.</stress>
      </p>
      <p> I’m no better than anyone else, in so far as I have my needs and desires like
                  everyone, and it’s very understandable that one reacts knowing for sure that one
                  is really being kept dangling, in the dark. </p>
      <p> If one goes from bad to worse — this wouldn’t be impossible in my case — what would
                  it matter? If one is badly off, one has to take a chance of making things better. </p>
      <p> Brother — I really must remind you of how I was at the very beginning of what we
                  began. <stress reason="love">Right from the outset I’ve talked to you about the question of women. I
                  still recall that I took you to the station in Roosendaal in the first year, and
                  that I said to you then that I was so against being alone that I would rather be
                  with a common whore than alone</stress>. Perhaps you remember that. I found the idea that
                  our relationship might not last almost unbearable at first. And I so very much
                  wished that it had been simple to change things. However I can’t always keep on
                  fooling myself that this can be done against the grain. </p>
      <p> The depression about it has thus been one of the reasons I wrote to you so
                  assertively from Drenthe, become a painter yet. Which cooled off immediately when
                  I saw that your dissatisfaction about business matters vanished when you were on
                  better terms with Goupil again. </p>
      <p> At first I thought it was only half sincere — then later, and now, still, I think it
                  very understandable and think it more a mistake on my part that I wrote to you,
                  become a painter, than on yours that you resumed your affairs with enthusiasm when
                  they became more possible to resume and the machinations making it impossible for
                  you ceased. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">What remains, though, is that I still feel depressed by the falseness of the
                  position between us. At this moment it’s more important for me to sell for 5
                  guilders than to receive 10 guilders by way of patronage. </stress>Well, you repeatedly
                  write, actually most definitely, that you haven’t made, aren’t making, nor believe
                  for the present you’re able to make the least or slightest effort for my work;
                  first, not as a dealer (I let that pass, and at least don’t take it amiss of you)
                  but, secondly, not in private either (and that I do take somewhat amiss of you).
                  In this case I mustn’t sit doing nothing or be a funker,<stress reason="family"> so straight out, if you
                  do nothing with my work, I don’t want your patronage. I state the reason plainly
                  and I’ll state it precisely the same way, when giving a reason for it is hard to
                  avoid.</stress>
      </p>
      <p> So it isn’t that I want to ignore or belittle your help from the start until now.
                  It’s a matter of my seeing more benefit in even the poorest, most wretched
                  muddling along than in patronage (which it’s degenerating into). </p>
      <p> One can’t do without it at the very, very beginning, but now I must for God’s sake,
                  God knows how, just start muddling along rather than acquiesce in something that
                  would take us no further anyway. Brotherly or not brotherly, if you can do nothing
                  other than absolutely the financial alone, you might as well keep that too. As it
                  has been in the last year, I almost dare to say, it was confined solely to money. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="love">And although you say you give me a completely free hand, it seemed to me, at bottom,
                  that if I do this or that with a woman, for instance, that you and others don’t
                  approve of (perhaps rightly disapprove of, but sometimes I don’t give a damn about
                  that), there comes one of those little tugs on the pursestrings just to make me
                  feel that it’s ‘in my interest’ to go along with your opinion.</stress>
      </p>
      <p> So you got your way regarding the woman, and it was finished, but — — — — — — what
                  damn good is it to me to get a bit of money if it means I have to practise
                  morality? Yet in itself I don’t think it something absurd in you when you
                  disapproved this summer of my still wanting to go through with it. But I can
                  foresee the following in the future: <stress reason="love">I’ll have another relationship in what you
                  people call the lower orders — and again, if I still have a relationship with you,
                  meet the same opposition. Opposition that you people could only carry through with
                  any semblance of fairness if I received so much from you that I could do something
                  different.</stress> Which you don’t give and can’t or won’t give, after all — neither you,
                  nor Pa, nor C.M. or the rest, who are always first off the mark to disapprove of
                  this or that — and which I don’t after all want from you either, since I don’t
                  give much thought to the lower or upper orders. </p>
      <p> Do you see why it wasn’t an irresponsible action on my part, and wouldn’t be if I
                  were to try it again? </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health> Because first I don’t have any pretension, don’t feel any desire at all, and
                  secondly don’t receive the means from anyone whatsoever, or earn them, to keep up
                  some sort of position or whatever you call it — I consider myself completely at
                  liberty to consort with the socalled lower orders if the opportunity arises.</bad_health> We’d
                  perpetually return to the same questions. </p>
      <p> Just ask yourself now if I’m alone among those in the same profession who would most
                  definitely turn down patronage if it entails obligations to maintain some sort of
                  position while the money wasn’t enough to be able to do it, so that one gets into
                  debt rather than make progress. If it could be done on the money, I might perhaps
                  not refuse to bend, any more than others do. But we’re certainly not that far at
                  present — I have a stretch of years in front of me, as you say yourself, when my
                  work will have very little commercial value. Very well — THEN I WOULD RATHER FALL
                  INTO THE HANDS OF MUDDLING ALONG and of living through hard times — which I’ve
                  done more than once — than into the hands of Messrs Van Gogh. </p>
      <p> My only regret about arguing with Pa when I did is that I didn’t do it 10 years
                  earlier. If you carry on in the footsteps of Pa and — you’ll just see how you’ll
                  gradually get annoyed — and — how you would also become annoying to certain
                  people. But those are awkward customers and, you’ll say — they’re of no
                  consequence.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
