<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Saturday, <date>6 December 1884</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>Many thanks for your letter and the enclosure, and also for what I received for St
            Nicholas too. I want to start by telling you that your letter really amazed me — because
            there has been no difference of any significance between Pa and Ma and myself, <stress reason="family">and that
            as regards the Begemann ladies, they’ve just very recently been to see Pa and Ma in
            considerable numbers — not just once but several times. Whether they come as often as or
            less often than before is something I can’t see that I have anything to do with, nor
            take the least or slightest interest in.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>The fact that I disapprove of their attitude and will certainly continue to do so is
            something that I told them once — succinctly — without reverting to it again.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="friendship">But that has nothing further to do with whether or not they come to our house, which
            concerns not me but Pa and Ma and themselves. I have been courteous to everyone in that
            family and did not start it but they attacked me and, which bothered me more, Margot —
            that’s why I’ve absolutely avoided contact with them — precisely because I don’t feel
            capable of taking back my decided disapproval of their attitude in this matter — or of
            concealing it.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>What you also know yourself — I say this for clarity, not to cause you sorrow — what you
            also know yourself, that in order to show you how I said what I said with composure I
            deliberately dropped you a brief line that I thought your own opinion wrong — (whether
            it is wrong is for you to decide, but I thought and think it wrong).</p>
      <p>So this is my subjective conviction — I have my own ideas in these things — my whys and
            wherefores — which I can feel better for myself than make them clear to you or anyone
            else — particularly when they have neither your attention nor your sympathy.
            <stress reason="career">Consequently, I let people say and think whatever they will of me more than you might
            imagine — but you can take this much from me ‘for your guidance’ — that just because I
            failed in something I don’t admit that I shouldn’t have started it — on the contrary, if
            I fail many times I find this a reason even if it’s sometimes impossible to continue in
            exactly the same way — nevertheless to try again in the same direction, since my
            convictions, too, are considered and intended by me, and I believe that there’s a raison
            d’être for them.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>For me personally, there’s a cardinal point of distinction between before and after the
            revolution — the reversal of the social position of the woman, and the collaboration one
            wants between men and women with equal rights, with equal freedom.</p>
      <p>I have neither the words nor the time to expand on this, nor, in the circumstances, the
            inclination. But enough, to my mind conventional morality is all backtofront and I hope
            it will be turned around and replaced in time.</p>
      <p>Now — as to what you say about yourself, probably also for my guidance, ‘that you are
            mistrustful’ — very well — I don’t want to influence that. You’ve most certainly shown
            me this — and it’s one of those ‘symptoms’ which I told you I didn’t find very
            attractive nor congratulated you on.</p>
      <p>But this, too, is a subjective opinion if you will. So go ahead, be mistrustful or not
            mistrustful as the mood takes you, I will in any event see to it that I accept the
            consequences for me, and can otherwise only refer you to what I said about standing on
            different sides of a barricade. <stress reason="family">Do what you want according to your principles — but I’ll
            act according to mine, and only — if possible, let’s avoid aiming at each other because
            we’re brothers. I’m older than you, and I’ve probably experienced some things
            differently and interpreted them differently from you. And this is my own
            responsibility, of course. That I can’t approve of everything I see you do or hear you
            say is something very different from wanting to bring you round to my point of view.
            It’s just — I like to lay my cards on the table.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>And bearing in mind that we must see to it that we avoid putting a spoke in each other’s
            wheels, I will, as I said, increasingly try to find other contacts or connections in
            Eindhoven, in Antwerp, in short, wherever I can.</p>
      <p>But this can’t be done all at once — and for my part it’s simply and solely because
            you’ve shown me all too clearly and unmistakably that I mustn’t imagine that you intend
            to involve yourself with me personally or with my work other than by way of patronage.
            Well, you can count me out. <stress reason="family">And while, without words, without sympathy, I’ve received
            the money very regularly but very coolly each month, I have — kept working — but —
            increasingly realizing that a moment could come when we each go our own way instead of
            the same way together. </stress>
         <stress reason="money">I don’t suppose in the least that I’ll gain by it financially —
            but — as soon as some dealer or other, however much of a cheapjack — gives me board and,
            even if it’s a tiny attic, lodgings and some paint, I’ll sell myself with great pleasure
            — if you choose to call it selling. Preferable to patronage. </stress>There you see my cards on
            the table. And whether I’ll succeed in this and when? <stress reason="career">I can’t say precisely, but — I
            work too hard for me to be so very far away from it. I want, precisely because I foresee
            that if our paths ever lead us to the same place we might well find ourselves
            considerably at odds — I want you not to be able to blame me then for being dependent on
            you. I’m still in two minds as to what I should try to do — but I’ll most probably not
            stay here after all — and then where to go will be the question.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">I don’t think that you’ll approve of my coming to Paris — but what can I do about it? You
            flatly refuse to look after my interests </stress>— very well — but I can’t just leave it at
            that. I wouldn’t have thought of it if you had written less decidedly that it was
            beneath you, but now — well, now — I can take no notice of you.</p>
      <p>In short, I don’t want to exchange the chance (even if it is only a chance) of making it,
            not even for the certainty of patronage which is, after all, rather tight.</p>
      <p>Since I see that I’m forfeiting my chance of selling by continuing to take the money from
            you, we must just part. <stress reason="money">Don’t you find it very understandable that, when I hear you say
            that you can’t do anything with my work for the next few years, I then get the slight
            sense that, if you want to remain high and mighty on this point, there’s a rather odd
            contradiction if — precisely because I’m not selling, however hard I work — I’m forced
            to say, Theo, I’m 25 guilders short, couldn’t you let me have a bit extra, then this
            proves not to be possible.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>This is very contrary of you: when one sends you something or one asks, please, try to
            find an opening with the illustrated magazines so that I can earn something extra — one
            hears no more about it and you don’t lift a finger.</p>
      <p>But one may not say, I can’t manage on my money.</p>
      <p>And up to now — all right — but to carry on — impossible. I also want to tell you that I
            shan’t be asking you whether you approve or disapprove of anything I do or don’t do — I
            won’t be embarrassed and, if I feel like going to Paris, for instance, I shan’t ask you
            whether or not you object. <stress reason="money">The drawback to painting is the paint bill. And at the moment
            I’m having a far from easy time with it. I already immediately paid out 40 guilders (80
            francs) of what was sent. Moreover also paid the carpenter for things. So that if, after
            deduction of what you had to pay, you still had 100 francs left — I have less than 25
            francs left, and although I don’t have to live on it at the moment, as you do, I still
            have to paint on it for a month, which, with models, with paints, is impossible this
            way.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>And I also have this pleasing prospect for January, when I’ll have to pay some more. <stress reason="money">So
            what I’m complaining about and why I said that it was actually most decidedly essential
            that I had something extra now and not later was so that I could for God’s sake at least
            keep working, and if I’m definitely stuck for financial reasons, it makes me very
            discontented. And for which I can’t then accordingly blame myself alone, because what I
            have to pay isn’t caused by extravagance but by working.</stress> If you can’t enter into this or
            sympathize, and choose to be mistrustful — well, old chap — I believe you really mean
            well and so — I really don’t take your mistrustfulness too much to heart. Except to the
            extent that if you’re doing it deliberately to get rid of me, you’re truly well on the
            way to achieving that goal.</p>
      <p>In the past you know that I often specifically asked you that we should keep up the
            relationship — now I could no longer urge it in the same way. <stress reason="career">Again, I work too hard for
            me to have to remain for much longer in a dependent position which degenerates too much
            into patronage, while when I write about it in a businesslike way I don’t even get an
            answer. No — old chap — seeing something in it that I may continue to regard as lasting
            is no longer reconcilable with my sense of honour, of justice.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Listen — Pa — has been very often and very seriously — mistrustful — of me. You know your
            side of that anyway, and I for my part perhaps know even more about it. But —
            nonetheless — he always called himself ‘my friend’ nonetheless — the man thought that he
            was right and simply couldn’t see any differently — and — so, after all — meant well if
            you will — namely.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">But for my part, one day I spoke out foursquare and said, don’t call yourself my friend
            if you think this or that of me — people who think of me like that, they’re not friends
            but enemies, the worst enemies as sure as 2 x 2 = 4. This also applies to you in answer
            to what you say about mistrust. With this distinction (which I’m willing to appreciate
            and take into account), Pa did not add ‘that he was mistrustful’, you add that — which
            makes up for a lot. Yet at bottom I still see the same thing in it.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Now I don’t want to influence anything, though — and I say bluntly that on my part I
            don’t in the least undertake to agree with Pa or you. Be aware of that — quite possibly
            there’s even more than a ditch between the two. And because something of the kind is
            quite possible, be aware that I absolutely do not urge you to think all sorts of fine
            and good things about me according to your or Pa’s view of things. It might well be that
            mine is opposed to them in a revolutionary way. I can’t worry about what people think of
            me — I must move forward, that’s what I have to think about.And so I go my way with a
            certain obstinacy, believing in some things and not in others. You — and rightly — set
            store by your position — don’t you? — by making progress or not making progress — your
            affairs going poorly or well. Well now, know that I too shall certainly stand up for my
            profession with no weaker motive than you have for yours. And without going about it all
            too delicately, must and will persevere. And also very certainly think to keep on my
            studio here — like Stengelin does, for instance, who has one on the Drenthe heaths —
            even if he happens to live somewhere else. I’ve rented it as a refuge and it will
            continue to serve me as such.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">So — taking rooms in Eindhoven would be sheer nonsense — and I can’t even think about it.
            A room in Antwerp later on, all right — that is indeed my intention — but firstly I
            don’t have any money for it now</stress>, and secondly <work origin="new" stage="planned">I still want to paint a fairly large
            number of heads first</work> —<stress reason="money"> with which I’ll make progress — to the extent that it’s at all
            possible for me to pay the models.</stress> Which in the circumstances, as you say, things don’t
            exactly foster. I can’t do any silly things just like that in the circumstances, and
            cook my own goose by breaking off here at a moment that doesn’t lend itself to it — just
            because you’re in a mistrustful period. But be aware of this, that if this mistrustful
            period endures with you and seems about to take root — even if I don’t do any silly
            things just like that — I’m nonetheless seriously thinking of seeing to it that we can
            part in peace and without damage to you or me.However, my very sincere thanks each time
            for what is sent, and know that if I press for a little extra — it’s precisely in order
            to continue until we can part, but — in peace — and without harm to you or me.Theo.
            Although appreciating your proposal to add another 50 francs monthly over and above the
            100 francs I asked for, intended as a contribution to Pa towards the cost of my keep, I
            must most decidedly refuse this (the 50 francs). If I’ve been here at home this long
            without paying for my board and lodging, you may regard that if you will as arrogance or
            tactlessness on my part. I did it for the sake of the progress of the painting, and have
            not profited from it myself in so far as even now I still have a fairly steep paint bill
            to pay, as surplus expenditure. Apart from that, I acknowledge that it has been
            advantageous to me after all.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">But the reason why I don’t think now is a suitable moment to make a sort of contract with
            Pa is that under the circumstances it cannot be part of my plans to intend to stay here
            for very much longer. Which I would like but, I must fear, will prove impossible.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>However, if you do want to agree something with Pa to the effect you indicate in your
            letter, let it be without involving me at all and in other words a matter between you
            and Pa which concerns me not at all.</p>
      <p>So that I can then continue to regard the fact that I live here as tactlessness on my
            part in all events, thus also in the event of payment by you.</p>
      <p>When I’m better I’ll probably go and live in the studio, at least in the daytime.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">It’s too much for me all at once, losing you in this respect, and having to pay for my
            keep again as well. Gradually, though, I’ll see to it that I find another resource of my
            own accord.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">If it can give you any satisfaction that what you call ‘my plans for the future’ are also
            lying pretty much in ruins,</stress> good luck to you. However, this is still no reason for me to
            approve of your views in this regard, which, I must repeat, I continue to find bad.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">I cannot give up the studio yet — I have to have something fixed, and they can’t in any
            event demand of me that I leave the village. The fact that it can be foreseen that I
            have to prepare myself for this, though, is precisely the point that makes me regret
            that I didn’t already realize last year that our arrangement was unsustainable for both
            of us. </stress>Regards.VincentI must object to an underlined section in your letter — which I
            copy.</p>
      <p>‘And I therefore request you, from now on, out of the 150 francs, which I shall keep on
            sending you, as agreed when we were good friends, it was accepted by us both to give 50
            francs to Pa.’</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">I object to that, it’s not true that ‘when we were still good friends’ and we agreed that
            I should pay 50 francs. I remember the conversation about it — in the garden — very
            well, and far from agreeing to something, I wasn’t willing to agree to anything of that
            sort then, on that occasion, and it ended with my pointing out to you fairly forcefully
            that I needed money to get started on several larger canvases I was planning, and had
            other expenses enough. If anything was agreed, it was for later, when I would be more on
            top of things.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>This letter tells you explicitly that I flatly refuse to have anything to do with what
            you might want to agree with Pa about possible payment for board.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Now in order to avoid further misunderstanding in this regard, about this 50 francs for
            board, I let Pa read your letter of today and this letter. I don’t want to hear any more
            about this matter; you settle it with Pa. I tell you once more, it’s not true I agreed
            to pay 50 francs for my board, if I had promised that I would have kept to it, but I
            remember the whole conversation about it and it’s simply the opposite, namely that I
            told you that for the time being I had too much else to pay, that I couldn’t do it
            yet.</stress>
      </p>
   </body>
   <close/>
   <sig/>
</letter>
