<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Thursday, <date>20 March 1884</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I just received your letter and the 250 francs enclosed. If I may regard your letter
                  as a reply to my proposal, I would certainly be able to accept what you say. For
                  my part I simply wish — in order to avoid correspondence, dispute — in order to be
                  able to say something when one is railed at in daily life by one person or another
                  as being ‘without means of support’ — that if I continue to receive the usual from
                  you, I may regard it as money that I’ve earned. Naturally I’ll send you work every
                  month. That work, as you say, is then your property — and I completely agree with
                  you that in that case you have every right to do nothing with it — indeed, I
                  wouldn’t even be in a position to object if you thought fit to tear it up.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">I for my part, needing money, am obliged to accept it even if someone says to me ‘I
                  don’t want to do anything with this drawing of yours or burn it, you can have this
                  much for it’ — in the circumstances I’d say — very well — give me the money — here
                  you have my work — I want to get on — in order to get on I must have money — I’m
                  seeing to it that I get it — and so — if need be, even if I really didn’t give a
                  damn about you, as long as I receive money from you each month that is useful and
                  necessary to me (without conditions that I may not do this, that or the other), I
                  won’t break the ties, and if need be I’ll put up with anything.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>This way of mine of regarding you and your money balances your way of regarding me
                  and my work — and as long as it remains in balance — I’ll accept it.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="friendship">If I receive money from you, you drawings or paintings from me — and I have something
                  to justify myself in the view of society and we otherwise have nothing in common
                  with each other, if need be — don’t write or talk about anything — even then it’s
                  enough for me for the moment and I accept it completely. Even if it pleases you to
                  tear my work up or if you want to do nothing with it, or if you want to do
                  something with it, I no longer have the right to criticize as soon as, for my
                  part, I may regard it as a purchase. </stress>Be so good as to tell me which term of abuse
                  I used about your friend Braat in my letter.</p>
      <p>In my letter, as far as I know, there was nothing about Braat except that I thought
                  he was already ill in the months that I knew him at Cie in Paris. At that time, as
                  far as I can recall, I got on very well with him, and I really don’t understand
                  how you get the idea that I ‘can’t stand’ him. So many years have passed, so much
                  has changed for me in those years, that the people I knew then are fairly vague
                  and indistinct in my memory and — that I seldom if ever think about them — which
                  nobody can blame me for, I believe. But as to Braat, far from my not wanting to
                  take any special notice of him, now that you’ve written about it that way, will
                  you please assure him that my sympathies are with him, as they would be with any
                  sufferer, and that, if he happens to remember me, I send my regards and wish him
                  as much peace and serenity as one may have in such a situation. Yet what good does
                  such a wish do him — not much — so, unless one is called upon to say something,
                  one keeps such things to oneself. I would ask you though, if you’ve said something
                  to him about my having written about him in the way you reproach me with, to tell
                  him that you had only seen that term of abuse in your imagination. For you
                  definitely won’t find it in my letter.</p>
      <p>You write that you had tried to answer my letters, but had left off. For my part,
                  too, I had wanted to write to you since then, but also left off.</p>
      <p>Know that if you don’t want to do anything with the work you buy from me, or tear it
                  up if need be, this will be no reason for me not to do my best in it.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="finished">For this month I have some pen drawings for you; in the first place the ones that are
                  with Rappard at the moment — about which I have a letter from him that he thought
                  they were all beautiful, and the sentiment in Behind the hedgerows and the
                  Kingfisher particularly beautiful.</work>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">Then those first 3 Winter gardens too, which he
                  was also taken with. </work>Aside from those, <work origin="new" stage="finished">I have some painted studies that are your
                  property</work> — to do with just as you will — which I can send you if you wish — which,
                  if you yourself don’t care to have them, I would ask you if I might keep for a
                  while so as to work from them.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">One is a large weaver who is weaving a piece of red cloth — the little church amidst
                  the wheat — a view of a little old village near here.</work>I’d just like to come back to
                  your letter about my drawings — the one you say I’ve interpreted utterly
                  impossibly.</p>
      <p>I see in it first that, among the things you say, there are a few whose tenor is that
                  there were things that pleased you in the tone, in the sentiment — so much the
                  better — if you will, that gives me a good deal of pleasure.</p>
      <p>Second, in that letter there’s a comparison of the schools of Millet and Lhermitte. I
                  found what you said about Millet better and more sensitive expressions than I am
                  used to from you — this was overshadowed, however, by the way you were again tired
                  of Lhermitte, and I’d also like to say about your whole argument once again,
                  you’re splitting your hairs too thin — why didn’t you take a broader view, why
                  didn’t you feel the same enthusiasm for both (who to my mind are to each other as
                  Rembrandt is to Maes, say) without immersing yourself in barren hairsplitting
                  about who is the greater? Third, there was something that was not in that letter,
                  namely an answer to the question as to whether we’d go on or not.</p>
      <p>That was the question that it was all about, and since my work depends on my paint
                  and tools (to an extent that I can’t ignore), and they in turn on whether or not I
                  receive money, I can’t possibly ascribe much usefulness to that letter.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">It would be less impossible for me to preserve my composure in our correspondence if,
                  when you don’t have the money on the date, you were to write, I haven’t got it,
                  you’ll get it at such and such a time. Now you wrote not a word in response to my
                  saying: it surprises me that I hear nothing, my having said I’d rather have it at
                  once than later, because you said that if I need it I can get the money by return.
                  If you’d written again then, I’m sorry but I haven’t got it, I shouldn’t have had
                  to get ideas into my head that you’re deliberately being lax in order to make my
                  life a bit more difficult.</stress> And — when you haven’t got it, I can’t take it amiss —
                  when you ignore — deliberately or not deliberately — that’s something that I
                  really wish you could cure yourself of, and something about which one really has
                  to get angry. What I said about doing something with my work, in Antwerp, for
                  instance, definitely is my plan. <stress reason="money">The frame of mind in which you now are about me,
                  the frame of mind in which I now am about you, is cool enough simply to ask and to
                  reply coolly. After all — leaving aside — giving a damn about each other or not —
                  can I count on its being fixed for 1 year that I’ll continue to receive the usual
                  monthly in return for supplying my work? Why I have to know this is because, if I
                  can count on it, I would take a slightly roomier studio somewhere, which I need in
                  order to be able to work with a model.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>The one I have at present has the following geographical location,and my powers of
                  imagination aren’t strong enough to think this an improvement on the situation
                  last year. This doesn’t alter the fact that, if I complain about something, there
                  appear in your letters such passages as: I (Theo) think that your position is
                  better now than last summer. Really? And I also draw the little map in response to
                  your expression ‘I’m not aware’, and I would also not be content with this letter
                  of yours if that wasn’t in it. To which I say — I don’t care whether or not you’re
                  aware that this or that isn’t quite in order, as long as you just don’t ask me to
                  walk round befuddled about it, and as long as you give me the means to improve
                  things I have no objection to your being ‘aware’ of all sorts of things.</p>
      <p>I hope this letter is as cool as yours — and I thank you very much for what you sent
                  — which makes up for the rest — at least makes it such that, if I could count on
                  its continuing thus for a year, I ask nothing more of you and will right gladly
                  send you my work.</p>
      <p>And would just suggest one other small thing to you: that if I can sell something in
                  Antwerp or somewhere, I notify you of it, and it’s deducted from the 150
                  francs.</p>
      <p>I don’t write to Rappard about business matters — at least I haven’t told him that
                  latterly I haven’t been on terms with you as in the past. Just think about whether
                  it’s quite in order that you, who know Rappard, have never seen anything of his
                  work, have absolutely no idea what he’s doing — no longer take any notice
                  whatsoever of him, except perhaps by hearsay from me. Yet he’s one of the people
                  who will amount to something — with whom people will have to reckon — of whose
                  work people will have to take notice. At the time Rappard came to you and felt
                  small in your presence, you who knew so much about art. Since that year he was in
                  Paris — how immensely he has progressed — but you — haven’t you rested on your
                  laurels a bit???</p>
   </body>
   <close/>
   <sig/>
</letter>
