<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Saturday, <date>4 April 1885</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I felt as you did, in so far as when you write that the work didn’t yet proceed as
                  usual the very first few days, I had the same experience.</p>
      <p>They have therefore been days that none of us will forget, and yet the overall
                  impression isn’t terrible but only grave. Life isn’t long for anyone, and the
                  question is just — to do something with it.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">The painting went better again today; the first two heads went wrong — today’s is a
                  head of a young girl, almost a child’s head.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="existing">As to colour, it’s a contrast of bright red and pale green against the colour of the
                  little face; there’s already a head like it among those you took with you.</work> I’d
                  like to hear sometime whether those rolledup ones arrived safely.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="finished">If I thought that C.M. meant it when he asked for heads of children, I could send him
                  this one I did today</work>, but..... I can’t say I feel much inclined to enter into
                  correspondence (unless he asks for something more specifically).</p>
      <p>It can do no harm, though, that he’s been to the studio.<work stage="planned" origin="new"> I don’t mind starting a new
                  still life of those honesty heads and dry leaves against blue either, because he
                  said something about that too.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Of course I intend to keep working hard, but it’s very necessary for me to square my
                  paint bill as soon as possible. </stress>Every other year, I’ve been able to get square at
                  about this time and buy myself some new equipment. <stress reason="money">And this year I’ve painted so
                  much the last few months that I actually need it more.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I didn’t want to keep talking about it or contradict you much when you were here —
                  but when you said that I would change some day and, no more than Mauve stayed in
                  Bloemendaal for ever, would I stay here for ever either — maybe — but — I don’t
                  see any advantage myself in moving, because I have a good studio here and the
                  countryside here is very beautiful.Don’t forget that I’m definitely convinced that
                  a painter of peasant life can do no better than follow the example of Barbizon –
                  dwelling and living right in the midst of what one is painting, for it’s new and
                  different outside every day.</p>
      <p>In short, the two reasons for living in the country are that one can do more work and
                  has fewer expenses.</p>
      <p>There are about 3 months, let’s say, between now and the time you come back here in
                  the summer.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">If I work hard day after day, I can have another 20 or so studies for you by then,
                  and moreover another twenty or so to take to Antwerp if you want.</work>
         <stress reason="money">But — it’s very
                  necessary for me to pay off my paint bill as soon as possible.</stress> You know I didn’t
                  say another word to you about it either in February or in March.</p>
      <p>But I didn’t have it easy in those months, I can tell you that.</p>
      <p>It has become colder again here. <work stage="planned" origin="new">As soon as we have a few fine days, I’ll make
                  something of the churchyard.</work>
         <work origin="new" stage="middle">I think the little head I made today is certainly as
                  good as the one you have with a large white cap, which is something like thisAfter
                  ‘this’ (dit) Van Gogh drew a little arrow pointing to the sketches And could serve
                  as a pendant to it.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">If you mount these two on gilded Bristol they might perhaps look good in the gold, do
                  better than by themselves.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Regards, with a handshake, and still thinking often of your visit</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
