<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, Monday, <date>6 July <year>1885</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="money">Thanks for the money,</unstress> your letter and Raffaëlli catalogue. I think the drawings in it
                  are masterly. What he himself also says about ‘character’ is interesting.</p>
      <p>His writing is a mixture of very simple words that come from the heart and from a
                  nervous artistic emotion — they’re moving — and further — of words that I think
                  Raffaëlli himself understands as little as one who has to read them. Thus it is
                  writing full of very fine things and full of mistakes — I would rather read that
                  than anything else. For what he’s talking about is mightily complicated.</p>
      <p>It seems to me, though, that the totality of what he says satisfies — when one has
                  read it — and with all his strange outbursts he nonetheless says something sound
                  and true.</p>
      <p>Theo, you mustn’t think that if I saw Uhde’s painting itself I would lose the
                  impression I got of it. I say again that I believe this man will go the same way
                  as Knaus and Lobrichon — namely that after a few things full of character, the
                  very technique will play a dirty trick on him, that’s to say he’ll start working
                  more and more correctly — and — more and more drily. I find Raffaëlli, say, a
                  painter who stands much higher — than Uhde.</p>
      <p>You don’t hear me having any pessimistic doubts about Lhermitte, do you? So I’m not
                  someone who always doubts. On the contrary, I have a very firm faith in some
                  people. I had never seen anything by Raffaëlli besides those two blacksmiths when
                  I wrote to you about it. Raffaëlli, and above all specifically Lhermitte, though,
                  have what Raffaëlli’s talking about, ‘conscience’. I’m afraid that that’s where
                  Uhde’s weak spot will be. That he’ll no longer know what he wants.</p>
      <p>Anyway. Now you say that Uhde’s silvery grey is so beautiful — and that if I saw the
                  painting I’d think differently about it. No, old chap. I’ve already seen so
                  almighty much grey that I’m not so easily seduced by a bit of silvery grey as I
                  once was. Painting grey as a system is becoming intolerable, and we’ll get the
                  other side of that coin! All the same, to convince you that I want to go on seeing
                  the good in it and am not against it, <work origin="new" stage="middle">I have a grey thing going right now.</work>We’ll —
                  inevitably talk about these things again sometime.</p>
      <p>Don’t forget, though, that although I have certain reservations about Uhde, I said at
                  the outset that I really do think this painting — as far as the main part is
                  concerned, which is 3/4 of the painting — the children — very fine.</p>
      <p>I must get going — didn’t want to wait any longer; am dogtired every day because I’m
                  so far away on the heath.</p>
      <p>I’ve got some more figures.</p>
      <p>I’m sorry about what you write about the money, that you’ll be short yourself.</p>
      <p>Painting is sometimes so damned expensive, and nowadays it just comes down to
                  following one’s own idea at all costs.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">We need an art with strength and vigour, says Raffaëlli, and in achieving this in the
                  figure one has so much difficulty finding models.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>The time has passed, and I’m not complaining about it. Although it’s enough for a
                  figure to be put together conventionally, academically – or actually, although
                  many people want precisely that, there’ll be a reaction nonetheless — and I hope
                  that will stir things up. The artists are calling for character, well — the public
                  will do the same. I assure you that I find Uhde’s Christ extraordinarily
                  unfortunate, it won’t do — the children are good.</p>
      <p>I’m so fond of Lhermitte — Raffaëlli — because it’s thought out through and through,
                  sensible and honest.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="new">I’ve got a few figures here, a woman with a spade seen from behind</work>,<work stage="finished" origin="new"> another one
                  bending over to glean ears of corn</work> — <work stage="finished" origin="new">another one from the front with her head
                  almost on the ground, digging up carrots.</work>
      </p>
      <p>I’ve been spying on these peasant figures here for 1 1/2 years and on their
                  activities, precisely to get some character into it. So I really can’t stand a
                  Santa Claus like Uhde put there in that little school — the little school itself
                  is so fine, though! Uhde himself — well, I wager that he knows it too — and that
                  he did it on account of the fact that the good citizens of that country where he
                  lives desire a ‘subject’ and ‘something conventional to think about’, and
                  otherwise he’d have to starve. <stress reason="career">If I find another moment one of these days when I’m
                  not too tired to write,</stress> I’ll try to tell you how outstandingly good I find some
                  things in Raffaëlli. Regards, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
