<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Antwerp</location>, on or about Thursday, <date>4 February 1886</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <bad_health>I already wrote to you the day before yesterday that on the one hand I was
                far from well,</bad_health>
         <unstress reason="environment">but that on the other hand I nevertheless thought I could
                see some light.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">However, I regret that I have to tell you even more categorically
                that I’m most definitely literally exhausted and overworked.</stress> When you think
            that I went to live in my own studio on 1 May — since then it’s perhaps been a matter of
            6 or 7 times, so far, that I’ve had my midday meal. For good reasons, <stress reason="family">I don’t want you to tell Ma that I’m not well</stress> — because she
            might possibly consider that it wasn’t nice that what happened, happened, that’s to say
            that I didn’t stay there — precisely because of these consequences. I shan’t say
            anything about it; don’t you say anything either. But I lived then, and since then,
            here, <stress reason="money">having nothing for my food because the work cost me too
                much and I relied too much on the idea that I could stick it out like
            this.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>What the doctor tells me is that I absolutely must live better, and that I have to take
            more care of myself with my work until I’m stronger. It’s total debilitation.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Well I’ve made it worse by smoking a lot,</bad_health> which I did all the
            more because then one isn’t troubled by one’s empty stomach.</p>
      <p>Anyway, they say — one has to experience lean times, and I’ve had my share of them.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Because it’s not just the food, it’s also all the worry and sorrow that one
                has.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>You know that for one reason or another the time in Nuenen was far from carefree for me.
            What’s more — here — <unstress reason="environment">I’m very pleased to have come here
            </unstress>— <stress reason="environment">but it’s been a difficult time all the
                same.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">What we have to do and what is largely lacking — is this. Paying
                the models ourselves is too much; as long as one doesn’t have enough money,</stress>
            one must take advantage of the opportunities at the studios, like Verlat, like Cormon.
            And one must be in the artists’ world and work at clubs where one shares the cost of the
            models.</p>
      <p>Now it’s true that I didn’t think of this before, or at least didn’t do it — but I wish
            now that I’d started on it a year earlier. If we could now find some way of living in
            the same city it would be far and away the best thing, at least for the time being.</p>
      <p>Only, the more I think about it, the more and more I fancy that it might be better not to
            spend much on a studio in the first year, because I’ll mostly have to draw in that first
            year.</p>
      <p>Because speaking of Cormon — I imagine he would tell me much the same as Verlat says —
            that I have to draw nudes or plaster casts for up to a year, precisely because I’ve
            always drawn from life.</p>
      <p>This isn’t really a harsh requirement, because I tell you that there are people here
            who’ve been in the class for 3 years and are still not allowed to stop, who also paint.
            In that year I have to practise the male and the female figure, both in detail and as a
            whole, and — then I’ll know it by heart, as it were. Drawing in itself, technically, is
            easy enough for me — I’m beginning to do it the way one writes, with the same ease. But
            precisely at this level it becomes more interesting, as one is not satisfied with the
            facility that one gradually acquires but really looks for originality and breadth of
            conception. Drawing the masses rather than the outlines. Solid modelling. And I can
            assure you it’s not a bad sign if people like Verlat or Cormon, let’s say, demand that
            of someone. For there are enough of them that Verlat simply leaves to get on with it
            because — they just aren’t the fellows for the loftier figure. You talk about the clever
            fellows at Cormon’s studio. Precisely because I damned well want to be one of them, I’m
            setting myself in advance, out of my own conviction, the requirement of spending at
            least a year in Paris mainly drawing from the nude and plaster casts. For the rest,
            let’s do whatsoever our hand finds to do in the way of painting, if an effect out of
            doors strikes us or we happen to have a good model (and);c.</p>
      <p>And don’t think that this is the long way, because it’s the short one. Someone who can
            draw his figures from memory is much more productive than someone who can’t. And by my
            taking the trouble to spend that year drawing — you’ll just see how productive we
            become. And don’t think either that the years I worked out of doors were wasted. For
            it’s the very thing that people who’ve never been anywhere else but at academies and
            studios lack, that view of reality in which they live, and finding subjects. Anyway.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Might it not be wise if we put off renting a studio at least for the first six months,
            precisely because it all comes down to the money? </stress>But otherwise I like the idea of
            setting up a studio a great deal, a very great deal. Even, if need be, such that one
            could combine with other painters to take models together. The more energy the better.
            And in hard times — one must especially seek a way out in friendship and
            collaboration.</p>
      <p>But Theo, it’s so rotten about this indisposition — I’m dreadfully sorry — but I’m still
            in good spirits. It will get better. You understand that it would have got worse and
            worse if I’d delayed doing something about it.</p>
      <p>What I think, though, is this — one mustn’t think that people whose constitution is
            damaged, wholly or half, aren’t fit for painting. It’s desirable for one to make it to
            60 at least, and necessary for one to make it to 50, if one begins when one is around
            30.</p>
      <p>But one absolutely doesn’t have to be perfectly healthy; one may have all sorts of things
            wrong. The work doesn’t always suffer as a result — on the contrary, nervous fellows are
            more sensitive and more refined. But Theo, precisely because it has proved in my case
            that my health leaves something to be desired — I’ve decided to concentrate specifically
            on the loftier figure and to try to refine myself. I<bad_health>t really struck me so unexpectedly —
            I did feel weak and feverish, but I still kept going. Only it began to worry me that
            teeth were breaking off one after another. And that I was starting to look worse and
            worse. Anyway, we’ll see about putting it right.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>I think that getting the teeth attended to will help in itself because, as my mouth was
            usually painful, I just swallowed my food as quickly as possible</bad_health>.</p>
      <p>And perhaps it will also help my appearance, at least a little.</p>
      <p>As regards this month, I’ve paid 25 francs in advance for my room, 30 francs in advance
            for my food, and 50 francs to the dentist; also a visit to the doctor and some drawing
            materials — which leaves 6 francs.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Now the important issue this month is not to be ill, which isn’t easy to resolve — and
            which could very well happen.</bad_health> But we’ll see — I still think I’ve got a certain toughness
            in common with the peasants, who also don’t eat anything very special and still go on
            living and working. So don’t worry too much about it. If you could send a little bit
            extra, very well — but if you can’t, I’ll wait calmly to see how it goes. <bad_health>What I don’t
            like is that I’m feverish, </bad_health>and I reason about it thus: although I may be weakened, I’ve
            still taken some care not to eat any unwholesome food. Overexertion isn’t excessive
            either — because, despite everything, I keep my spirits up all the time — so that it’s
            because I’m weak that I overexert myself. It seems to me that it must sort itself out.
            You understand, though, that if it were to get worse — and took a virulent turn — one
            might have to contend with typhus or at least typhoid fever.</p>
      <p>And actually the only reasons why I certainly don’t expect that are these — 1 that I’ve
            had a great deal of fresh air, and 2 that, as I said, even though I’ve evidently not fed
            myself well enough, as a precaution I’ve nonetheless made do with very simple food
            rather than the muck in the cheap restaurants — and 3 — that I have a degree of calm and
            serenity in the face of things.</p>
      <p>So we must wait and see. Don’t you worry about it, because not even I do — I maintain
            that, supposing I do get a fever, I’ve lived and eaten too simply for it to become very
            virulent all that easily. After all, things don’t happen of their own accord, and
            there’s a reason for everything. Write to me soon, though, because I really do need
            it.</p>
      <p>As regards going to Nuenen too — I want to know what you’d think best.</p>
      <p>But I’m not needed there — because someone like Rijken, the gardener, for instance, can
            see to what needs to be packed or sent at least as well as I can.</p>
      <p>If there’s any point in it, though, I can be ready by March if need be.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Regards, with a handshake.Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent.</sig>
</letter>
