<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Tuesday, <date>14 July 1885</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I wish that the 4 canvases I wrote to you about were gone. I may work on them again
                  if I keep them here too long, and I think it’s better for you to get them as they
                  come from the heath.</p>
      <p>The reason why I don’t send them off is that<stress reason="money"> I don’t want to send them to you with
                  the carriage unpaid at a moment when you say that you might be short yourself, and
                  I can’t pay the carriage myself either.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>I’ve never seen the little house where Millet lived — but I imagine that these 4
                  little human nests are of the same kind.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="finished" origin="existing">One of them is the residence of a gentleman who’s popularly known here as ‘the
                  peasant of Rauwveld’ </work>—<work stage="finished" origin="existing"> the other is occupied by a worthy soul who, when I went
                  there, was engaged in nothing more mysterious than turning over her potato patch,
                  but must also be able to work magic, though — at any rate she goes by the name of
                  ‘the witch’s head’. </work>You remember that it says in the book by Gigoux how it came
                  about that Delacroix had 17 paintings rejected at the same time. This shows — at
                  least so it seems to me — that he and others from that period — were faced with
                  connoisseurs and nonconnoisseurs, none of whom either understood it or wanted to
                  buy — this shows that those who are rightly described in the book as ‘the valiant
                  ones’ didn’t talk about fighting a losing battle, but carried on painting.</p>
      <p>Something else I wanted to say to you is that we’ll have to paint a lot more if we
                  take that about Delacroix as our startingpoint. <stress reason="money">I must necessarily be the most
                  disagreeable of all people, that’s to say having to ask for money.</stress>
         <stress reason="money">And since I
                  don’t think that things will take a turn for the better as regards sales in the
                  next few days, this is bad enough.</stress> But I ask you, isn’t it better, after all, for
                  both of us to work hard even though there are difficulties attached to it, than to
                  sit about philosophizing at a time like this?</p>
      <p>I don’t know the future, Theo — but — I do know the eternal law that everything
                  changes — think back 10 years and things were different, the conditions, the mood
                  of the people, everything in short. And 10 years on, a great deal is bound to have
                  changed again. But doing something endures — and one doesn’t easily regret having
                  done something. The more active the better, and I’d rather fail than sit idle.
                  Whether Portier is or isn’t the man to do something with my work — we need him now
                  all the same. And here’s what I think – after working for a year, say, we’ll have
                  got more together than now, and I know for sure that my work will do better as I
                  complete one thing with another. The people who have some feeling for it now, who,
                  like him, talk about showing it sometime — they’re consequently useful, because
                  after another year’s work, say, they’ll have a few more things together that will
                  speak for themselves, even if they say nothing at all. Should you happen to see
                  Portier, feel free to tell him that, far from giving up, I’m planning to send him
                  much more. You must also go on showing when you meet people. It won’t be so very
                  long before what we can show will be more important. Y<good_health>ou can see for yourself —
                  and it’s a phenomenon that gives me surprisingly great pleasure — that people are
                  increasingly starting to stage exhibitions of 1 person or a very few who belong
                  together.</good_health> This is a phenomenon in the art trade which I dare think has more future
                  than other enterprises. It’s good that people are beginning to understand that a
                  Bouguereau can’t do well beside a Jacque — nor a figure by Beyle or Lhermitte
                  beside a Schelfhout or Koekkoek. </p>
      <p>Scatter Raffaëlli’s drawings about — and judge for yourself whether it would be
                  possible to form a good idea of this singular artist. He — Raffaëlli — isn’t like
                  Régamey — but I find him just as much of a personality. If my work stayed with me
                  — I think I’d be constantly working over it. By sending it to you and to Portier
                  as it comes from the countryside or from the cottages, the odd thing that isn’t
                  right will sometimes get through — but things that wouldn’t be improved by
                  frequently working over them will be preserved.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="existing" stage="finished">If you had these 4 canvases and a few more, smaller studies of cottages,</work> and someone
                  saw nothing by me other than those, they’d be bound to think that I did nothing
                  other than paint cottages. <work stage="finished" origin="existing">And likewise with that series of heads.</work> But peasant
                  life involves such diverse things that when Millet speaks of ‘working like a bunch
                  of negroes’, this really does have to happen if one wants to achieve a whole. One
                  may laugh at Courbet’s saying, ‘painting angels! who has ever seen angels!’ But
                  I’d just like to add, for instance, ‘justices in the harem, who has ever seen
                  justices in the Harem?’ (the painting by BenjaminConstant). ‘Bull fights, who has
                  ever seen those?’ and so many other Moorish, Spanish things, Cardinals, and then
                  all those history paintings, which are still always there, metres high by metres
                  wide! What’s the point of it all, and what do people want with it? After a few
                  years most of it becomes stale and dull, and more and more boring.But still.
                  Perhaps they’re well painted — maybe. Nowadays, when connoisseurs stand in front
                  of a painting like the one by BenjaminConstant, or like a reception at a
                  cardinal’s by some Spaniard or other — it’s the custom to say, with a knowing air,
                  something about ‘clever technique’. But — as soon as those same connoisseurs found
                  themselves in front of a scene from peasant life or a drawing by Raffaëlli, say,
                  they would criticize the technique with the same air — à la C.M.</p>
      <p>Perhaps you think that I’m wrong to comment on this — but — I’m so gripped by the
                  thought that all these exotic paintings are painted in THE STUDIO. But just go and
                  sit outdoors, painting on the spot itself! Then all sorts of things like the
                  following happen — I must have picked a good hundred flies and more off the 4
                  canvases that you’ll be getting, not to mention dust and sand (and);c. — not to
                  mention that, when one carries them across the heath and through hedgerows for a
                  few hours, the odd branch or two scrapes across them . Not to mention that
                  when one arrives on the heath after a couple of hours’ walk in this weather, one
                  is tired and hot. Not to mention that the figures don’t stand still like
                  professional models, and the effects that one wants to capture change as the day
                  wears on.I don’t know how it is with you — but for my part, the more I work on it
                  the more peasant life absorbs me.<unstress reason="career"> And the less and less I care about either the
                  Cabanelesque things, among which I would also count Jacquet, also
                  BenjaminConstant’s present work — or the highly praised but so unspeakably,
                  hopelessly dry technique of the Italians and Spaniards.</unstress> Image makers! — what
                  Jacque said, I often think about it. But I’m not biased; I like Raffaëlli who,
                  after all, paints something very different from peasants — I like Alfred Stevens,
                  Tissot, to mention something that’s entirely unlike peasants — I like a fine
                  portrait. Zola who otherwise, to my mind, often makes colossal mistakes in his
                  judgement of paintings — says something beautiful about art in general in ‘Mes
                  haines’. ‘In the painting (the work of art) I look for, I love the man — the
                  artist.’</p>
      <p>There you are, I think that’s perfectly true — I ask you, what sort of a man, what
                  sort of a visionary/observer or thinker, what sort of a human character is there
                  behind some of these canvases praised for their technique — often, after all,
                  nothing. But a Raffaëlli — is someone, a Lhermitte is someone, and in many
                  paintings by virtually unknown people one feels that they were made with a will,
                  with emotion, with passion, with love. The TECHNIQUE of a painting from peasant
                  life or — like Raffaëlli — from the heart of urban workers — entails difficulties
                  quite different from those of the slick painting and the rendering of action of a
                  Jacquet or BenjaminConstant. That’s to say, living in those cottages day in and
                  day out, being out in the fields just like the peasants — enduring the heat of the
                  sun in the summer, the snow and frost in the winter, not indoors but outside, and
                  not for a walk, but day in and day out like the peasants themselves.</p>
      <p>And I ask you, when you think about it, am I so wrong to criticize the criticism of
                  the connoisseurs, who are presently fencing more busily than ever with the often
                  so meaningless word technique (they’re increasingly giving it a conventional
                  meaning)?</p>
      <p>When one counts all the trudging and lugging one has to do to paint ‘the peasant of
                  Rauwveld’ and his cottage, I dare swear that this is a longer and more tiring
                  expedition than many painters of exotic subjects, be it the justice in the harem
                  or the reception at the cardinal’s, make for their choicest eccentric subjects.
                  For in Paris one can get Arab or Spanish or Moorish models simply by ordering and
                  paying for them. But it’s harder for someone like Raffaëlli, who paints the
                  ragpickers of Paris in their own small quarter, and his work is more serious.</p>
      <p>Seemingly there’s nothing simpler than painting peasants or ragpickers and other
                  labourers but — no subjects in painting are as difficult as those everyday
                  figures!There isn’t — as far as I know — a single academy where one learns to draw
                  and paint a digger, a sower, a woman hanging a pot over the fire, or a seamstress.
                  But in every town of any consequence at all there’s an academy with a choice of
                  models for historical, Arab, Louis XV and, in a word, all figures, provided they
                  don’t exist in reality.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="planned">If I send you and Serret a few studies of diggers or peasant women who are weeding,
                  gleaning corn (and);c. as the start of a whole series about all kinds of work in
                  the fields — then it may be that either Serret or you will discover faults in them
                  which will be useful for me to know about, and which I’ll naturally concede
                  myself.</work> But I want to point out something that’s perhaps worth noting. All
                  academic figures are constructed in the same way and, let’s admit, one couldn’t do
                  better. Impeccable — without faults — you’ll already have seen what I’m driving at
                  — also without giving us anything new to discover. Not so the figures of a Millet,
                  a Lhermitte, a Régamey, a Lhermitte, a Daumier. They’re also well constructed —
                  but not the way the academy teaches, after all. I think that no matter how
                  academically correct a figure may be, it’s REDUNDANT in this day and age, even if
                  it were by Ingres himself (apart from his Source of course, because that indeed
                  was and is and will remain something new) if it lacks that essential modernism —
                  the intimate character, the actual DOING SOMETHING.</p>
      <p>When will the figure not be redundant then, even though there were necessarily faults
                  and grave faults in it to my mind, you’ll probably ask.</p>
      <p>When the digger digs, when the peasant is a peasant, and the peasant woman a peasant
                  woman. Is this something new? Yes. Even the little figures by Ostade, Ter Borch
                  don’t work the way they do nowadays.I’d like to say a lot more about this and I’d
                  like to say how much I myself want to do what I’ve begun even better — and how
                  much higher than my own I value the work of some others. I ask you — do you know
                  of a single digger, a single sower in the old Dutch school??? Did they ever try to
                  make ‘a labourer’? Did Velázquez try it in his watercarrier? Or his folk types?
                  No. Work, that’s what the figures in the old paintings don’t do. <work stage="middle" origin="new">These days I’m
                  slogging away at a woman whom I saw last winter, lifting carrots in the snow.</work>
                  There it is — Millet did it, Lhermitte, and in general the peasant painters of
                  this century — an Israëls — they find that more beautiful than anything else. But
                  even in this century, how relatively few there are among the legion of painters
                  who want the figure — yes — above all — for the sake of the figure (i.e. for the
                  sake of form and modelling) but can’t conceive of it other than working, and also
                  have the need — which the old masters avoided, as did the old Dutch masters who
                  depicted so many conventional actions — and — I say — have the need to paint the
                  action for the action’s sake.</p>
      <p>So that the painting or the drawing is a figure drawing for the sake of the figure
                  and the inexpressibly harmonic form of the human body — yet at the same time — is
                  lifting carrots in the snow. Am I expressing myself clearly? I hope so, and just
                  say this to Serret — I can say it in fewer words — a nude figure by Cabanel, a
                  lady by Jacquet and a peasant woman not by BastienLepage himself, but a peasant
                  woman by a Parisian who learnt to draw at the academy, will always show the limbs
                  and the structure of the body in the same way — sometimes charmingly — correct —
                  in proportion and anatomy. But when Israëls or when Daumier or Lhermitte, say,
                  draw a figure, one will feel the form of the body much more and yet — this is why
                  I particularly want to include Daumier — the proportions will sometimes be almost
                  random, the anatomy and structure often completely wrong ‘in the eyes of the
                  academicians’.</p>
      <p>But it will live. And above all Delacroix, too.</p>
      <p>It still isn’t expressed properly. Tell Serret that I would be desperate if my
                  figures were good, tell him that I don’t want them academically correct. Tell him
                  that I mean that if one photographs a digger, then he would certainly not be
                  digging. Tell him that I think Michelangelo’s figures magnificent, even though the
                  legs are definitely too long — the hips and buttocks too broad. Tell him that in
                  my view Millet and Lhermitte are consequently the true painters, because they
                  don’t paint things as they are, examined drily and analytically, but as they,
                  Millet, Lhermitte, Michelangelo, feel them. Tell him that my great desire is to
                  learn to make such inaccuracies, such variations, reworkings, alterations of the
                  reality, that it might become, very well — lies if you will — but — truer than the
                  literal truth.</p>
      <p>And now I must close soon — I did need, though, just to talk about the fact that
                  those who paint the life of the peasants or the common people, although they
                  aren’t counted among the men of the world — will still, however, perhaps endure
                  better in the long run than the makers of the exotic but painted in Paris harems
                  and cardinals’ receptions.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">I know that it’s being a disagreeable person when one’s in need of money at
                  inconvenient times — but my excuse is just that painting the seemingly most
                  everyday things is sometimes the most difficult and most expensive.The expenses
                  that I must incur if I want to work are sometimes very heavy in relation to my
                  means. I assure you that if my constitution weren’t becoming virtually like that
                  of a peasant as a result of wind and weather, I wouldn’t stick it out, for there’s
                  simply nothing left over for my own comfort. But I don’t desire that for myself
                  either, any more than many peasants desire to live other than as they live. But
                  what I do ask is both for paint and, above all, for models. You’ll perhaps realize
                  from what I say about the figure drawings that I’m positively passionate about
                  going on with them.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>You recently wrote to me that Serret had spoken to you ‘with conviction’ about
                  certain faults in the structure of the figures of the potato eaters. But you’ll
                  have been able to see from my answer that my own criticism also condemns them,
                  considered from that point of view, only I’ve pointed out how this was an
                  impression I had after I’d seen the cottage in the dim lamplight on many evenings,
                  after having painted 40 heads, from which it follows that I was starting from a
                  different point of view. Now we’ve started talking about the figure, though, I
                  have a great deal to say. I find in Raffaëlli’s words, his perception about
                  ‘Character’, what he says about that is good — and in its place — and clarified by
                  the drawings themselves.</p>
      <p>People who move in artistic and literary circles, though, as Raffaëlli does in Paris,
                  think differently after all from, say, the way I do out in the country among the
                  peasants. I mean they search for one word that sums up all their ideas — he
                  suggests the word ‘Character’ for the figures of the future. I agree with it, with
                  the intention — I believe — but I believe as little in the accuracy of the word as
                  in the accuracy of other words — as little as in the accuracy or appositeness of
                  my own expressions.Rather than saying there has to be character in a digger — I
                  describe it by saying this peasant has to be a peasant, this digger has to dig,
                  and then there’s something in it that is essentially modern. But I feel that
                  people can draw conclusions I don’t mean even from these words — even were I to
                  add a whole list.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Instead of reducing the expenses for models — which are already quite a burden on me
                  — I think it would be desirable — very desirable — if I could increase them a
                  little.</stress> Because I’m concerned with something very different from being able to do
                  ‘a little figure’ drawing. Showing the figure of the peasant in action, you see
                  that’s what a figure is — I repeat — essentially modern — the heart of modern art
                  itself — that which neither the Greeks, nor the Renaissance, nor the old Dutch
                  school have done.</p>
      <p>To me, this is a matter I think about every day. However, this difference between
                  both the great and the lesser masters of the present (the great, for instance
                  Millet, Lhermitte, Breton, Herkomer; the lesser, for instance Raffaëlli and
                  Régamey) and the old schools isn’t something I’ve often found expressed truly
                  forthrightly in articles on art.</p>
      <p>Just think about whether you don’t find it’s true, though. The figure of the peasant
                  and the workman started more as a ‘genre’ — but nowadays, with Millet in the van
                  as the eternal master, it’s the very heart of modern art and will remain so.</p>
      <p>People like Daumier — one has to respect them because they’re among the pioneers. The
                  simple nude but modern figure ranks high — as revived by Henner and Lefebvre,
                  Baudry and, above all, the sculptors like a Mercier, Dalou, they’re also among the
                  very soundest. But peasants and labourers simply aren’t nude, and so one doesn’t
                  have to think nude. The more people who start making figures of workmen and
                  peasants the better I’ll like it. <good_health>And I myself, I know of nothing else in which I
                  take so much delight.</good_health> This is a long letter and I still don’t know whether I’ve
                  said what I mean clearly enough. I may perhaps drop Serret a line. If I do, I’ll
                  send the letter to you to read, because I want to make it clear how much I attach
                  to this question of the figure.</p>
   </body>
   <close/>
   <sig/>
</letter>
