<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Monday, <date>17 August 1885</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I’ve heard from that colourman — who tells me I can send the paintings. But that he wants me
      to send them as soon as possible because there are many strangers in The Hague at present.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">He’s quite right there. What I want to ask you is that you try to send me enough for me to
      get the crate made and pay the carriage. Deduct it next month, if you like — but I have
      nothing, and it’s important to me to get my consignment off immediately.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Your visit really left me with a less than favourable impression</bad_health> — I believe more than ever
      that more difficulties await you in the next few years than you imagine.</p>
      <p>I continue to insist that it’s somewhat fatal that your energy has evidently taken a
      different direction, rather than working on our getting our heads above water with the
      painting. And yet it’s such a short while ago that you wrote that you now had more confidence
      that my work was good. You take it as though I was doing you wrong or was hostile to you, now
      I most decidedly have rather a lot of remarks to make. And considerable concerns for the
      future. I can’t speak other than I did, can I?</p>
      <p>To my mind you don’t in the least belong among the rising men now. Take this amiss of me — if
      you will — and treat me as you will accordingly. </p>
      <p>I’m willing to take back my remarks should I see very different things in you, but that I
      made them during your visit — Yes. But even though you say today, ‘I’m selling 500,000 francs’
      worth a year’ — this doesn’t make any impression on me at all, since I’m only too convinced of
      the precariousness of it all — you keeping up even a half or a fifth of that and delivering in
      the years ahead. It’s too up in the air for me, too little at ground level.</p>
      <p>And art itself is solid enough, that’s not the trouble.</p>
      <p>But, ‘to be a countinghouse will pass’ was said, not by me, but by someone whose words came
      dreadfully true. And I wish you were, or would become, a painter. I put it bluntly, more
      strongly than before, because I believe so firmly that the largescale art trade is, in many
      respects, too much like tulip mania.</p>
      <p>And the positions in it dependent on chance and whim. Make a miscalculation — make what may
      be an insignificant mistake — and — what’s left of that huge figure you’re turning over now?
      That figure depends on  whim.</p>
      <p>And KNOWLEDGE of art, stripped bare, is related, more closely than you think, to the practice
      of art. TRADE in paintings is something very different when one is on one’s own from when one
      works for large distributors. And it’s the same with other things, too. Anyway — work hard —
      but — try to work sensibly too.</p>
      <p>The trouble you’ve taken together with me — for providing money is also taking trouble and
      there’s absolutely no getting away from it — this trouble has at least been an act of personal
      initiative, and of personal will and energy — but what am I to think or say of it if, little
      by little, with the decided weakening of the financial aid, something else weren’t to be put
      in its place? And now, above all, to my mind at any rate, it’s the time to try to push ahead
      with my work.</p>
      <p>I’ve also been looking for addresses in Antwerp, and will hear more precisely about them
      before long. Then I can probably send things there, too. But if you want these things, help me
      to bring them about. You said to me yourself, Where there is a will there is a way; well then,
      <stress reason="money">I’ll take you at your word a little as to whether you’re really seeking for us to make
      progress. If I were to ask for extravagant things and you refused, then so be it — but where
      they’re the most essential, the very simplest necessities, and the lack just becomes more and
      more, and worse and worse, then I think you’re taking economy too far, and in this respect
      it’s very far from being useful.</stress>
      </p>
   </body>
   <close>Regards.Yours truly,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>Just a word about Serret and about Portier.<stress reason="money"> Tell them as it is, that is that I did have
      studies ready, but that I had to pay a colourman who was making it difficult for me just now.</stress>
      That in order to put a stop to it, I wrote to tell him that I put his paint in my studies, and
      that I asked him to take the trouble to sell something for me instead of nagging. That I’ll go
      through with it, and have to send him things.</p>
      <p>That as to the drawings which I said I’d show Serret, since I’m in a hurry to do things, I
      need them myself. But I do still think it’s of some importance that at any rate he knows that
      I really did have them when you came, and that you tell him that you saw them at my place, and
      then also tell him exactly what you think. I won’t influence your own opinion. That I’m sad
      about your thinking that this is all right, though, yes — that is so.</p>
      <p>But I don’t refuse to take such measures — and even if one of these colourmen wanted to sell
      off my bits and pieces, he would be welcome to go to those lengths. It’s certain that the
      paintdealing gentlemen wouldn’t blush to do it.</p>
      <p>However, I’m fed up with talking about it; I’ve said what I had to say — and you — you can
      deal with my suggestion as you see fit. </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">And if these fellows want to attack me and sell me up, since they expressly threatened me
      with collection, and that over matters of less than 30 guilders, then I won’t be able to
      resist them and will let them do as they please, but it will be as if it happens before your
      very eyes, since you’ve just been here.</stress> That I can’t stop the work at the level I now am,
      that’s true. <stress reason="career">I need paint every day. I must make progress,</stress> and <stress reason="money">if I want to pay for
      what I need today, then an outstanding bill from yesterday will have to wait.</stress> For your
      information, this is how it is with me for the rest of the year, precisely and in detail — <stress reason="money">I
      have to pay:three suppliers who are all pestering me, one 45 guilders, the other 25 guilders, the other
      30 guilders. These are the exact sums outstanding on accounts which have of course been much
      higher over the course of the year, but which I pay off in cash, as much as I possibly can
      with the utmost effort.deficit therefore 100 guilders</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">Add to this rent in November 25 ,, _________ 125 guilders = 250 francs</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Suppose I get 4 x 150 francs from you for Sept. Oct. Nov. Dec.= 600 francs. That then leaves
      350 francs to last from now until New Year. And then bear in mind that I have literally
      nothing left this month, and that I also have to live this month.</p>
      <p>So that from Aug. – 1 January, in other words almost 5 months, I have to live and paint on
      350 francs. Which I can do on 150 francs a month, but not easily, but anyway it’s possible as
      a minimum.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">However, if in the course of 4 months 250 francs has to be deducted to pay for paint and
      rent, well then, the work is hampered and obstructed so much that one doesn’t know what to do,
      and would rather say to the fellows sell my things then!</stress>
         <stress reason="career">But let me work! Without hesitation
      I’ve just thrown this month in to calm the fellows down. But the hardship that’s caused is bad
      enough.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>And my last word on the subject is that if my work were weak and awful, I would agree with
      you if you said — ‘I can’t do anything about it’.</p>
      <p>Well — since larger and smaller painted studies as well as new drawings were able to make you
      understand that we’re making progress with it, I’m not so sure whether ‘I can’t do anything
      about it’ should be your final word. Talk to Serret, talk to Portier about it — and say how
      much I want to keep working and how little opportunity I have myself to find art lovers, since
      painting the peasants means that once and for all the countryside, not the city is my place of
      work.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
