<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Thursday, <date>28 May <year>1885</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="environment">I’ve just received Germinal, which I started on immediately. I’ve read 50 pages of it
                  — which I think splendid.</unstress> I also walked there once.Here’s a croquis of a head that
                  I just brought back. You received the same one in the last studies I sent, the
                  largest one among them, but painted smoothly.</p>
      <p>
         <work origin="new" stage="finished">This time I haven’t smoothed out the brushstroke, and besides the colour is very
                  different too. I haven’t yet made a head that’s so much painted with the soil, and
                  more will certainly follow now.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">If all goes well — if I earn rather more so that I can travel more</stress> — well then I’ll
                  also, <work stage="planned" origin="new">I hope, paint the miners’ heads sometime.</work> However, I’ll keep working until
                  I’m absolutely and utterly sure of my case — such that I’m working even faster
                  than now and will also be able to bring home 30 or so studies in the space of a
                  month, say.</p>
      <p>
         <good_health>I don’t know whether we’ll earn money, but if it’s just enough to work a tremendous
                  amount then I’m content; doing what one wants is what matters.</good_health>
      </p>
      <p>Yes, we must do the miners one day!What did Portier say about the potato eaters? I
                  know myself that there are flaws in it; all the same, precisely because I see that
                  the heads I’m doing now are becoming more powerful, <work origin="new" stage="planned">I dare assert that the potato
                  eaters will also hold up in association with subsequent paintings.</work>
      </p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="career">Last year I was often desperate about colour, but now I’m working much more
                  confidently.</unstress> You must just write and tell me what you think best; whether I should
                  keep the work I’m doing now for Antwerp or that I send it to you and Portier as
                  soon as possible. Because it’s all the same to me. I have <work stage="finished" origin="new">7 heads</work> and <work origin="new" stage="finished">1
                  watercolour</work> ready now, so I could make another small consignment. Regards, thanks
                  again for Germinal, I’m still reading it as I write. It’s splendid.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
