<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Antwerp</location>, on or about Tuesday, <date>9 February <year>1886</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I have to write to you one more time because the sooner we can take an outright decision
            the better. As regards a studio — if we could find, in one and the same house, a room
            with an alcove and also a garret or a corner attic — then you could have that apartment
            of room and alcove, and we could make it just as comfortable as possible. And during the
            day the room could serve as studio, and the garret could serve for various more
            unsightly tools or for dirty work, and I could also sleep there — and you in the studio
            alcove.</p>
      <p>It seems to me that such an arrangement or something similar would be perfectly
            satisfactory for the first year. <stress reason="family">What I’m not sure about is whether we’ll get on
            personally, although I don’t despair of it — but it’ll be much more agreeable for you to
            come home to a workplace than to an ordinary room, which always has something gloomy
            about it. And it’s that gloom that’s our worst enemy.</stress> When the doctor tells me that I
            have to take better care of myself, physically — well, who knows whether such a measure
            mightn’t do you good too. <bad_health>For you’re also neither happy nor in good spirits — let’s not
            mince words, you have too much worry and too little prosperity.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>But perhaps it’s because of our policy that we’re each too much alone and our forces and
            resources are too divided, and in that form insufficient. So — unity is strength — would
            certainly be much better.</p>
      <p>So there has to be more life, it seems to me, and we have to throw out all sorts of
            doubts and a certain lack of confidence.</p>
      <p>Do you want a reason on which one can rely to preserve one’s serenity, even when one
            stands alone and isn’t understood and one’s material wellbeing has gone by the board?
            Well there’s still this — I believe — one feels instinctively that a tremendous amount
            is changing, and everything will change. <stress reason="environment">We’re in the last quarter of a century that
            will end with another colossal revolution.But suppose we both yet see the beginning of
            it at the end of our lives.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>We’ll certainly not experience the better times of clear air and refreshment of the whole
            of society after those great storms. All the same, it’s something not to be taken in by
            the falseness of one’s time, in so far as one detects in it the unhealthy closeness and
            mugginess of the hours that precede the thunderstorm.</p>
      <p>And says — it’s oppressive for us — but the next generations will be able to breathe more
            freely. Men like Zola and the De Goncourts believe in it with the simplicity of
            overgrown children. They, the most rigorous analysts — whose diagnosis is both so
            merciless and so accurate.</p>
      <p>And particularly the one you mentioned, Turgenev, and Daudet — they don’t work without a
            goal or without looking towards the other side.</p>
      <p>Only they all, and rightly, avoid prophesying utopias and are pessimists in so far as if
            one analyzes, one sees so terribly in the history of this century the way the
            revolutions fail, no matter how nobly they begin.</p>
      <p>You see, where one gets support is when one doesn’t always have to walk alone with one’s
            feelings and thoughts, when one works and thinks in a group of people together. Then at
            the same time one can do more — and one is infinitely happier.</p>
      <p>Well I’d already wanted to have that between us for a long time, and you see, I imagine
            that if you stayed on your own you’d become depressed because the times aren’t
            encouraging unless one finds satisfaction in one’s work. I’m sending you that novel by
            De Goncourt specifically for the introduction above all — which contains a résumé of
            their works and aims.</p>
      <p>Y<bad_health>ou’ll see that these fellows haven’t been precisely happy, in the same way as Delacroix
            said about himself, I haven’t been happy at all in the sense in which I understood it /
            wanted it in the past</bad_health>.</p>
      <p>Well, whether or not it comes soon — a moment will come for you, too, when you’ll be sure
            that material wellbeing has gone by the board, fatally and irrevocably. I’d safely dare
            say that, but adding this, that I think that at that same moment there will be a certain
            compensation of feeling a capacity for work.</p>
      <p>What touches me is the magnificent serenity of the great thinkers of the present day,
            like, say, the last walk of the two De Goncourts, which you’ll find described. The last
            days of the ageing Turgenev were like that, too — he was with Daudet a great deal then.
            Sensitive, subtle, intelligent as women, sensitive to their own suffering, too, and
            always still full of life and selfassurance, no indifferent stoicism, no contempt for
            life — I say again, those fellows, they die like women die. No idée fixe about God or
            abstractions — always on the ground floor of life itself and attached only to that,
            again, like women who have loved much — touched and — as Silvestre says of Delacroix —
            thus died, almost smiling.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, we haven’t yet reached that point, on the contrary we’re at the point of
            working first, living first — most likely with the normal kind of wellbeing going by the
            board. But whatever the future may be, you can be sure that I’d be very pleased indeed
            if I could work with Cormon for a year or so, unless there’s somewhere better for
            drawing in L’Ecole des BeauxArts or other studios I’ve heard about here.</p>
      <p>The ancients won’t prevent us from being realistic, come on — on the contrary. Of course
            I’m also desperately longing for French paintings.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="love">Apropos, don’t you like this?Everything that is bad came from woman — Clouded Reason, an
            appetite for lucre, betrayal Golden cups in which wines are mixed with lees. Every
            crime, every happy lie, every kind of madness</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Comes from her..... Adore her none the less, since the gods Made her... and — she is the
            best thing that they have made. After all, working has the secret of being able to give
            someone a second youth.</p>
      <p>Tell me, have you ever read anything by Carlyle? Actually that’s not necessary when one
            sees the fellow’s face and knows his work is something like Michelet. Whistler and
            Legros have both made his portrait. That’s another one who dared a great deal and had a
            different insight on many things from the rest. But the more I look into it, always the
            same story — lack of money, poor health, opposition, isolation, in short, trouble from
            beginning to end.</p>
      <p>Mantz’s piece about Paul Baudry was very good, and I found that ‘he worked on the renewal
            of the smile’ particularly singular.</p>
      <p>Could one say of Delacroix ‘he worked on the renewal of passion’? Perhaps so. Anyway — do
            write soon in any event, and regards.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
