<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Antwerp</location>, on or about Thursday, <date>11 February <year>1886</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <stress reason="family">I definitely need to tell you that it would reassure me greatly if you were to approve my
            coming to Paris much earlier than June or July if need be. The more I think about it,
            the more desirable this appears to me.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>Consider that if everything goes well and if I had good food throughout that
            time, which will certainly not be plain sailing, consider that even in that case it will
            take 6 months or so before I’m entirely well.</p>
      <p>But it would certainly take even longer if things were to be the same for me in Brabant
            from March to July as they’ve been for the past few months, and it’s likely they’d be no
            different.</p>
      <p>
         <bad_health>Now at the moment it’s just because of reaction to overexertion that I feel terribly
            weak, in fact even worse. Still, that’s the natural course of things and nothing
            unusual.</bad_health>
      </p>
      <p>But where the issue is — to take better care of oneself —<stress reason="money"> well in Brabant I’d wear myself
            out again taking models, the same old story would start all over again, and it doesn’t
            seem to me that any good could come of it.</stress> That way — we’d be straying from the path. So
            please give me permission to come sooner if need be. In fact I’d say right away, if need
            be. If I take a garret in Paris, bring my painting box and drawing materials with me —
            then as far as the work’s concerned I can finish the most pressing things at once —
            those studies of plaster casts that will certainly help me when I go to Cormon’s. <work origin="new" stage="planned">I can
            go and draw either in the Louvre or in L’Ecole des BeauxArts.</work>
      </p>
      <p>For the rest, we could then also think about it and discuss it so much better before we
            go about setting ourselves up somewhere else.</p>
      <p>Know that I don’t mind going to Nuenen in the month of March if need be and seeing how
            things are there, and how the people are, and whether or not I can get models.</p>
      <p>But if that doesn’t work out, which is likely, then after March I could come straight to
            Paris and start drawing, in the Louvre, for instance. I’ve given a lot of thought to
            what you wrote about taking a studio — but it seems to me that it would be a good thing
            if we were to look for it together and that before we start living together permanently
            — did it for a while — provisionally — and I started by renting a garret at the
            beginning of April, say, until June. Then I’ll be more accustomed to Paris again by the
            time I go to Cormon’s. </p>
      <p>And — I think this way I’ll remain more cheerful. I also have to tell you that although I
            still go there — <stress reason="friendship">it’s often insupportable for me, the carping of the fellows at the
            academy, for it has proved that they’re still spiteful.</stress> However, I make a point of
            avoiding any quarrel, and go my own way. And I think I’m getting on the track of what
            I’m looking for, and perhaps I might find it even sooner if I were to sit in front of
            the plaster casts entirely on my own. All the same, I’m glad I went to the academy, if
            only because I have ample opportunity to observe the results of starting from the
            outline, because they do that systematically and they pick petty quarrels with me about
            it. Make an outline first — your outline isn’t right — I won’t correct that if you model
            before having conscientiously finished your outline. You see, it all comes down to that.
            And you really should see!!! how flat, how dead and how bloody boring the results of
            that system are. Oh, I tell you, I’m very glad to have seen it properly at close
            quarters — David or even worse — Pieneman in full bloom. I must have wanted to say at
            least twentyfive times — your outline’s just a trick — but I haven’t thought it
            worthwhile arguing. All the same, even though I don’t say anything, I irritate them —
            and they me.</p>
      <p>This doesn’t matter so much, though — the issue is to really go on trying to find a
            better system of working. So, patience and perseverance.</p>
      <p>They go so far as to say — colour and modelling, that’s nothing, one learns that very
            quickly — it’s the outline that’s the essential thing and the most difficult. You see,
            one can learn something new at the academy — I never knew before that colour and
            modelling came of their own accord. <work origin="new" stage="finished">Just yesterday I finished a drawing that I’ve made
            for the competition in the evening class. It’s the Germanicus figure that you know.</work> Very
            well — I know for sure that I’ll certainly come last, because all the drawings by the
            others are the same, and mine is completely different. But I saw the drawing that will
            be considered to be the best being done — I was sitting just behind — and it’s correct,
            it’s anything you like, but it’s dead and so are all those drawings that I saw.</p>
      <p>Enough about this — just let it bore us so much that we become enthusiastic about
            something nobler. And that we make haste to achieve it.</p>
      <p>You also need to take better care of yourself, and should we succeed in uniting, the two
            of us would know more than each one individually, and could do more.</p>
      <p>Tell me, did you notice that subtle remark of Paul Mantz’s — women are perhaps the
            supreme difficulty in life — it was in the article on Baudry? We’ll certainly experience
            our share of that, aside from what we may already have experienced. It struck me in a
            chapter from Zola’s L’oeuvre in Gil Blas — that the painter — Manet, of course — had a
            scene with a woman who had posed for him and had then cooled to the idea; oh curiously
            well described. What one can learn at the academy in this regard is — just don’t paint
            women then. They hardly ever use nude female models, not at all in class at any rate —
            very occasionally individually.</p>
      <p>Even in the plaster cast class, 10 male figures as against 1 female figure. That’s nice
            and easy.</p>
      <p>That must surely be better in Paris — and it occurs to me that one actually learns so
            much by constantly comparing male and female, which are always so very different in
            everything. It may be the supreme difficulty, but what would art and what would life be
            without that? Regards, write back about this soon, with a handshake.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Yours truly,</close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>My being in Nuenen, at least for the month of March, would be because of the move, and I
            ought to go there for myself because of changing my abode. But if need be, as far as I’m
            concerned, I’d be prepared not to go back at all.</p>
   </ps>
</letter>
