<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Tuesday, <date>9 June <year>1885</year></date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>
         <work origin="existing" stage="finished">Today I sent off that little crate, containing 1 other painting, Peasant cemetery,
                  besides what I already told you.</work>
      </p>
      <p>I’ve left out some details — I wanted to say how this ruin shows that for centuries
                  the peasants have been laid to rest there in the very fields that they grubbed up
                  in life — I wanted to say how perfectly simply death and burial happen, coolly as
                  the falling of an autumn leaf — no more than a bit of earth turned over — a little
                  wooden cross. The fields around — where the grass of the churchyard ends, beyond
                  the little wall, they make a last fine line against the horizon — like the horizon
                  of a sea. And now this ruin says to me how a faith and religion mouldered away,
                  although it was solidly founded — how, though, the life and death of the peasants
                  is and will always be the same, springing up and withering regularly like the
                  grass and the flowers that grow there in that churchyard. Victor Hugo, whom
                  they’ve also just buried, said Religions pass, God remains.I don’t know whether
                  you’ll see anything in these two things — the cottage with the mossy roof reminded
                  me of a wren’s nest. Anyway, you must just look at them.</p>
      <p>Now I must take this opportunity of explaining to you again — which I found new,
                  clear words for — why I wrote and write to you that I’m still far from sure
                  whether your present view is your definite conviction. The firm of G(and)Cie
                  isn’t a good school for getting to know paintings, let alone painters. I tell you
                  this as my opinion — that one doesn’t even learn how to look independently
                  there.</p>
      <p>Who did they greatly honour? Paul Delaroche. I don’t have to tell you how Delaroche
                  was one of the people who really didn’t stand up to scrutiny — there’s simply no
                  one left who takes his part.</p>
      <p>Someone else who won’t stand up to scrutiny — even though he’s better — although he
                  did make something very fine once or twice — who will also fail — that is —
                  Gérôme.His Prisoner, though, his Syrian shepherd are felt, and I think them as
                  fine as anybody, and readily and willingly.</p>
      <p>But by far the most often he’s a Delaroche II. Each of them, taking into account the
                  context of their age, is of equal worth. What I’m now asserting is — that I
                  consider it highly likely that the whole situation will bore you more by the
                  year.</p>
      <p>What I further assert is that one does both others and especially oneself too a
                  disservice by being bored. In spite of many wise lessons, I’ve never seriously
                  granted that being bored ‘for one’s own good’ can have its good, practical side.
                  Now a MASS of people have reformed themselves at the age of about 30 and changed
                  very considerably.</p>
      <p>Just think calmly about this — I tell you that nothing of what I learnt and heard
                  about art at G(and)Cie stood up to scrutiny. How if one reverses the generalities
                  that count there as the conversation killers in judging art — namely praising the
                  old or presentday Delaroche to the skies and discrediting the unorthodox — if, I
                  say, one reverses certain maxims, then — one takes a breath of fresh air. In short
                  — old chap — such curious turns in situations and affairs are possible — not only
                  that — but even the rule. It’s funny, isn’t it — that, after all, I still doubt
                  whether you’ll stay in the trade.</p>
      <p>You don’t have to take any notice of this or reply to it — I say it to you just to
                  express my idea frankly, not to start futile exchanges of words.</p>
      <p>But it’s — an enchanted land — where one isn’t free.</p>
      <p>Anyway — I’ll hear sometime whether you’ve received the little crate and whether you
                  find anything in it.</p>
      <p>
         <work stage="planned" origin="new">Tomorrow I’m going to paint a thing in another village — also a cottage — in a
                  smaller size.</work>
         <unstress reason="environment">I found it last Sunday on a long trip I made in the company of a
                  peasant boy — in order to get hold of a wren’s nest. We found 6; without doubt it
                  was a place that Bodmer would have adored. And they were all nests from which the
                  young had already flown, so that one could take them without too many pangs of
                  conscience. It was so real; I also have some other splendid nests.</unstress> Regards, write
                  soon, with a handshake.Yours truly,</p>
   </body>
   <close/>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
   <ps>
      <p>I’d like you to give both the paintings a varnish before you show them to Portier or
                  Serret.</p>
      <p>The peasant cemetery has sunk in particularly badly, because it was very different on
                  the canvas at first and I scraped the first thing off completely. It was a total
                  failure at first — then I gave it short shrift and started from the beginning,
                  went and sat on another side and painted early in the morning instead of in the
                  evening. Well, and the other — the one of the cottage — was originally a shepherd.
                  The sheep were shorn last week; I saw it — on a table in a barn.</p>
      <p>I’m glad that this time I can show Portier something very different again. <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’m busy
                  drawing, by the way, so as to send a few fulllength figures in a little while.</work>
         <work stage="planned" origin="new">But
                  working on the cottages — perhaps you’ll say imitations of Michel, although they
                  aren’t — and searching for subjects, I’ve found such splendid cottages that I now
                  really must go bird’s nesting with a number of variations of these ‘people’s
                  nests’, which remind me so much of the nests of wrens — that’s to say, paint
                  them.</work>
      </p>
      <p>Oh — one mustn’t doubt — anyone who paints the peasants nowadays and has his heart in
                  his work, he wins — at least a part, and not the worst although it’s not the
                  largest — of the public.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="money">This doesn’t alter the fact that my end or second half of the month — can still work
                  out remarkably meagre. But the same happens to the peasant lads too, and — they
                  still have fun.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <good_health>I wish you’d been here on Sunday when we went on that trip. I came back covered in
                  mud because we had to spend a good half hour wading through a stream. But for me
                  painting is now becoming as stimulating and enticing as hunting — it is a hunt,
                  after all, for models, and beautiful places too.</good_health> Regards again, and best wishes to
                  you. It’s already late and I have to be at the place at 5 o’clock, so — adieu.
            </p>
   </ps>
</letter>
