<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
   <head>
      <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Tuesday, <date>17 November 1885</date>.</head>
   <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
   <body>
      <p>I’ll tell you in a few words what Van de Loo said about Ma. He says</p>
      <p>1) that there’s nothing wrong with her</p>
      <p>2) that she can live for another 10 years or so</p>
      <p>3) that if she dies before that time, then she would have to have contracted some
                  disease or other.</p>
      <p>Lastly, he seemed to find it very natural that she was sometimes a little bit dazed,
                  and didn’t make anything of it.</p>
      <p>So she can do whatever she likes and doesn’t have to feel awkward about travelling or
                  moving house.</p>
      <p>
         <unstress reason="family">So much the better, then. In any event it’s reassuring. Because for my part I believe
                  what he says, and with the good care that Ma gets thanks to Wil there’s little
                  chance of ‘contracting some disease or other’.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>Wanted to let you know straightaway. It’s reassuring for me, too.I’m really looking
                  forward to Antwerp now. The first thing I’ll do there will probably be to go and
                  see Leys’s paintings in his dining room, if one can see them. You know, that Walk
                  on the ramparts and the one that Bracquemond etched, The table, The servant.</p>
      <p>I imagine that it’ll be beautiful there in the winter, too, with snow on the docks.
                  Obviously I’ll take a few paintings with me, and they’ll be the ones that I would
                  otherwise have sent to you in the next few days.</p>
      <p>A large mill on the heath in the evening, and a view of the village behind a row of
                  poplars with yellow leaves, a still life and a number of drawings of figures.</p>
      <p>I’m at something of a stand with the work here at present. It’s freezing hard, so
                  it’s no longer possible to work outdoors. It’s better if I just don’t use any more
                  models as long as I’m living in this house; at any rate not until I come back.
                  Besides, I’m saving my paint and canvas so as to have ammunition there.<stress reason="environment">SO THE
                  SOONER I CAN GET AWAY, THE BETTER.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">I recently received a letter from Leurs about my paintings. He wrote that Tersteeg
                  and Wisselingh had seen them and thought them ‘not suitable for them’.</stress>
      </p>
      <p>All the same, I maintain that I’ll make people change their minds — even if Tersteeg
                  and Wisselingh don’t want to.</p>
      <p>I’ve just read a few books in the style of Gigoux’s Souvenirs, which my friend in
                  Eindhoven had sent for, in which I found some very interesting things about the
                  fellows of those days, starting with Paul Huet. <unstress reason="career">And which give me confidence that
                  I haven’t tackled nature the wrong way, nor the technique of painting, although I
                  freely admit that I will and must still change.</unstress>
      </p>
      <p>There you have those heads that are with you, there must be good ones among them, I’m
                  as good as certain of it. So — let’s go.</p>
      <p>I don’t think this winter will be dull. It’s obvious that it’ll mainly be a question
                  of working hard. But there’s something singular in the very idea that one has to
                  take the plunge.</p>
      <p>I’m taking a stock of the paint that I can easily get ground here myself — but it’ll
                  help me if I can find a few more colours in a better quality there. I’m also
                  taking at least 40 stretching frames the same size as those studies of heads that
                  are with you. And drawing materials and paper so that, however I get on, I’ll
                  always be able to do something. Because I’ve worked entirely alone for years, I
                  imagine that although I will and although I can learn from others and even adopt
                  technical things — all the same I’ll always see through my own eyes and tackle
                  things originally.</p>
      <p>However, nothing could be surer than that I’ll try to learn more things. And if I can
                  — particularly the nude figure. <stress reason="money">I imagine, though, that in order to get models, as
                  many as I want and good, I won’t be done all at once, but will have to find the
                  money for it by making other things.</stress> Be it landscapes, be it townscapes, be it
                  portraits, as I said — or — even if it were signboards and decoration. Or —
                  something I didn’t mention in my last letter among the things that I could do ‘on
                  the side’ — give lessons in painting, letting them begin by painting still lifes —
                  which I believe is a different method from that of the drawing masters. I’ve tried
                  it out on those friends of mine in Eindhoven, and I’d dare repeat it.</p>
      <p>I’ll certainly leave immediately, as soon as I get the monthly allowance from you.
                  And as to that, should you by chance be in a position to send it a week earlier,
                  I’d leave a week earlier. It goes without saying, though, that I’m not counting on
                  it. I’m glad that I went to see the museum in Amsterdam once more before this,
                  because I’ve seen from the work since that what I saw there has been useful to me.
                  Write soon if you have time. I wanted to tell you Van de Loo’s opinion of Ma
                  straightaway.Since I’m already busy packing up my things, it goes without saying
                  that my thoughts are more there than here.</p>
      <p>
         <stress reason="career">Here I’ve just kept on ceaselessly painting in order to learn painting, to get firm
                  ideas about colour, without leaving much room in my head for other
                  things.</stress>
         <unstress reason="environment">But when I escaped to Amsterdam for a few days, I was really delighted to
                  see paintings once again.</unstress> For it’s sometimes damned hard to be entirely away from
                  paintings and the world of painters and not to see anything by other people. Since
                  then I’ve had quite a yearning to get back into it, at least for a while.</p>
      <p>If one’s entirely out of it for a couple of years and wrestles with nature, that can
                  sometimes help, and at the same time one perhaps gets a new stock of confidence
                  and health out of it, which one can under no circumstances have too much of,
                  though, because the painter’s life is often harsh enough.As regards my work, I’ll
                  have to act according to circumstances, I mean, if I could perhaps make the
                  acquaintance of an art buyer and persuade him to show some of my things. But
                  tomorrow doesn’t mean never, and you’ll soon see something of it, particularly if
                  I succeed in making new studies of heads or figures. <work origin="existing" stage="finished">The one landscape I’m taking
                  with me — and possibly both — but the one with the yellow leaves:</work> I think you’d
                  like it too. I enclose a quick croquis of it.</p>
      <p>The horizon is a dark line against a light line of sky in white and blue. In this
                  dark line little flecks of red, bluish and green or brown, forming the silhouette
                  of the roofs and orchards, the field greenish. The sky higher up, grey, against it
                  the black trunks and yellow leaves. Foreground completely covered with fallen
                  yellow leaves, in which 2 little black figures and one blue. On the right a birch
                  trunk, white and black, and a green trunk with redbrown leaves.</p>
   </body>
   <close>Regards, with a handshake.Yours truly, </close>
   <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
